{"analogies":[{"question":"Odometer is to mileage as compass is to","options":{"A":"speed","B":"hiking","C":"needle","D":"direction"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"direction"},{"question":"Marathon is to race as hibernation is to","options":{"A":"winter","B":"bear","C":"dream","D":"sleep"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"sleep"},{"question":"Window is to pane as book is to","options":{"A":"novel","B":"glass","C":"cover","D":"page"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"page"},{"question":"Cup is to coffee as bowl is to","options":{"A":"dish","B":"soup","C":"spoon","D":"food"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"soup"},{"question":"Yard is to inch as quart is to","options":{"A":"gallon","B":"ounce","C":"milk","D":"liquid"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"ounce"},{"question":"Elated is to despondent as enlightened is to","options":{"A":"aware","B":"ignorant","C":"miserable","D":"tolerant"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"ignorant"},{"question":"Optimist is to cheerful as pessimist is to","options":{"A":"gloomy","B":"mean","C":"petty","D":"helpful"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"gloomy"},{"question":"Reptile is to lizard as flower is to","options":{"A":"petal","B":"stem","C":"daisy","D":"alligator"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"daisy"},{"question":"Play is to actor as concert is to","options":{"A":"symphony","B":"musician","C":"piano","D":"percussion"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"musician"},{"question":"Sponge is to porous as rubber is to","options":{"A":"massive","B":"solid","C":"elastic","D":"inflexible"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"elastic"},{"question":"Careful is to cautious as boastful is to","options":{"A":"arrogant","B":"humble","C":"joyful","D":"suspicious"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"arrogant"},{"question":"Pen is to poet as needle is to","options":{"A":"thread","B":"button","C":"sewing","D":"tailor"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"tailor"},{"question":"Secretly is to openly as silently is to","options":{"A":"scarcely","B":"impolitely","C":"noisily","D":"quietly"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"noisily"},{"question":"Embarrassed is to humiliated as frightened is to","options":{"A":"terrified","B":"agitated","C":"courageous","D":"reckless"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"terrified"},{"question":"Pride is to lion as shoal is to","options":{"A":"teacher","B":"student","C":"self-respect","D":"fish"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"fish"},{"question":"Artist is to painting as senator is to","options":{"A":"attorney","B":"law","C":"politician","D":"constituents"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"law"},{"question":"Exercise is to gym as eating is to","options":{"A":"food","B":"dieting","C":"fitness","D":"restaurant"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"restaurant"},{"question":"Candid is to indirect as honest is to","options":{"A":"frank","B":"wicked","C":"truthful","D":"untruthful"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"untruthful"},{"question":"Guide is to direct as reduce is to","options":{"A":"decrease","B":"maintain","C":"increase","D":"preserve"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"decrease"},{"question":"Oar is to rowboat as foot is to","options":{"A":"running","B":"sneaker","C":"skateboard","D":"jumping"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"skateboard"},{"question":"","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"1"},{"question":"","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"4"},{"question":"","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"1"},{"question":"","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"2"},{"question":"","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"1"},{"question":"","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"4"},{"question":"","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"3"},{"question":"","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"3"},{"question":"","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"3"},{"question":"","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"3"},{"question":"","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"1"},{"question":"","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"4"},{"question":"","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"4"},{"question":"","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"3"},{"question":"","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"2"},{"question":"","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"2"},{"question":"","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"2"},{"question":"","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"1"},{"question":"","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"2"},{"question":"","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"2"},{"question":"","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"3"},{"question":"","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"4"},{"question":"","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"3"},{"question":"","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"4"},{"question":"","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"1"},{"question":"","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"2"},{"question":"","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"1"},{"question":"","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"3"},{"question":"","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"1"},{"question":"","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"2"},{"question":"","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"4"},{"question":"","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"2"},{"question":"","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"1"},{"question":"","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"4"},{"question":"","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"3"},{"question":"","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"3"},{"question":"","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"2"},{"question":"","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"4"},{"question":"    candle    lamp    floodlight    hut    cottage    ?","options":{"A":"tent","B":"city","C":"dwelling","D":"house"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"house"},{"question":"    daisy    flower    plant    bungalow    house    ?","options":{"A":"building","B":"cottage","C":"apartment","D":"city"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"building"},{"question":"    palette    easel    brush    textbook    lesson plan    ?","options":{"A":"artist","B":"teacher","C":"reportcard","D":"paint"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"reportcard"},{"question":"    rule    command    dictate    doze    sleep    ?","options":{"A":"snore","B":"govern","C":"awaken","D":"hibernate"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"hibernate"},{"question":"    apples    fruit    supermarket    novel    book    ?","options":{"A":"bookstore","B":"magazine","C":"vegetable","D":"shopping"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"bookstore"},{"question":"    ant    fly    bee    hamster    squirrel    ?","options":{"A":"spider","B":"mouse","C":"rodent","D":"cat"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"mouse"},{"question":"    carpenter    saw    nails    pediatrician    stethoscope    ?","options":{"A":"thermometer","B":"baby","C":"doctor","D":"illness"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"thermometer"},{"question":"    tadpole    frog    amphibian    lamb    sheep    ?","options":{"A":"animal","B":"wool","C":"farm","D":"mammal"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"mammal"},{"question":"    table    wood    oak    shirt    cloth    ?","options":{"A":"sewing","B":"dress","C":"cotton","D":"tree"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"cotton"},{"question":"    snow    mountain    ski    warmth    lake    ?","options":{"A":"sand","B":"swim","C":"sunburn","D":"vacation"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"swim"},{"question":"    walk    skip    run    toss    pitch    ?","options":{"A":"swerve","B":"hurl","C":"jump","D":"dance"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"hurl"},{"question":"    meal    banquet    feast    shelter    palace    ?","options":{"A":"mansion","B":"hallway","C":"protection","D":"haven"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"mansion"},{"question":"    honeybee    angel    bat    kangaroo    rabbit    ?","options":{"A":"mermaid","B":"possum","C":"grasshopper","D":"sprinter"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"grasshopper"},{"question":"    fence    wall    boundary    path    alley    ?","options":{"A":"ramp","B":"passageway","C":"airfield","D":"pedestrian"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"passageway"},{"question":"BINDING : BOOK","options":{"A":"criminal:gang","B":"display:museum","C":"artist:carpenter","D":"nail:hammer","E":"frame:picture"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"frame:picture"},{"question":"EXPLORE : DISCOVER","options":{"A":"read:skim","B":"research:learn","C":"write:print","D":"think:relate","E":"sleep:wake"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"research:learn"},{"question":"SIAMESE : CAT","options":{"A":"type:breed","B":"dog:puppy","C":"mark:spot","D":"romaine:lettuce","E":"collar:leash"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"romaine:lettuce"},{"question":"FINCH : BIRD","options":{"A":"frog:toad","B":"elephant:reptile","C":"Dalmatian:dog","D":"collie:marsupial","E":"ant:ladybug"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"Dalmatian:dog"},{"question":"PETAL : FLOWER","options":{"A":"salt:pepper","B":"tire:bicycle","C":"base:ball","D":"sandals:shoes","E":"puppy:dog"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"tire:bicycle"},{"question":"COTTON : BALE","options":{"A":"butter:churn","B":"wine:ferment","C":"grain:shock","D":"curd:cheese","E":"beef:steak"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"grain:shock"},{"question":"ELEPHANT : PACHYDERM","options":{"A":"mantis:rodent","B":"poodle:feline","C":"kangaroo:marsupial","D":"zebra:horse","E":"tuna:mollusk"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"kangaroo:marsupial"},{"question":"PSYCHOLOGIST : NEUROSIS","options":{"A":"ophthalmologist:cataract","B":"dermatologist:fracture","C":"infant:pediatrician","D":"rash:orthopedist","E":"oncologist:measles"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"ophthalmologist:cataract"},{"question":"PASTORAL : RURAL","options":{"A":"metropolitan:urban","B":"harvest:autumn","C":"agrarian:benevolent","D":"sleepy:nocturnal","E":"wild:agricultural"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"metropolitan:urban"},{"question":"TAILOR : SUIT","options":{"A":"scheme:agent","B":"edit:manuscript","C":"revise:writer","D":"mention:opinion","E":"implode:building"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"edit:manuscript"},{"question":"PEDAL : BICYCLE","options":{"A":"inch:yardstick","B":"walk:skip","C":"tire:automobile","D":"buckle:belt","E":"oar:canoe"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"oar:canoe"},{"question":"DIVISION : SECTION","options":{"A":"layer:tier","B":"tether:bundle","C":"chapter:verse","D":"riser:stage","E":"dais:speaker"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"layer:tier"},{"question":"DEPRESSED : SAD","options":{"A":"neat:considerate","B":"towering:cringing","C":"rapid:plodding","D":"progressive:regressive","E":"exhausted:tired"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"exhausted:tired"},{"question":"BRISTLE : BRUSH","options":{"A":"arm:leg","B":"stage:curtain","C":"recline:chair","D":"key:piano","E":"art:sculpture"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"key:piano"},{"question":"RAIN : DRIZZLE","options":{"A":"swim:dive","B":"hop:shuffle","C":"juggle:bounce","D":"walk:run","E":"run:jog"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"run:jog"},{"question":"PULSATE : THROB","options":{"A":"walk:run","B":"tired:sleep","C":"examine:scrutinize","D":"ballet:dancer","E":"find:lose"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"examine:scrutinize"},{"question":"FISH : SHOAL","options":{"A":"wolf:pack","B":"elephant:jungle","C":"beagle:clan","D":"herd:peacock","E":"cow:farm"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"wolf:pack"},{"question":"ODOMETER : DISTANCE","options":{"A":"scale:weight","B":"length:width","C":"inch:foot","D":"mileage:speed","E":"area:size"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"scale:weight"},{"question":"WAITRESS : RESTAURANT","options":{"A":"doctor:diagnosis","B":"actor:role","C":"driver:truck","D":"teacher:school","E":"author:book"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"teacher:school"},{"question":"SKEIN : YARN","options":{"A":"squeeze:lemon","B":"fire:coal","C":"ream:paper","D":"tree:lumber","E":"plow:acre"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"ream:paper"},{"question":"MONK : DEVOTION","options":{"A":"maniac:pacifism","B":"explorer:contentment","C":"visionary:complacency","D":"rover:wanderlust","E":"philistine:culture"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"rover:wanderlust"},{"question":"SLAPSTICK : LAUGHTER","options":{"A":"fallacy:dismay","B":"genre:mystery","C":"satire:anger","D":"mimicry:tears","E":"horror:fear"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"horror:fear"},{"question":"VERVE : ENTHUSIASM","options":{"A":"loyalty:duplicity","B":"devotion:reverence","C":"intensity:color","D":"eminence:anonymity","E":"generosity:elation"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"devotion:reverence"},{"question":"SPY : CLANDESTINE","options":{"A":"accountant:meticulous","B":"furrier:rambunctious","C":"lawyer:ironic","D":"shepherd:garrulous","E":"astronaut:opulent"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"accountant:meticulous"},{"question":"COBBLER : SHOE","options":{"A":"jockey:horse","B":"contractor:building","C":"mason:stone","D":"cowboy:boot","E":"potter:paint"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"contractor:building"},{"question":"UMBRAGE : OFFENSE","options":{"A":"confusion:penance","B":"infinity:meaning","C":"decorum:decoration","D":"elation:jubilance","E":"outrage:consideration"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"elation:jubilance"},{"question":"DIRGE : FUNERAL","options":{"A":"chain:letter","B":"bell:church","C":"telephone:call","D":"jingle:commercial","E":"hymn:concerto"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"jingle:commercial"},{"question":"DOMINANCE : HEGEMONY","options":{"A":"romance:sympathy","B":"furtherance:melancholy","C":"independence:autonomy","D":"tolerance:philanthropy","E":"recompense:hilarity"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"independence:autonomy"},{"question":"PHOBIC : FEARFUL","options":{"A":"finicky:thoughtful","B":"cautious:emotional","C":"envious:desiring","D":"shy:familiar","E":"asinine:silly"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"asinine:silly"},{"question":"FERAL : TAME","options":{"A":"rancid:rational","B":"repetitive:recurrent","C":"nettlesome:annoying","D":"repentant:honorable","E":"ephemeral:immortal"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"ephemeral:immortal"},{"question":"METAPHOR : SYMBOL","options":{"A":"pentameter:poem","B":"rhythm:melody","C":"nuance:song","D":"slang:usage","E":"analogy:comparison"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"analogy:comparison"},{"question":"INTEREST : OBSESSION","options":{"A":"mood:feeling","B":"weeping:sadness","C":"dream:fantasy","D":"plan:negation","E":"highlight:indication"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"dream:fantasy"},{"question":"CONDUCTOR : ORCHESTRA","options":{"A":"jockey:mount","B":"thrasher:hay","C":"driver:tractor","D":"skipper:crew","E":"painter:house"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"skipper:crew"},{"question":"FROND : PALM","options":{"A":"quill:porcupine","B":"blade:evergreen","C":"scale:wallaby","D":"tusk:alligator","E":"blade:fern"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"quill:porcupine"},{"question":"SOUND : CACOPHONY","options":{"A":"taste:style","B":"touch:massage","C":"smell:stench","D":"sight:panorama","E":"speech:oration"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"smell:stench"},{"question":"AERIE : EAGLE","options":{"A":"capital:government","B":"bridge:architect","C":"unit:apartment","D":"kennel:veterinarian","E":"house:person"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"house:person"},{"question":"PROFESSOR : ERUDITE","options":{"A":"aviator:licensed","B":"inventor:imaginative","C":"procrastinator:conscientious","D":"overseer:wealthy","E":"moderator:vicious"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"inventor:imaginative"},{"question":"DELTOID : MUSCLE","options":{"A":"radius:bone","B":"brain:nerve","C":"tissue:organ","D":"blood:vein","E":"scalpel:incision"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"radius:bone"},{"question":"JAUNDICE : LIVER","options":{"A":"rash:skin","B":"dialysis:kidney","C":"smog:lung","D":"valentine:heart","E":"imagination:brain"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"rash:skin"},{"question":"CONVICTION : INCARCERATION","options":{"A":"reduction:diminution","B":"induction:amelioration","C":"radicalization:estimation","D":"marginalization:intimidation","E":"proliferation:alliteration"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"reduction:diminution"},{"question":"DEPENDABLE : CAPRICIOUS","options":{"A":"fallible:cantankerous","B":"erasable:obtuse","C":"malleable:limpid","D":"capable:inept","E":"incorrigible:guilty"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"capable:inept"}],"analyzing-arguments":[{"question":"One New York publisher has estimated that 50,000 to 60,000 people in the United States want an anthology that includes the complete works of William Shakespeare. And what accounts for this renewed interest in Shakespeare? As  scholars point out, his psychological insights into both male and female characters are amazing even today. This paragraph best supports the statement that","options":{"A":"Shakespeare'scharactersaremoreinterestingthanfictionalcharacterstoday.","B":"peopleeventodayareinterestedinShakespeare'sworkbecauseofthecharacters.","C":"academicscholarsareputtingtogetherananthologyofShakespeare'swork.","D":"NewYorkershavearenewedinterestedintheworkofShakespeare.","E":"Shakespearewasapsychiatristaswellasaplaywright."},"answer_option":"B","answer":"peopleeventodayareinterestedinShakespeare'sworkbecauseofthecharacters."},{"question":"One of the warmest winters on record has put consumers in the mood to spend money. Spending is likely to be the strongest in thirteen years. During the month of February, sales of existing single-family homes hit an annual record rate of 4.75 million.This paragraph best supports the statement that","options":{"A":"consumerspendingwillbehigherthirteenyearsfromnowthanitistoday.","B":"morepeoplebuyhousesinthemonthofFebruarythaninanyothermonth.","C":"duringthewintermonths,thepricesofsingle-familyhomesarethelowest.","D":"therewereabout4millionhomesforsaleduringthemonthofFebruary.","E":"warmwinterweatherislikelytoaffecttherateofhomesales."},"answer_option":"E","answer":"warmwinterweatherislikelytoaffecttherateofhomesales."},{"question":"Generation Xers are those people born roughly between 1965 and 1981. As employees, Generation Xers tend to be more challenged when they can carry out tasks independently. This makes Generation Xers the most entrepreneurial generation in history.This paragraph best supports the statement that Generation Xers","options":{"A":"workharderthanpeoplefromothergenerations.","B":"haveatendencytobeself-directedworkers","C":"haveaninterestinmakinghistory","D":"tendtoworkinjobsthatrequirerisk-takingbehavior.","E":"liketochallengetheirbossesworkattitudes."},"answer_option":"B","answer":"haveatendencytobeself-directedworkers"},{"question":"If you're a fitness walker, there is no need for a commute to a health club. Your neighborhood can be your health club. You don't need a lot of fancy equipment to get a good workout either. All you need is a well-designed pair of athletic shoes.This paragraph best supports the statement that","options":{"A":"fitnesswalkingisabetterformofexercisethanweightlifting.","B":"amembershipinahealthclubisapoorinvestment.","C":"walkingoutdoorsprovidesabetterworkoutthanwalkingindoors.","D":"fitnesswalkingisaconvenientandvaluableformofexercise.","E":"poorlydesignedathleticshoescancausemajorfootinjuries."},"answer_option":"D","answer":"fitnesswalkingisaconvenientandvaluableformofexercise."},{"question":"In the past, consumers would rarely walk into an ice cream store and order low-fat ice cream. But that isn't the case today. An increasing health consciousness combined with a much bigger selection of tasty low-fat foods in all categories has made low-fat ice cream a very profitable item for ice cream store owners.This paragraph best supports the statement that","options":{"A":"low-faticecreamproducesmorerevenuethanotherlow-fatfoods.","B":"icecreamstoreownerswouldbebetteroffcarryingonlylow-faticecream.","C":"icecreamstoreownersnolongerthinkthatlow-faticecreamisanunpopularitem.","D":"low-faticecreamismorepopularthanotherkindsoficecream.","E":"consumersarefickleanditisimpossibletopleasethem"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"icecreamstoreownersnolongerthinkthatlow-faticecreamisanunpopularitem."},{"question":"Today's high school students spend too much time thinking about trivial and distracting matters such as fashion. Additionally, they often dress inappropriately on school grounds. Rather than spending time writing another detailed dress policy, we should make school uniforms mandatory. If students were required to wear uniforms, it would increase a sense of community and harmony in our schools and it would instill a sense of discipline in our students. Another positive effect would be that teachers and administrators would no longer have to act as clothing police, freeing them up to focus on more important issues.This paragraph best supports the statement that","options":{"A":"inappropriateclothingleadstofailinggrades.","B":"studentswhowearschooluniformsgetintobettercolleges.","C":"teachersandadministratorsspendatleast25%oftheirtimeenforcingthedresscode.","D":"studentsarenotinterestedinbeingpartofacommunity","E":"schooluniformsshouldbecompulsoryforhighschoolstudents."},"answer_option":"E","answer":"schooluniformsshouldbecompulsoryforhighschoolstudents."},{"question":"The criminal justice system needs to change. The system could be more just if it allowed victims the opportunity to confront the person who has harmed them. Also, mediation between victims and their offenders would give the offenders a chance to apologize for the harm they have done.This paragraph best supports the statement that victims of a crime should","options":{"A":"learntoforgivetheiroffenders.","B":"havetherighttoconfronttheiroffenders.","C":"learntheartofmediation.","D":"insistthattheiroffendersbepunished.","E":"havetherighttoimposeasentenceontheiroffenders."},"answer_option":"B","answer":"havetherighttoconfronttheiroffenders."},{"question":"A few states in this country are considering legislation that would prohibit schools from using calculators before the sixth grade. Other states take a different position. Some states are insisting on the purchase of graphing calculators for every student in middle school.This paragraph best supports the statement that in this country","options":{"A":"thereareatleasttwoopinionsabouttheuseofcalculatorsinschools.","B":"calculatorsarefrequentlyadetrimenttolearningmath.","C":"statelegislatorsaremoreinvolvedineducationthaneverbefore.","D":"thepriceofgraphingcalculatorsislesswhenschoolsbuyinbulk.","E":"theargumentagainstcalculatorsinschoolsisunfounded."},"answer_option":"A","answer":"thereareatleasttwoopinionsabouttheuseofcalculatorsinschools."},{"question":"Today's workforce has a new set of social values. Ten years ago, a manager who was offered a promotion in a distant city would not have questioned the move. Today, a manager in that same situation might choose family happiness instead of career advancement.This paragraph best supports the statement that","options":{"A":"mostmanagersarenotloyaltothecorporationsforwhichtheywork.","B":"businessestodaydonotunderstandtheiremployeesneeds.","C":"employeessocialvalueshavechangedoverthepasttenyears.","D":"careeradvancementisnotimportanttotoday'sbusinessmanagers.","E":"companiesshouldrequiretheiremployeestoacceptpromotions."},"answer_option":"C","answer":"employeessocialvalueshavechangedoverthepasttenyears."},{"question":"It is well known that the world urgently needs adequate distribution of food, so that everyone gets enough. Adequate distribution of medicine is just as urgent. Medical expertise and medical supplies need to be redistributed throughout the world so that people in emerging nations will have proper medical care.This paragraph best supports the statement that","options":{"A":"themajorityofthepeopleintheworldhaveneverbeenseenbyadoctor.","B":"foodproductioninemergingnationshasslowedduringthepastseveralyears.","C":"mostoftheworld'sdoctorsareselfishaboutgivingtimeandmoneytothepoor.","D":"themedical-supplyindustryshouldstepupproductionofitsproducts.","E":"manypeoplewholiveinemergingnationsarenotreceivingpropermedicalcare"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"manypeoplewholiveinemergingnationsarenotreceivingpropermedicalcare"},{"question":"Yoga has become a very popular type of exercise, but it may not be for everyone. Before you sign yourself up for a yoga class, you need to examine what it is you want from your fitness routine. If you're looking for a high-energy, fast-paced aerobic workout, a yoga class might not be your best choice.This paragraph best supports the statement that","options":{"A":"yogaismorepopularthanhigh-impactaerobics.","B":"beforeembarkingonanewexerciseregimen,youshouldthinkaboutyourneedsanddesires.","C":"yogaischangingtheworldoffitnessinmajorways","D":"yogabenefitsyourbodyandmind","E":"mostpeoplethinkthatyogaisn'tarigorousformofexercise."},"answer_option":"B","answer":"beforeembarkingonanewexerciseregimen,youshouldthinkaboutyourneedsanddesires."},{"question":"Human technology developed from the first stone tools about two and a half million years ago. At the beginning, the rate of development was slow. Hundreds of thousands of years passed without much change. Today, new technologies are reported daily on television and in newspapers.This paragraph best supports the statement that","options":{"A":"stonetoolswerenotreallytechnology.","B":"stonetoolswereinusefortwoandahalfmillionyears","C":"thereisnowaytoknowwhenstonetoolsfirstcameintouse.","D":"Intoday'sworld,newtechnologiesareconstantlybeingdeveloped","E":"noneofthelatesttechnologiesisassignificantasthedevelopmentofstonetools."},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Intoday'sworld,newtechnologiesareconstantlybeingdeveloped"},{"question":"Mathematics allows us to expand our consciousness. Mathematics tells us about economic trends, patterns of disease, and the growth of populations. Math is good at exposing the truth, but it can also perpetuate misunderstandings and untruths. Figures have the power to mislead people.This paragraph best supports the statement that","options":{"A":"thestudyofmathematicsisdangerous.","B":"wordsaremoretruthfulthanfigures.","C":"thestudyofmathematicsismoreimportantthanotherdisciplines.","D":"thepowerofnumbersisthattheycannotlie.","E":"figuresaresometimesusedtodeceivepeople."},"answer_option":"E","answer":"figuresaresometimesusedtodeceivepeople."},{"question":"In the 1966 Supreme Court decision Miranda v. Arizona, the court held that before the police can obtain statements from a person subjected to an interrogation, the person must be given a Miranda warning. This warning means that a person must be told that he or she has the right to remain silent during the police interrogation. Violation of this right means that any statement that the person makes is not admissible in a court hearing.This paragraph best supports the statement that","options":{"A":"policewhodonotwarnpersonsoftheirMirandarightsareguiltyofacrime.","B":"aMirandawarningmustbegivenbeforeapoliceinterrogationcanbegin.","C":"thepolicemaynolongerinterrogatepersonssuspectedofacrimeunlessalawyerispresent.","D":"the1966SupremeCourtdecisioninMirandashouldbereversed","E":"personswhoareinterrogatedbypoliceshouldalwaysremainsilentuntiltheirlawyercomes"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"aMirandawarningmustbegivenbeforeapoliceinterrogationcanbegin."},{"question":"During colonial times in America, juries were encouraged to ask questions of the parties in the courtroom. The jurors were, in fact, expected to investigate the facts of the case themselves. If jurors conducted an investigation today, we would throw out the case.This paragraph best supports the statement that","options":{"A":"juriesarelessimportanttodaythantheywereincolonialtimes.","B":"jurorstodayarelessinterestedincourtcasesthantheywereincolonialtimes.","C":"courtroomstodayaremoreefficientthantheywereincolonialtimes.","D":"jurorsincolonialtimesweremoreinformedthanjurorstoday.","E":"thejurysysteminAmericahaschangedsincecolonialtimes."},"answer_option":"E","answer":"thejurysysteminAmericahaschangedsincecolonialtimes."},{"question":"There are no effective boundaries when it comes to pollutants. Studies have shown that toxic insecticides that have been banned in many countries are riding the wind from countries where they remain legal. Compounds such as DDT and toxaphene have been found in remote places like the Yukon and other Arctic regions.This paragraph best supports the statement that","options":{"A":"toxicinsecticidessuchasDDThavenotbeenbannedthroughouttheworld.","B":"morepollutantsfindtheirwayintopolarclimatesthantheydointowarmerareas","C":"studieshaveproventhatmanycountrieshaveignoredtheirownantipollutionlaws.","D":"DDTandtoxaphenearethetwomosttoxicinsecticidesintheworld.","E":"evenaworldwidebanontoxicinsecticideswouldnotstopthespreadofDDTpollution."},"answer_option":"A","answer":"toxicinsecticidessuchasDDThavenotbeenbannedthroughouttheworld."},{"question":"The Fourth Amendment to the Constitution protects citizens against unreasonable searches and seizures. No search of a person's home or personal effects may be conducted without a written search warrant issued on probable cause. This means that a neutral judge must approve the factual basis justifying a search before it can be conducted.This paragraph best supports the statement  that the police cannot search a person's home or private papers unless they have","options":{"A":"legalauthorization","B":"directevidenceofacrime.","C":"readthepersonhisorherconstitutionalrights.","D":"areasonablebeliefthatacrimehasoccurred.","E":"requestedthatajudgebepresent."},"answer_option":"A","answer":"legalauthorization"},{"question":"Obesity is a serious problem in this country. Research suggests that obesity can lead to a number of health problems including diabetes, asthma, and heart disease. Recent research has even indicated that there may be a relationship between obesity and some types of cancer. Major public health campaigns that increase awareness and propose simple lifestyle changes that will, with diligence and desire, eliminate or least mitigate the incidence of obesity are a crucial first step in battling this critical problem.This paragraph best supports the statement that","options":{"A":"publichealthcampaignsthatraiseconsciousnessandproposelifestylechangesareaproductivewaytofightobesity.","B":"obesityistheleadingcauseofdiabetesinourcountry.","C":"peopleinourcountrywatchtoomuchtelevisionanddonotexerciseenough.","D":"adeclineinobesitywouldradicallydecreasetheincidenceofasthma.","E":"fast-foodrestaurantsandunhealthyschoollunchescontributegreatlytoobesity."},"answer_option":"A","answer":"publichealthcampaignsthatraiseconsciousnessandproposelifestylechangesareaproductivewaytofightobesity."},{"question":"Critical reading is a demanding process. To read critically, you must slow down your reading and, with pencil in hand, perform specific operations on the text. Mark up the text with your reactions, conclusions, and questions. When you read, become an active participant.This paragraph best supports the statement that","options":{"A":"criticalreadingisaslow,dull,butessentialprocess","B":"thebestcriticalreadinghappensatcriticaltimesinaperson'slife.","C":"readersshouldgetinthehabitofquestioningthetruthofwhattheyread.","D":"criticalreadingrequiresthoughtfulandcarefulattention.","E":"criticalreadingshouldtakeplaceatthesametimeeachday."},"answer_option":"D","answer":"criticalreadingrequiresthoughtfulandcarefulattention."},{"question":"Walk into any supermarket or pharmacy and you will find several shelves of products designed to protect adults and children from the sun. Additionally, a host of public health campaigns have been created, including National Skin Cancer Awareness Month, that warn us about the sun's damaging UV rays and provide guidelines about protecting ourselves. While warnings about the sun's dangers are frequent, a recent survey found that fewer than half of all adults adequately protect themselves from the sun.This paragraph best supports the statement that","options":{"A":"childrenarebetterprotectedfromthesun'sdangerousraysthanadults","B":"salesofsunprotectionproductsareatanall-timehigh.","C":"adultsarenotheedingthewarningsaboutthedangersofsunexposureseriouslyenough.","D":"moreadultshaveskincancernowthaneverbefore","E":"thereisnotenoughinformationdisseminatedaboutthedangersofsunexposure."},"answer_option":"C","answer":"adultsarenotheedingthewarningsaboutthedangersofsunexposureseriouslyenough."},{"question":"For too long, school cafeterias, in an effort to provide food they thought would be appetizing to young people, mimicked fast-food restaurants, serving items such as burgers and fries, pizza, hot dogs, and fried chicken. School districts nationwide are now addressing this trend by incorporating some simple and inexpensive options that will make cafeteria lunches healthier while still appealing to students.This paragraph best supports the statement that","options":{"A":"schoolcafeteriashavealwaysemphasizednutritionalguidelinesoveranyotherconsiderations.","B":"youngpeoplewouldrathereatinaschoolcafeteriathanalocalfast-foodrestaurant.","C":"schoollunchmenusarebecominghealthierduetomajornewinitiativesonthepartofschooldistricts.","D":"itispossibletomakeschoollunchesbothhealthierandappealingwithoutspendingagreatdealofmoneyandundertakingaradicaltransformation.","E":"vegetarianlunchoptionswouldgreatlyimprovethenutritionalvalueoftheschoollunchprogram."},"answer_option":"D","answer":"itispossibletomakeschoollunchesbothhealthierandappealingwithoutspendingagreatdealofmoneyandundertakingaradicaltransformation."},{"question":"Forest fires feed on decades-long accumulations of debris and leap from the tops  of young trees into the branches of mature trees. Fires that jump from treetop to treetop can be devastating. In old-growth forests, however, the shade of mature trees keeps thickets of small trees from sprouting, and the lower branches of mature trees are too high to catch the flames.This paragraph best supports the statement that","options":{"A":"forestfiredamageisreducedinold-growthforests.","B":"smalltreesshouldbecutdowntopreventforestfires.","C":"maturetreesshouldbethinnedouttopreventforestfires","D":"forestfiresdothemostdamageinold-growthforests.","E":"old-growthforestshavealargeraccumulationofforestdebris."},"answer_option":"A","answer":"forestfiredamageisreducedinold-growthforests."},{"question":"During the last six years, the number of practicing physicians has increased by about 20%. During the same time period, the number of healthcare managers has increased by more than 600%. These percentages mean that many doctors have lost the authority to make their own schedules, determine the fees that they charge, and decide on prescribed treatments.This paragraph best supports the statement that doctors","options":{"A":"resenttheinterferenceofhealthcaremanagers.","B":"nolongerhaveadequatetraining.","C":"careagreatdealabouttheirpatients.","D":"arelessindependentthantheyusedtobe.","E":"aremakingalotlessmoneythantheyusedtomake."},"answer_option":"D","answer":"arelessindependentthantheyusedtobe."},{"question":"By the time they reach adulthood, most people can perform many different activities involving motor skills. Motor skills involve such diverse tasks as riding a bicycle, threading a needle, and cooking a dinner. What all these activities have in common is their dependence on precision and timing of muscular movement.This paragraph best supports the statement that","options":{"A":"mostadultshavenotrefinedtheirmotorskills.","B":"alladultsknowhowtorideabicycle.","C":"refinedmotorskillsarespecificallylimitedtoadults.","D":"childrenperformfewerfinemotoractivitiesinadaythanadultsdo.","E":"threadinganeedleisaprecisemotorskill."},"answer_option":"E","answer":"threadinganeedleisaprecisemotorskill."},{"question":"Most Reality TV centers on two common motivators: fame and money. The shows transform waitresses, hairdressers, investment bankers, counselors, and teachers, to name a few, from obscure figures to house-hold names. A lucky few successfully parlay their fifteen minutes of fame into celebrity. The luckiest stars of Reality TV also reap huge financial rewards for acts including eating large insects, marrying someone they barely know, and revealing their innermost thoughts to millions of people. This paragraph best supports the statement that","options":{"A":"thestarsofRealityTVareinterestedinbeingrichandfamous.","B":"RealityTVisthebestthingthathashappenedtonetworktelevisioninalongtime.","C":"forRealityTVstars,famewilllastonlyaslongastheirparticulartelevisionshow.","D":"traditionaldramasandsitcomsarebeingreplacedbyRealityTVprogrammingatanalarmingrate.","E":"RealityTVshowsrepresentanewwaveofsensationalistic,lowqualityprogramming."},"answer_option":"A","answer":"thestarsofRealityTVareinterestedinbeingrichandfamous."},{"question":"The image of a knitter as an older woman sitting in a comfortable, old-fashioned living room with a basket of yarn at her feet and a bun in her hair is one of the past. As knitting continues to become more popular and increasingly trendy, it is much more difficult to describe the average knitter. Knitters today might be 18, 28, 40, or 65. They might live in a big urban center and take classes in a knit- ting shop that doubles as a café or they may gather in suburban coffee shops to support one another in knitting and other aspects of life. They could be college roommates knitting in their dorm room or two senior citizens knitting in a church hall. Even men are getting in the act.  It would be incredibly difficult to come up with an accurate profile of a contemporary knitter to replace that image of the old woman with the basket of yarn!This paragraph best supports the statement that","options":{"A":"peoplearereturningtoknittinginanattempttoreconnectwithsimplertimes.","B":"knittingisnowmoreofagroupactivity,asopposedtoanindividualhobby.","C":"creatinganaccurateprofileofaparticulartypeofpersondependsonthepeopleinthisgrouphavingtraitsandcharacteristicsincommon.","D":"today'sknittersaremuchlessaccomplishedthanknittersofthepast.","E":"youngpeopleareturningtoknittinginrecordnumbers."},"answer_option":"C","answer":"creatinganaccurateprofileofaparticulartypeofpersondependsonthepeopleinthisgrouphavingtraitsandcharacteristicsincommon."},{"question":"Close-up images of Mars by the Mariner 9 probe indicated networks of valleys that looked like the stream beds on Earth. These images also implied that Mars once had an atmosphere that was thick enough to trap the sun's heat. If this were true, something happened to Mars billions of years ago that stripped away the planet's atmosphere. This paragraph best supports the statement that","options":{"A":"Marsnowhaslittleornoatmosphere.","B":"MarsoncehadathickeratmospherethanEarthdoes.","C":"theMariner9probetookthefirstpicturesofMars.","D":"MarsisclosertothesunthanEarthis.","E":"MarsismoremountainousthanEarthis."},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Marsnowhaslittleornoatmosphere."},{"question":"Originating in the 1920s, the Pyramid scheme is one of the oldest con games going. Honest people are often pulled in, thinking the scheme is a legitimate investment enterprise. The first customer to \"fall for\" the Pyramid scheme will actually make big money and will therefore persuade friends and relatives to join also. The chain then continues with the con artist who originated the scheme pocketing, rather than investing, the money. Finally, the pyramid collapses, but by that time, the scam artist will usually have moved out of town, leaving no forwarding address.This paragraph best supports the statement that","options":{"A":"itisfairlyeasytospotaPyramidschemeinthemaking.","B":"hefirstcustomerofaPyramidschemeisthemostgullible.","C":"thepeoplewhosetupPyramidschemesareabletofoolhonestpeople.","D":"thePyramidschemehaditsheydayinthe1920s,butit'smakingacomeback.","E":"thePyramidschemegotitsnamefromitsstructure."},"answer_option":"C","answer":"thepeoplewhosetupPyramidschemesareabletofoolhonestpeople."},{"question":"Which of the following is similar to the argument made by the speaker?","options":{"A":"Therichshouldnotbeallowedto\"buy\"politicians,sotheCongressshouldenactcampaignfinancereform.","B":"Theideaoffreedomofreligionalsomeanstherightnottoparticipateinreligion,somandatedschoolprayerviolatesfreedomofreligion.","C":"TheConstitutionguaranteesfreedomtoownproperty,sotaxesshouldbeillegal.","D":"Convictedfelonsshouldnothavetheirconvictionsoverturnedonatechnicality.","E":"Inordertounderstandwhatmaybeconstitutionaltoday,oneneedstolookatwhatthelawswerewhentheConstitutionwasenacted."},"answer_option":"B","answer":"Theideaoffreedomofreligionalsomeanstherightnottoparticipateinreligion,somandatedschoolprayerviolatesfreedomofreligion."},{"question":"Which of the following, if true, would weaken the speaker's argument?","options":{"A":"Anactionisnotconsideredapartoffreedomofspeech.","B":"Peoplewhoburntheflagusuallycommitothercrimesaswell.","C":"Theflagwasnotrecognizedbythegovernmentuntil1812.","D":"Stateflagsarealmostneverburned","E":"Mostpeopleareagainstflagburning."},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Anactionisnotconsideredapartoffreedomofspeech."},{"question":"Which of the following best expresses the main point of the passage?","options":{"A":"Onlyveteranscareabouttheflag-burningissue.","B":"Flagburningalmostneverhappens,sooutlawingitisawasteoftime.","C":"Flagburningwillbeaveryimportantissueinthenextelection.","D":"Tooutlawflagburningistooutlawwhattheflagrepresents.","E":"Burningtheflagshouldonlybeillegalwhenitisdoneinforeigncountries."},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Tooutlawflagburningistooutlawwhattheflagrepresents."},{"question":"Which of the following, if true, would strengthen the speaker's argument?","options":{"A":"studiesshowingcomputersareexpensive","B":"researchontheeffectofcomputergamesonchildren","C":"examplesofhighschoolstudentswhousecomputersimproperly","D":"proofthatthecostofcomputersiscomingdown","E":"evidencethatusingcomputersmakeslearningtoreaddifficult"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"evidencethatusingcomputersmakeslearningtoreaddifficult"},{"question":"Which of the following, if true, would weaken the speaker's argument?","options":{"A":"ademonstrationthatcomputerscanbeusedtoteachreadingandarithmetic","B":"analysisofthecost-effectivenessofnewcomputersversusrepairingoldcomputers","C":"examplesofadultswhodonotknowhowtousecomputers","D":"recentgradereportsofstudentsinthecomputerclasses","E":"avisittoaclassroomwherecomputersarebeingused"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"ademonstrationthatcomputerscanbeusedtoteachreadingandarithmetic"},{"question":"Which of the following methods of argument is used in the previous passage?","options":{"A":"aspecificexamplethatillustratesthespeaker'spoint","B":"attackingthebeliefsofthosewhodisagreewiththespeaker","C":"relyingonananalogytoprovethespeaker'spoint","D":"displayingstatisticsthatbackupthespeaker'spoint","E":"comparingdifferentmethodsoflearning"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"relyingonananalogytoprovethespeaker'spoint"},{"question":"What is the point at issue between Quinn and Dakota?","options":{"A":"whethersixteen-year-oldsshouldberequiredtotakedriverseducationbeforebeingissuedalicense","B":"whetherschoolsoughttoprovidedriverseducationtofourteen-andfifteen-year-oldstudents","C":"whetherthestandardsforissuingdriverslicensesshouldbecomemorestringent","D":"whethersixteen-year-oldsarepreparedtodriveintoday'strafficconditions","E":"whetherparentsareabletodoagoodjobteachingtheirchildrentodrive"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"whethersixteen-year-oldsarepreparedtodriveintoday'strafficconditions"},{"question":"On what does Quinn rely in making her argument?","options":{"A":"statistics","B":"emotion","C":"fairness","D":"anecdotes","E":"actualities"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"fairness"},{"question":"On what does Dakota rely in making her argument?","options":{"A":"statistics","B":"emotion","C":"fairness","D":"anecdotes","E":"actualities"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"actualities"}],"artificial-language":[{"question":"Here are some words translated from an artificial language.gorblflur means fan beltpixngorbl means ceiling fanarthtusl means tile roofWhich word could mean \"ceiling tile\"?","options":{"A":"gorbltusl","B":"flurgorbl","C":"arthflur","D":"pixnarth"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"pixnarth"},{"question":"Here are some words translated from an artificial language.hapllesh means cloudburstsrenchoch means pinballresbosrench means ninepinWhich word could mean \"cloud nine\"?","options":{"A":"leshsrench","B":"ochhapl","C":"haploch","D":"haplresbo"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"haplresbo"},{"question":"Here are some words translated from an artificial language.agnoscrenia means poisonous spiderdelanocrenia means poisonous snakeagnosdeery means brown spiderWhich word could mean \"black widow spider\"?","options":{"A":"deeryclostagnos","B":"agnosdelano","C":"agnosvitriblunin","D":"trymuttiagnos"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"agnosvitriblunin"},{"question":"Here are some words translated from an artificial language.moolokarn means blue skywilkospadi means bicycle racemoolowilko means blue bicycleWhich word could mean \"racecar\"?","options":{"A":"wilkozwet","B":"spadiwilko","C":"moolobreil","D":"spadivolo"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"spadivolo"},{"question":"Here are some words translated from an artificial language.migenlasan means cupboardlasanpoen means boardwalkcuopdansa means pullmanWhich word could mean \"walkway\"?","options":{"A":"poenmigen","B":"cuopeisel","C":"lasandansa","D":"poenforc"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"poenforc"},{"question":"Here are some words translated from an artificial language.godabim means kidney stonesromzbim means kidney beansromzbako means wax beansWhich word could mean \"wax statue\"?","options":{"A":"godaromz","B":"lazbim","C":"wasibako","D":"romzpeo"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"wasibako"},{"question":"Here are some words translated from an artificial language.granamelke means big treepinimelke means little treemelkehoon means tree houseWhich word could mean \"big house\"?","options":{"A":"granahoon","B":"pinishur","C":"pinihoon","D":"melkegrana"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"granahoon"},{"question":"Here are some words translated from an artificial language.daftafoni means advisementimodafta means misadviseimolokti means misconductWhich word could mean \"statement\"?","options":{"A":"kratafoni","B":"kratadafta","C":"loktifoni","D":"daftaimo"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"kratafoni"},{"question":"Here are some words translated from an artificial language.lelibroon means yellow hatplekafroti means flower gardenfrotimix means garden saladWhich word could mean \"yellow flower\"?","options":{"A":"lelifroti","B":"lelipleka","C":"plekabroon","D":"frotibroon"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"lelipleka"},{"question":"Here are some words translated from an artificial language.myncabel means saddle horseconowir means trail ridecabelalma means horse blanketWhich word could mean \"horse ride\"?","options":{"A":"cabelwir","B":"conocabel","C":"almamyn","D":"conoalma"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"cabelwir"},{"question":"Here are some words translated from an artificial language.dionot means oak treeblyonot means oak leafblycrin means maple leafWhich word could mean \"maple syrup\"?","options":{"A":"blymuth","B":"hupponot","C":"patricrin","D":"crinweel"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"patricrin"},{"question":"Here are some words translated from an artificial language.tamceno means sky bluecenorax means blue cheeseaplmitl means star brightWhich word could mean \"bright sky\"?","options":{"A":"cenotam","B":"mitltam","C":"raxmitl","D":"aplceno"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"mitltam"},{"question":"Here are some words translated from an artificial language.gemolinea means fair warninggerimitu means report cardgilageri means weather reportWhich word could mean \"fair weather\"?","options":{"A":"gemogila","B":"gerigeme","C":"gemomitu","D":"gerimita"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"gemogila"},{"question":"Here are some words translated from an artificial language.slar means jumpslary means jumpingslarend means jumpedWhich word could mean \"playing\"?","options":{"A":"clargslarend","B":"clargy","C":"ellaclarg","D":"slarmont"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"clargy"},{"question":"Here are some words translated from an artificial language.jalkamofti means happy birthdaymoftihoze means birthday partymentogunn means goodnessWhich word could mean \"happiness\"?","options":{"A":"jalkagunn","B":"mentohoze","C":"moftihoze","D":"hozemento"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"jalkagunn"},{"question":"Here are some words translated from an artificial language.plekapaki means fruitcakepakishillen means cakewalktreftalan means buttercupWhich word could mean \"cupcake\"?","options":{"A":"shillenalan","B":"treftpleka","C":"pakitreft","D":"alanpaki"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"alanpaki"},{"question":"Here are some words translated from an artificial language.malgauper means peach cobblermalgaport means peach juicemoggagrop means apple jellyWhich word could mean \"apple juice\"?","options":{"A":"moggaport","B":"malgaauper","C":"gropport","D":"moggagrop"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"moggaport"},{"question":"Here are some words translated from an artificial language.peslligen means basketball courtligenstrisi means courtroomoltaganti means placement testWhich word could mean \"guest room\"?","options":{"A":"peslstrisi","B":"vosefstrisi","C":"gantipesl","D":"oltastrisi"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"vosefstrisi"},{"question":"Here are some words translated from an artificial language.mallonpiml means blue lightmallontifl means blueberryarpantifl means raspberryWhich word could mean \"lighthouse\"?","options":{"A":"tiflmallon","B":"pimlarpan","C":"mallonarpan","D":"pimldoken"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"pimldoken"},{"question":"Here are some words translated from an artificial language.briftamint means militantuftonel means occupieduftonalene means occupationWhich word could mean \"occupant\"?","options":{"A":"elbrifta","B":"uftonamint","C":"elamint","D":"briftalene"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"uftonamint"},{"question":"Here are some words translated from an artificial language.morpirquat means birdhousebeelmorpir means bluebirdbeelclak means bluebellWhich word could mean \"houseguest\"?","options":{"A":"morpirhunde","B":"beelmoki","C":"quathunde","D":"clakquat"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"quathunde"},{"question":"Here are some words translated from an artificial language.relftaga means carefreeotaga means carefulfertaga means carelessWhich word could mean \"aftercare\"?","options":{"A":"zentaga","B":"tagafer","C":"tagazen","D":"relffer"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"tagazen"},{"question":"Here are some words translated from an artificial language.aptaose means first baseeptaose means second baselartabuk means ballparkWhich word could mean \"baseball\"?","options":{"A":"buklarta","B":"oseepta","C":"bukose","D":"oselarta"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"oselarta"},{"question":"Here are some words translated from an artificial language.krekinblaf means workforcedritakrekin means groundworkkrekinalti means workplaceWhich word could mean \"someplace\"?","options":{"A":"moropalti","B":"krekindrita","C":"altiblaf","D":"dritaalti"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"moropalti"}],"cause-and-effect":[{"question":"Statements:  The prices of petrol and diesel in the domestic market have remained unchanged for the past few months. The crude oil prices in the international market have gone up substantially in the last few months. ","options":{"A":"StatementIisthecauseandstatementIIisitseffect","B":"StatementIIisthecauseandstatementIisitseffect","C":"BoththestatementsIandIIareindependentcauses","D":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofindependentcauses","E":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofsomecommoncause"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofindependentcauses"},{"question":"Statements:  The government has recently fixed the fees for professional courses offered by the unaided institutions which are much lower than the fees charged last year. The parents of the aspiring students launched a severe agitation last year protesting against the high fees charged by the unaided institutions. ","options":{"A":"StatementIisthecauseandstatementIIisitseffect","B":"StatementIIisthecauseandstatementIisitseffect","C":"BoththestatementsIandIIareindependentcauses","D":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofindependentcauses","E":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofsomecommoncause"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"StatementIIisthecauseandstatementIisitseffect"},{"question":"Statements:  The Reserve Bank of India has recently put restrictions on few small banks in the country. The small banks in the private and co-operative sector in India are not in a position to withstand the competitions of the bigger in the public sector. ","options":{"A":"StatementIisthecauseandstatementIIisitseffect","B":"StatementIIisthecauseandstatementIisitseffect","C":"BoththestatementsIandIIareindependentcauses","D":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofindependentcauses","E":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofsomecommoncause"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"StatementIIisthecauseandstatementIisitseffect"},{"question":"Statements:  All the schools in the area had to be kept closed for most part of the week. Many parents have withdrawn their children from the local schools. ","options":{"A":"StatementIisthecauseandstatementIIisitseffect","B":"StatementIIisthecauseandstatementIisitseffect","C":"BoththestatementsIandIIareindependentcauses","D":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofindependentcauses","E":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofsomecommoncause"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofindependentcauses"},{"question":"Statements:  India has surpassed the value of tea exports this year over all the earlier years due to an increase in demand for quality tea in the European market. There is an increase in demand of coffee in the domestic market during the last two years. ","options":{"A":"StatementIisthecauseandstatementIIisitseffect","B":"StatementIIisthecauseandstatementIisitseffect","C":"BoththestatementsIandIIareindependentcauses","D":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofindependentcauses","E":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofsomecommoncause"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"BoththestatementsIandIIareindependentcauses"},{"question":"Statements:  There is unprecedented increase in the number of young unemployed in comparison to the previous year. A large number of candidates submitted applications against an advertisement for the post of manager issued by a bank. ","options":{"A":"StatementIisthecauseandstatementIIisitseffect","B":"StatementIIisthecauseandstatementIisitseffect","C":"BoththestatementsIandIIareindependentcauses","D":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofindependentcauses","E":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofsomecommoncause"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"StatementIisthecauseandstatementIIisitseffect"},{"question":"Statements:  The police authority has recently caught a group of house breakers. The citizens group in the locality have started night vigil in the area. ","options":{"A":"StatementIisthecauseandstatementIIisitseffect","B":"StatementIIisthecauseandstatementIisitseffect","C":"BoththestatementsIandIIareindependentcauses","D":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofindependentcauses","E":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofsomecommoncause"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofsomecommoncause"},{"question":"Statements:  Majority of the students in the college expressed their opinion against the college authority's decision to break away from the university and become autonomous. The university authorities have expressed their inability to provide grants to its constituent colleges. ","options":{"A":"StatementIisthecauseandstatementIIisitseffect","B":"StatementIIisthecauseandstatementIisitseffect","C":"BoththestatementsIandIIareindependentcauses","D":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofindependentcauses","E":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofsomecommoncause"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"StatementIIisthecauseandstatementIisitseffect"},{"question":"Statements:  The literacy rate in the district has been increasing for the last four years. The district administration has conducted extensive training programme for the workers involved in the literacy drive. ","options":{"A":"StatementIisthecauseandstatementIIisitseffect","B":"StatementIIisthecauseandstatementIisitseffect","C":"BoththestatementsIandIIareindependentcauses","D":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofindependentcauses","E":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofsomecommoncause"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"StatementIIisthecauseandstatementIisitseffect"},{"question":"Statements:  The school authority has asked the X Std. students to attend special classes to be conducted on Sundays. The parents of the X Std. students have withdrawn their wards from attending private tuitions conducted on Sundays. ","options":{"A":"StatementIisthecauseandstatementIIisitseffect","B":"StatementIIisthecauseandstatementIisitseffect","C":"BoththestatementsIandIIareindependentcauses","D":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofindependentcauses","E":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofsomecommoncause"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"StatementIisthecauseandstatementIIisitseffect"},{"question":"Statements:  The Government has imported large quantities of sugar  as per trade agreement with other countries. The prices of sugar in the domestic market have fallen sharply in the recent months. ","options":{"A":"StatementIisthecauseandstatementIIisitseffect","B":"StatementIIisthecauseandstatementIisitseffect","C":"BoththestatementsIandIIareindependentcauses","D":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofindependentcauses","E":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofsomecommoncause"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"StatementIisthecauseandstatementIIisitseffect"},{"question":"Statements:  There is sharp decline in the production of oil seeds this year. The Government has decided to increase the import quantum of edible oil. ","options":{"A":"StatementIisthecauseandstatementIIisitseffect","B":"StatementIIisthecauseandstatementIisitseffect","C":"BoththestatementsIandIIareindependentcauses","D":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofindependentcauses","E":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofsomecommoncause"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"StatementIisthecauseandstatementIIisitseffect"},{"question":"Statements:  The private medical colleges have increased the tuition fees in the current year by 200 per cent over the last year's fees to meet the expenses. The Government medical colleges have not increased their fees in spite of price escalation. ","options":{"A":"StatementIisthecauseandstatementIIisitseffect","B":"StatementIIisthecauseandstatementIisitseffect","C":"BoththestatementsIandIIareindependentcauses","D":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofindependentcauses","E":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofsomecommoncause"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"BoththestatementsIandIIareindependentcauses"},{"question":"Statements:  Large number of people living in the low-lying areas has been evacuated during the last few days to safer places. The Government has rushed in relief supplies to the people living in the affected areas. ","options":{"A":"StatementIisthecauseandstatementIIisitseffect","B":"StatementIIisthecauseandstatementIisitseffect","C":"BoththestatementsIandIIareindependentcauses","D":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofindependentcauses","E":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofsomecommoncause"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofsomecommoncause"},{"question":"Statements:  It is the aim of the city's civic authority to get the air pollution reduced by 20% in the next two months. The number of asthma cases in the city is constantly increasing. ","options":{"A":"StatementIisthecauseandstatementIIisitseffect","B":"StatementIIisthecauseandstatementIisitseffect","C":"BoththestatementsIandIIareindependentcauses","D":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofindependentcauses","E":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofsomecommoncause"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"StatementIIisthecauseandstatementIisitseffect"},{"question":"Statements:  The local co-operative credit society has decided to stop giving loans to farmers with immediate effect. A large number of credit society members have withdrawn major part of their deposits from the credit society. ","options":{"A":"StatementIisthecauseandstatementIIisitseffect","B":"StatementIIisthecauseandstatementIisitseffect","C":"BoththestatementsIandIIareindependentcauses","D":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofindependentcauses","E":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofsomecommoncause"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"StatementIIisthecauseandstatementIisitseffect"},{"question":"Statements:  The employees of the biggest bank in the country have given an indefinite strike call starting from third of the next month. The employees of the Central Government have withdrawn their week long demonstrations. ","options":{"A":"StatementIisthecauseandstatementIIisitseffect","B":"StatementIIisthecauseandstatementIisitseffect","C":"BoththestatementsIandIIareindependentcauses","D":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofindependentcauses","E":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofsomecommoncause"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofindependentcauses"},{"question":"Statements:  Police resorted to lathi-charge to disperse the unlawful gathering of large number of people. The citizens' forum called a general strike in protest against the police atrocities. ","options":{"A":"StatementIisthecauseandstatementIIisitseffect","B":"StatementIIisthecauseandstatementIisitseffect","C":"BoththestatementsIandIIareindependentcauses","D":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofindependentcauses","E":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofsomecommoncause"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"StatementIIisthecauseandstatementIisitseffect"},{"question":"Statements:  Majority of the citizens in the locality belongs to higher income group. The sales in the local super market are comparatively much higher than in other localities. ","options":{"A":"StatementIisthecauseandstatementIIisitseffect","B":"StatementIIisthecauseandstatementIisitseffect","C":"BoththestatementsIandIIareindependentcauses","D":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofindependentcauses","E":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofsomecommoncause"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"StatementIisthecauseandstatementIIisitseffect"},{"question":"Statements:  The life today is too fast, demanding and full of variety in all aspects which at times leads to stressful situations. Number of suicide cases among teenagers is on increase. ","options":{"A":"StatementIisthecauseandstatementIIisitseffect","B":"StatementIIisthecauseandstatementIisitseffect","C":"BoththestatementsIandIIareindependentcauses","D":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofindependentcauses","E":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofsomecommoncause"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"StatementIisthecauseandstatementIIisitseffect"},{"question":"Statements:  The government has decided to make all the information related to primary education available to the general public. In the past, the general public did not have access to all these information related to primary education. ","options":{"A":"StatementIisthecauseandstatementIIisitseffect","B":"StatementIIisthecauseandstatementIisitseffect","C":"BoththestatementsIandIIareindependentcauses","D":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofindependentcauses","E":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofsomecommoncause"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"StatementIIisthecauseandstatementIisitseffect"},{"question":"Statements:  The farmers have decided against selling their kharif crops to the Government agencies. The Government has reduced the procurement price of kharif crops starting from last month to the next six months. ","options":{"A":"StatementIisthecauseandstatementIIisitseffect","B":"StatementIIisthecauseandstatementIisitseffect","C":"BoththestatementsIandIIareindependentcauses","D":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofindependentcauses","E":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofsomecommoncause"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"StatementIIisthecauseandstatementIisitseffect"},{"question":"Statements:  The performance of most of the students in final exam of class X in the schools run by the Government was excellent. Many teachers of the Government schools left the school and joined private schools. ","options":{"A":"StatementIisthecauseandstatementIIisitseffect","B":"StatementIIisthecauseandstatementIisitseffect","C":"BoththestatementsIandIIareindependentcauses","D":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofindependentcauses","E":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofsomecommoncause"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofindependentcauses"},{"question":"Statements:  There is considerable reduction in the number of people affected by water-borne diseases in City A during this rainy season. The government has opened four new civil hospitals in City A in the beginning of the year. ","options":{"A":"StatementIisthecauseandstatementIIisitseffect","B":"StatementIIisthecauseandstatementIisitseffect","C":"BoththestatementsIandIIareindependentcauses","D":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofindependentcauses","E":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofsomecommoncause"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"BoththestatementsIandIIareindependentcauses"},{"question":"Statements:  The prices of vegetables have been increased considerably during this summer. There is tremendous increase in the temperature during this summer thereby damaging crops greatly. ","options":{"A":"StatementIisthecauseandstatementIIisitseffect","B":"StatementIIisthecauseandstatementIisitseffect","C":"BoththestatementsIandIIareindependentcauses","D":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofindependentcauses","E":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofsomecommoncause"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"StatementIIisthecauseandstatementIisitseffect"},{"question":"Statements:  There has been a high increase in the incidents of atrocities against women in the city during the past few months. The police authority has been unable to nab the culprits who are committing crime against women. ","options":{"A":"StatementIisthecauseandstatementIIisitseffect","B":"StatementIIisthecauseandstatementIisitseffect","C":"BoththestatementsIandIIareindependentcauses","D":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofindependentcauses","E":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofsomecommoncause"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"BoththestatementsIandIIareindependentcauses"},{"question":"Statements:  Rural and semi-urban areas in the country have been suffering due to load shedding for quite some time. If the Government is not able to overcome the power crisis, load shedding will be extended even to the urban areas. ","options":{"A":"StatementIisthecauseandstatementIIisitseffect","B":"StatementIIisthecauseandstatementIisitseffect","C":"BoththestatementsIandIIareindependentcauses","D":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofindependentcauses","E":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofsomecommoncause"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofsomecommoncause"},{"question":"Statements:  The university authority has instructed all the colleges under its jurisdiction to ban use of all phones inside the college premises. Majority of the teachers of the colleges signed a joint petition to the university complaining the disturbances caused by cell phone ring-tones inside the classrooms. ","options":{"A":"StatementIisthecauseandstatementIIisitseffect","B":"StatementIIisthecauseandstatementIisitseffect","C":"BoththestatementsIandIIareindependentcauses","D":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofindependentcauses","E":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofsomecommoncause"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"StatementIIisthecauseandstatementIisitseffect"},{"question":"Statements:  Most of the steel producing companies in the country have made considerable profit during the last financial year. Many Asian countries have been importing huge quantities of steel from India. ","options":{"A":"StatementIisthecauseandstatementIIisitseffect","B":"StatementIIisthecauseandstatementIisitseffect","C":"BoththestatementsIandIIareindependentcauses","D":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofindependentcauses","E":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofsomecommoncause"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"StatementIIisthecauseandstatementIisitseffect"},{"question":"Statements:  There is increase in water level of all the water tanks supplying drinking water to the city during the last fortnight. Most of the trains were cancelled last week due to water-logging on the tracks. ","options":{"A":"StatementIisthecauseandstatementIIisitseffect","B":"StatementIIisthecauseandstatementIisitseffect","C":"BoththestatementsIandIIareindependentcauses","D":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofindependentcauses","E":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofsomecommoncause"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BoththestatementsIandIIareeffectsofsomecommoncause"}],"course-of-action":[{"question":"Statement:  A large number of people in ward X of the city are diagnosed to be suffering from a fatal malaria type. Courses of Action:   The city municipal authority should take immediate steps to carry out extensive fumigation in ward X. The people in the area should be advised to take steps to avoid mosquito bites. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statement:  Severe drought is reported to have set in several parts of the country. Courses of Action:   Government should immediately make arrangement for providing financial assistance to those affected. Food, water and fodder should immediately be sent to all these areas to save the people and cattle. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  Since its launching in 1981, Vayudoot has so far accumulated losses amounting to Rs 153 crore. Courses of Action:   Vayudoot should be directed to reduce wasteful expenditure and to increase passenger fare. An amount of about Rs 300 crore should be provided to Vayudoot to make the airliner economically viable. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  Exporters in the capital are alleging that commercial banks are violating a Reserve Bank of India directive to operate a post shipment export credit denominated in foreign currency at international rates from January this year. Courses of Action:   The officers concerned in the commercial banks are to be suspended. The RBI should be asked to stop giving such directives to commercial banks. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  A large number of people die every year due to drinking polluted water during the summer. Courses of Action:   The government should make adequate arrangements to provide safe drinking water to all its citizens. The people should be educated about the dangers of drinking polluted water. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statement:  Most of those who study in premier engineering colleges in India migrate to developed nations for better prospects in their professional pursuits. Courses of Action:   All the students joining these colleges should be asked to sign a bond at the time of admission to the effect that they will remain in India at least for ten years after they complete education. All those students who desire to settle in the developed nations should be asked to pay entire cost of their education which the government subsidises. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  There is an unprecedented increase in migration of villagers to urban areas as repeated crop failure has put them into precarious financial situation. Courses of Action:   The villagers should be provided with alternate source of income in their villages which will make them stay put. The migrated villagers should be provided with jobs in the urban areas to help them survive. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  As stated in the recent census report the female to male ratio is alarmingly low. Courses of Action:   The government should conduct another census to verify the results. The government should immediately issue orders to all the departments to encourage people to improve the ratio. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  Four districts in State A have been experiencing severe drought for the last three years resulting into exodus of people from these districts. Courses of Action:   The government should immediately start food for work programme in the district to put a halt to the exodus. The government should make since efforts to provide drinking/potable water to these districts ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statement:  If the retired Professors of the same Institutes are also invited to deliberate on restructuring of the organisation, their contribution may be beneficial to the Institute. Courses of Action:   Management may seek opinion of the employees before calling retired professors. Management should involve experienced people for the systematic restructuring of the organisation. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  The sale of a particular product has gone down considerably causing great concern to the company. Courses of Action:   The company should make a proper study of rival products in the market. The price of the product should be reduced and quality improved. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  The Asian Development Bank has approved a $285 million loan to finance a project to construct coal ports by Paradip and Madras Port Trusts. Courses of Action:   India should use financial assistance from other international financial organisations to develop such ports in other places. India should not seek such financial assistance from the international financial agencies. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  Doordarshan is concerned about the quality of its programmes particularly in view of stiff competition it is facing from STAR and other satellite TV channels and is contemplating various measures to attract talent for its programmes. Courses of Action:   In an effort to attract talent, the Doordarshan has decided to revise its fee structure for the artists. The fee structure should not be revised until other electronic media also revise it. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  The Minister said that the teachers are still not familiarised with the need, importance and meaning of population education in the higher education system. They are not even clearly aware about their role and responsibilities in the population education programme. Courses of Action:   Population education programme should be included in the college curriculum. Orientation programme should be conducted for teachers on population education ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  A recent study shows that children below five die in the cities of the developing countries mainly from diarrhoea and parasitic intestinal worms. Courses of Action:   Governments of the developing countries should take adequate measures to improve the hygienic conditions in the cities. Children below five years in the cities of the developing countries need to be kept under periodic medical check-up. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statement:  The kharif crops have been affected by the insects for consecutive three years in the district and the farmers harvested less than fifty percent of produce during these years. Courses of Action:   The farmers should seek measures to control the attack of insects to protect their crops next year. The Government should increase the support price of kharif crops considerably to protect the economic interests of farmers. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statement:  The car dealer found that there was a tremendous response for the new XYZ's car-booking with long queues of people complaining about the duration of business hours and arrangements. Courses of Action:   People should make their arrangement of lunch and snacks while going for car XYZ's booking and be ready to spend several hours. Arrangement should be made for more booking desks and increased business hours to serve more people in less time. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  The State Government has decided to declare 'Kala Azar' as a notifiable disease under the Epidemics Act. Family members or neighbours of the patient are liable to be punished in case they did not inform the State authorities. Courses of Action:   Efforts should be made to effectively implement the Act. The cases of punishment should be propagated through mass media so that more people become aware of the stern actions. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statement:  The Chairman stressed the need for making education system more flexible and regretted that the curriculum has not been revised in keeping with the pace of the changes taking place. Courses of Action:   Curriculum should be reviewed and revised periodically. System of education should be made more flexible. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statement:  The Central Bureau of Investigation receives the complaint of an officer taking bribe to do the duty he is supposed to. Courses of Action:   CBI should try to catch the officer red-handed and then take a strict action against him. CBI should wait for some more complaints about the officer to be sure about the matter. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  The Indian electronic component industry venturing into the West European markets faces tough competition from the Japanese. Courses of Action:   India should search for other international markets for its products. India should improve the quality of the electronic components to compete with the Japanese in capturing these markets. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  Orissa and Andhra Pradesh have agreed in principle to set up a joint control board for better control, management and productivity of several inter-state multipurpose projects. Courses of Action:   Other neighbouring states should set up such control boards. The proposed control board should not be allowed to function as such joint boards are always ineffective. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  The Government has decided not to provide financial support to voluntary organisations from next Five Year Plan and has communicated that all such organisations should raise funds to meet their financial needs. Courses of Action:   Voluntary organisations should collaborate with foreign agencies. They should explore other sources of financial support. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  The availability of imported fruits has increased in the indigenous market and so the demand for indigenous fruits has been decreased. Courses of Action:   To help the indigenous producers of fruits, the Government should impose high import duty on these fruits, even if these are not of good quality. The fruit vendors should stop selling imported fruits. So that the demand for indigenous fruits would be increased. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  There has been an unprecedented increase in the number of successful candidates in this year's School Leaving Certificate Examination. Courses of Action:   The government should make arrangements to increase number of seats of intermediate courses in existing colleges. The government should take active steps to open new colleges to accommodate all these successful candidates. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  On an average, about twenty people are run over by trains and die every day while crossing the railway tracks through the level crossing. Courses of Action:   The railway authorities should be instructed to close all the level crossings. Those who are found crossing the tracks, when the gates are closed, should be fined heavily ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  Majority of the students in many schools do not pass in the final examination. Courses of Action:   These schools should be closed down as these have become unproductive. The teachers of these schools should immediately be retrenched. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  In spite of the Principal's repeated warnings, a child was caught exploding crackers secretly in the school. Courses of Action:   All the crackers should be taken away from the child and he should be threatened not to do it again. The child should be severely punished for his wrong act. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  It is necessary to adopt suitable measures to prevent repetition of bad debts by learning from the past experiences of mounting non-performing assets of banks. Courses of Action:   Before granting loan to customers their eligibility for loan should be evaluated strictly. To ensure the payment of instalments of loan, the work, for which loan was granted, should be supervised minutely on regular basis. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statement:  A very large number of students have failed in the final high school examination due to faulty questions in one of the subjects. Courses of Action:   All the students who have failed in the subject should be allowed to take supplementary examination. All those who are responsible for the error should be suspended and an enquiry should be initiated to find out the facts. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statement:  A large number of engineering graduates in the country are not in a position to have gainful employment at present and the number of such engineers is likely to grow in the future. Courses of Action:   The government should launch attractive employment generation schemes and encourage these graduates to opt for such schemes to use their expertise and knowledge effectively. This happened due to proliferation of engineering colleges in the country and thereby lowered the quality of the engineering graduates. Those colleges which are not equipped to impart quality education should be closed down. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  Every year, at the beginning or at the end of the monsoons, we have some cases of conjunctivitis, but this year, it seems to be a major epidemic, witnessed after nearly four years. Courses of Action:   Precautionary measures should be taken after every four years to check this epidemic. People should be advised to drink boiled water during rainy season. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  Every year large number of devotees dies due to severe cold on their way to the shrine located at the top of the mountain range. Courses of Action:   The devotees should be discouraged to visit the shrine without having proper warm clothes and other amenities. The government should provide warm clothes and shelter to all the devotees visiting the shrine. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  There has been an unprecedented increase in the number of requests for berths in most of the long distance trains during the current holiday season. Courses of Action:   The railway authority should immediately increase the capacity in each of these trains by attaching additional coaches. The people seeking accommodation should be advised to make their travel plan after the holiday. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  The Finance Minister submits his resignation a month before the new budget is to be presented in the Parliament. Courses of Action:   The resignation should be accepted and another person should be appointed as the Finance Minister. The resignation should not be accepted. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  A large number of people visiting India from country X have been tested positive for carrying viruses of a killer disease. Courses of Action:   The government of India should immediately put a complete ban on people coming to India from country X including those Indians who are settled in country X. The government of India should immediately set up detection centres at all its airports and seaports to identify and quarantine those who are tested positive. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  There has been less than forty percent voter turnout in the recent assembly elections. Courses of Action:   The election commission should cancel the entire election process as the votes cast are not adequate to represent people. The election commission should take away the voting rights of those who did not exercise their rights. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  Most of the development plans develop in papers only. Courses of Action:   The in-charges should be instructed to supervise the field-work regularly. The supply of paper to such departments should be cut short. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  The vegetable traders feel that the prices of onion will again go up shortly in the State 'P' Courses of Action:   The 'P' State Government should purchase and store sufficient quantity of onion in advance to control prices. The 'F' State Government should make available network of fair price shops for the sale of onions during the period of shortage. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statement:  It is reported that though Vitamin E present in fresh fruits and vegetables is beneficial for human body, capsule Vitamin E does not have the same effect on human body. Courses of Action:   The sale of capsule Vitamin E should be banned. People should be encouraged to take fresh fruits and vegetables to meet the body's requirement of Vitamin E. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  Youngsters are often found staring at obscene posters. Courses of Action:   Children should be punished and penalized if they are found doing so. Any display of such material should be banned. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  One of the problems facing the food processing industry is the irregular supply of raw material. The producers of raw material are not getting a reasonable price. Courses of Action:   The government should regulate the supply of raw material to other industries also. The government should announce an attractive package to ensure regular supply of raw material for food processing industry. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  The Committee has criticized the Institute for its failure to implement a dozen of regular programmes despite an increase in the staff strength and not drawing up a firm action plan for studies and research. Courses of Action:   The broad objectives of the Institute should be redefined to implement a practical action plan. The Institute should give a report on reasons for not having implemented the planned programmes. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statement:  India has been continuously experiencing military threats from its neighbouring countries. Courses of Action:   India should engage into an all out war to stop the nagging threats. India should get the neighbours into a serious dialogue to reduce the tension at its borders. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  As many as ten coaches of a passenger train have derailed and blocked both pairs of the railway tracks. Courses of Action:   The railway authorities should immediately send men and equipment to the spot to clear the railway tracks. All the trains running in both the directions should be diverted to other routes. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statement:  There has been a significant drop in the water level of all the lakes supplying water to the city. Courses of Action:   The water supply authority should impose a partial cut in supply to tackle the situation. The government should appeal to all the residents through mass media for minimal use of water. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statement:  The police department has come under a cloud with recent revelations that at least two senior police officials are suspected to have been involved in the illegal sale of a large quantity of weapons from the state police armoury. Courses of Action:   A thorough investigation should be ordered by the State Government to bring out all those who are involved into the illegal sale of arms. State police armoury should be kept under Central Government's control. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  Financial stringency prevented the State Government from paying salaries to its employees since April this year. Courses of Action:   The State Government should immediately curtail the staff strength at least by 30%. The State Government should reduce wasteful expenditure and arrange to pay the salaries of its employees. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  The cinema halls are incurring heavy losses these days as people prefer to watch movies in home on TV than to visit cinema halls. Courses of Action:   The cinema halls should be demolished and residential multi-storey buildings should be constructed there. The cinema halls should be converted into shopping malls. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  Duty free technology parks where foreign firms can manufacture electronic hardware components are proposed to be established at various places in the country. Courses of Action:   Government should immediately implement the proposal to augment the foreign currency reserve by exporting the products. Government should not implement the proposal as it will hinder indigenous production of hardware components. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  The Secretary lamented that the electronic media was losing its credibility and that it should try to regain it by establishing better communications with the listeners and the viewers. He also emphasised the need for training to improve the functioning. Courses of Action:   Efforts should be made to get organised feed back on the programme. The critical areas in which the staff requires training should be identified. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statement:  Courts take too long in deciding important disputes of various departments. Courses of Action:   Courts should be ordered to speed up matters. Special powers should be granted to officers to settle disputes concerning their department. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statement:  Certain mining industries in Gujarat may come to a standstill because of the notification issued by the Department of Environment and Forest banning mining operations and industries alike within 25 kms of National Park, the game sanctuary and reserve forest areas. Courses of Action:   The Department should be asked to immediately withdraw the notification. The Government should make effort to shift the parks, sanctuaries and reserve forests to other non-mining areas. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  There have been many instances of derailment of trains due to landslide in the hilly areas which caused loss of many lives. Courses of Action:   The railway authority should arrange to deploy pilot engines before the movement of passenger trains in the hilly areas to alert the trains in case of any landslide. The railway authority should strengthen the hill slopes by putting iron meshes so that the loose boulders do not fall on the track. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"EitherIorIIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  India today is midstream in its demographic transaction. In the last 60 years there has been an almost continuous decline in mortality; while fertility has declined over the last 20 years. The consequence is that there has been a rapid growth in population over the last 50 years. Courses of Action:   India should immediately revitalise its family planning programme. The Government should immediately launch a massive education programme through mass media highlighting the implication of population growth at the present rate. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statement:  Footpaths of a busy road are crowded with vendors selling cheap items. Courses of Action:   The help of police should be sought to drive them away. Some space should be provided to them where they can earn their bread without blocking footpaths. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statement:  Some serious blunders were detected in the Accounts section of a factory. Courses of Action:   An efficient team of auditors should be appointed to check the Accounts. A show cause notice should be issued to all the employees involved in the irregularity. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statement:  Researchers are feeling agitated as libraries are not equipped to provide the right information to the right users at the right time in the required format. Even the users are riot aware about the various services available for them. Courses of Action:   All the information available to the libraries should be computerised to provide faster services to the users. Library staff should be trained in computer operations. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statement:  Many medical and engineering graduates are taking up jobs in administrative services and in banks.  Courses of Action:   All the professionals should be advised to refrain from taking up such jobs. The government should appoint a committee to find out the reasons for these professionals taking up such jobs and to suggest remedial measures. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  Due to substantial reduction in fares by different airline services, large number of passengers so far travelling by upper classes in trains have switched over to airline services. Courses of Action:   The railways should immediately reduce the fare structure of the upper classes substantially to retain its passengers. The railways should reduce the capacity of upper classes in all the trains to avoid loss. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  The Meteorology Department has forecast that a severe cyclonic storm would hit coastal Andhra Pradesh and Orissa in the next forty-eight hours. Courses of Action:   The local administration should advise the fishermen not to go to dangerous area in the sea. The local administration should alert the people of coastal areas of these two states and they should be prepared to shift to safer places. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statement:  There has been large number of cases of internet hacking in the recent months creating panic among the internet users. Courses of Action:   The government machinery should make an all out effort to nab those who are responsible and put them behind bars. The internet users should be advised to stay away from using internet till the culprits are caught. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  The Union Ministry of Tourism and Civil Aviation has fixed an annual target of Rs 10,000 crores by way of tourism earnings towards the end of the current decade. Courses of Action:   There is no need of development of further new tourist spots to meet the target. The Ministry should evolve attractive packages to woo the foreign tourists to meet the target. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  A large number of students have been caught using unfair means during the final-year degree examination. Courses of Action:   All these students should be debarred permanently from appearing for any examination conducted by the authority. The guardians of these students should be called by the authority to inform them that any such behaviour in future will not be tolerated. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  The alert villagers caught a group of dreaded dacoits armed with murderous weapons. Courses of Action:   The villagers should be provided sophisticated weapons. The villagers should be rewarded for their courage and unity. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  The employees union of the Municipal Corporation has decided to strike work for indefinite period in protest against the management's refusal to grant bonus. Courses of Action:   The government should immediately pay ex-gratia grant to the Municipal Corporation to grant bonus to its employees. The striking employees should be persuaded to defer the strike notice. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  The killer entric fever has so far claimed 100 lives in some tribal villages in M.P. during the past three weeks. Courses of Action:   The residents of these villages should immediately be shifted to a non-infected area. The Government should immediately send a medical squad to this area to restrict spread of the killer disease. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  There is a substantial increase in the number of accidents causing deaths and severe injuries due to malfunctioning of the traffic signals. Courses of Action:   The traffic police should immediately post traffic personnel at the junctions. The signal system should immediately be repaired or replaced. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"EitherIorIIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  India's performance in the recent Olympic Games was very poor. Not even a single medal could be bagged by the players. Government has spent Rs. 5 crores in training and deputing a team of players to participate in the Olympic Games. Courses of Action:   India should stop sending players to the future Olympic Games. Government should immediately set up an enquiry commission to find out the reason for India's dismal performance. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  Three persons were caught with huge arms and ammunition in the city. Courses of Action:   Police should be instructed for night patrolling. The three persons should be set free and their movements should be carefully watched to nab the other criminals. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  Majority of the students have failed in one paper in the first semester examination. Courses of Action:   All those students who failed should be asked to drop out of the course. The faculty teaching the paper should be asked to resign. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  Mr. X, an active member of the Union, often insults his superiors in the office with his rude behaviour. Courses of Action:   He should be transferred to some other department. The matter should be referred to the Union. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  The weather bureau has through a recent bulletin forecast heavy rainfall during the next week which may cause water logging in several parts of the city. Courses of Action:   The bulletin should be given wide publicity through the mass media. The civic authority should keep in readiness the pumping system for removal of water from these parts. The people should be advised to stay indoors during the period. ","options":{"A":"Nonefollows","B":"OnlyIandIIfollow","C":"OnlyIIfollows","D":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow"},{"question":"Statement:  A train derailed near a station while moving over a bridge and fell into a river, resulting in the death of 65 people. Courses of Action:   The Railway Authorities should clarify the reason of the accident to the Government. The Government should allocate funds to compensate the destruction caused.                    The protection walls of the bridge should be made strong enough to avoid such accidents. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIfollow","B":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","C":"OnlyIIIfollows","D":"Allfollow","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyIIIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  Poverty is increasing because the people, who are deciding how to tackle it, know absolutely nothing about the poor. Courses of Action:   The decision makers should go to the grass root levels. The decision makers should come from the poorer sections of the society. A new set of decision makers should replace the existing one. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"OnlyeitherIorIIIfollows","D":"Allfollow"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  Besides looks and appearances, it is also important to develop oneself from within. Courses of Action:   One should not pay attention to fashion. One should pay attention to fashion. Books on self-development should be encouraged. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"OnlyIIIfollows","D":"OnlyIandIIIfollow"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyIIIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  There is an unprecedented increase in the production of wheat this kharif season in most parts of the country. Courses of Action:   The government should immediately lower down the procurement price of wheat. The farmers should be asked to store the excess produces with themselves to be used for future. The government should make its best efforts to export wheat to augment its presence in international market. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIfollow","B":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","C":"OnlyIandIIIfollow","D":"Allfollow","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Noneofthese"},{"question":"Statement:  A large number of students are reported to be dropping out of school in villages as their parents want their children to help them in farms. Courses of Action:   The government should immediately launch a programme to create awareness among the farmers about the value of education. The government should offer incentives to those farmers whose children remain in schools. Education should be made compulsory for all children up to the age of 14 and their employment banned. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIfollow","B":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","C":"OnlyIandIIIfollow","D":"Allfollow","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Allfollow"},{"question":"Statement:  Without the active cooperation between the proprietor and the employees of the mill, it cannot remain a profitable concern for long. Courses of Action:   The mill should be closed down. The workers should be asked to cooperate with the owners. The owners should be asked to cooperate with the employees. ","options":{"A":"Nonefollows","B":"OnlyIandIIfollow","C":"Allfollow","D":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow"},{"question":"Statement:  The air and rail services have been severely disrupted due to thick fog in the northern part of the country. Courses of Action:   The rail and air services should be temporarily suspended in the region. People should be advised to make their travel plan keeping in mind the probable disruption resulting in delay or cancellation of services. The government should immediately install modern machines which will enable it to guide the rail and air services even if the thick fog develops. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIIfollows","B":"OnlyIIIfollows","C":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","D":"Allfollow","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Allfollow"},{"question":"Statement:  There are more than 200 villages in the hill area of Uttar Pradesh which are severely damaged due to cyclone and it causes an extra burden of Rs 200 crore on State Government for relief and rehabilitation work. Courses of Action:   People of hill area should be shifted to other safer places. State Government should ask more financial support from Central Government. Government should levy relief tax to the corporate sector to ease the additional burden. ","options":{"A":"Nonefollows","B":"OnlyIandIIfollow","C":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","D":"OnlyIandIIIfollow","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Noneofthese"},{"question":"Statement:  Any further increase in the pollution level in the city by way of industrial effluents and automobile exhaustions would pose a severe threat to the inhabitants. Courses of Action:   All the factories in the city should immediately be closed down. The automobiles should not be allowed to ply on the road for more than four hours a day. The Government should restrict the issue of fresh licences to factories and automobiles. ","options":{"A":"Nonefollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"OnlyIIIfollows","D":"Allfollows","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyIIIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  Lack of coordination between the University, its colleges and various authorities has resulted in students ousted from one college seeking migration to another. Courses of Action:   If a student is ousted from a college, the information should be sent to all the other colleges of the University The admissions to all the colleges of the University should be handled by the University directly. A separate section should be made for taking strict action against students indulging in anti-social activities. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"OnlyIIIfollows","D":"OnlyIandIIIfollow","E":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  Over 27,000 bonded labourers identified and freed are still awaiting rehabilitation. Courses of Action:   More cases of bonded labourers should be identified. Till the proper rehabilitation facilities are available, the bonded labourers should not be freed. The impediments in the way of speedy and proper rehabilitation of bonded labourers should be removed. ","options":{"A":"Nonefollows","B":"OnlyIfollows","C":"OnlyIIfollows","D":"OnlyIIIfollows","E":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"OnlyIIIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  Number of dropouts from the municipal schools has significantly increased after withdrawal of mid-day meal scheme. Courses of Action:   The government should reconsider its decision of withdrawal of midday meal scheme.The government should close down some of the municipal schools. The government should carry out a detailed study to find out the reasons for school dropouts.  ","options":{"A":"Nonefollows","B":"OnlyIfollows","C":"OnlyIandIIIfollow","D":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","E":"Allfollow"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyIandIIIfollow"},{"question":"Statement:  There has been unprecedented increase in the prices of essential commodities during the past few days due to the strike call given by the transporters association. Courses of Action:   The transporters' association should be ordered by the government to immediately withdraw strike call or else they will face severe consequences. The government should immediately make alternative arrangements to ensure adequate supply of essential commodities in the market. The government should immediately declare the strike illegal and put all those responsible for the strike behind the bars. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIfollow","B":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","C":"OnlyIandIIIfollow","D":"Allfollow","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statement:  A large number of students studying in municipal schools could not pass the Xth Std. Board examination causing frustration among the students and their parents. Courses of Action:   The Municipal authority should immediately review the position and initiate measures to improve the situation. The municipal authority should immediately fill up the teachers' vacancies in the municipal schools. The municipal authority should close down some of their schools and concentrate their attention on remaining schools to improve the conditions. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIfollow","B":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","C":"OnlyIandIIIfollow","D":"Allfollow","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Noneofthese"},{"question":"Statement:  Incessant rain for the past several days has posed the problem of overflowing and flood as the river bed is full of silt and mud. Courses of Action:   The people residing near the river should be shifted to a safe place. The people should be made aware about the imminent danger over radio/television. The silt and mud from the river bed should be cleared immediately after the receding of the water level. ","options":{"A":"Nonefollows","B":"OnlyIandllfollow","C":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","D":"OnlyIandIIIfollow","E":"Allfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Allfollow"},{"question":"Statement:  Some strains of mosquito have become resistant to chloroquine - the widely used medicine for malaria patients. Courses of Action:   Selling of chloroquine should be stopped. Researchers should develop a new medicine for patients affected by such mosquitoes. All the patients suffering from malaria should be checked for identification of causal mosquito. ","options":{"A":"Nonefollows","B":"OnlyIandIIIfollow","C":"Allfollow","D":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow"},{"question":"Statement:  Many private sector banks have reduced interest rate on housing loans in comparison to public sector banks. Courses of Action:   The case should be raised before the regulatory authority for investigation by the public sector banks as they cannot follow such reduction. Public sector banks must adopt such policy to remain in competition. The public sector banks should advertise their special feature repeatedly so that they do not lose their future customers. ","options":{"A":"Allfollow","B":"OnlyIandIIfollow","C":"OnlyIandIIIfollow","D":"OnlyeitherIIorIIIfollows","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"OnlyeitherIIorIIIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  The Deputy Mayor of city Z has proposed to install a plant of mineral water and to supply citizen's mineral water bottles at Rs. 6 per litre as against Rs. 10 per litre being sold by local private companies. Courses of Action:   The local private companies of city Z will have to close their operation. The Corporation of city Z will have to provide for losses in this project in its budget. The tap water schemes of city Z will have to be stopped. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIfollow","B":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","C":"OnlyIandIIIfollow","D":"Allfollow","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Noneofthese"},{"question":"Statement:  The meteorological department has issued a notification forecasting less rainfall during next year's monsoon. Courses of Action:   The government should immediately set up a water authority for proper management of water resources. The water supply authorities should be asked to implement reduction in regular water supply to tackle the situation. The farmers should be advised to cultivate alternate crops which require less water during the coming months. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIfollow","B":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","C":"OnlyIandIIIfollow","D":"Allfollow","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statement:  There was a spurt in criminal activities in the city during the recent festival season. Courses of Action:   The police should immediately investigate into the causes of this increase. In future the police should take adequate precaution to avoid recurrence of such situation during festival. The known criminals should be arrested before any such season. ","options":{"A":"Nonefollows","B":"OnlyIandIIfollow","C":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","D":"Allfollows","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statement:  A large number of students who have passed their XII Std. terminal examination in the country could not get admission to colleges as the number of seats available are grossly inadequate. Courses of Action:   The evaluation system of XII Std. terminal examination should be made more tough so that fewer students pass the examination. The Government should encourage the private sector to open new colleges by providing them land at cheaper rate. The rich people should be asked to send their wards to foreign countries for higher studies enabling the needy students to get admission in colleges within the country. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"OnlyIandIIfollow","D":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  It has been reported by one of the TV channels that the answer papers of Board examination of one State are evaluated by students studying in the same standard with the help of model answers as instructed by the examiners. Courses of Action:   All such examiners should be immediately suspended from their official positions. All such papers evaluated by the students should be immediately confiscated and got evaluated by qualified teachers. The Board should explore possibilities even though they are remote, of getting the answer papers of this examination evaluated by computerised machines. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"OnlyIIIfollows","D":"OnlyIandIIfollow","E":"Allfollow"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"OnlyIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statement:  The condition of all the major roads in the city has deteriorated due to incessant rain during the last two months. Courses of Action:   The city civic authority should deploy additional traffic staff to regulate the vehicular movement. The city civic authority should immediately make arrangements for repairs of the damaged roads. Motorists should be alerted at various places by putting up sign boards about the bad patches of the roads to enable them to plan their journey accordingly. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIfollow","B":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","C":"OnlyIandIIIfollow","D":"Allfollow","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Allfollow"},{"question":"Statement:  There have been quite a few incidents of highway robbery on the super expressway between/cities A and B during recent months. Courses of Action:   The local administration should immediately set up police tickets along the expressway to prevent robbery. The local administration should immediately close down the expressway till the robbers are apprehended. More and more people should be given training on how to tackle with the robbers. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIandIIfollow","C":"OnlyIandIIIfollow","D":"Allfollow","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  The Institute has fixed for the investors a validity period of one year for transfer forms for some of its listed schemes. Courses of Action:   The Institute should consult investors before fixing the duration of validity period. The investors should be duly informed about the validity period. List of schemes covered under this validity period should be communicated. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIfollow","B":"OnlyIIIfollows","C":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","D":"OnlyIandIIIfollow","E":"Allfollow"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow"},{"question":"Statement:  The vehicular traffic has increased so much in the recent past that it takes at least two hours to travel between the city and the airport during peak hours. Courses of Action:   Non-airport bound vehicles should not be allowed to ply on the road connecting the city and the airport. The load of vehicular traffic should be diverted through various link roads during peak hours. The departure and arrival of flights should be regulated so as to .avoid congestion during peak hours. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"OnlyIandIIfollow","D":"Allfollow","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  There is a considerable increase in the number of persons affected by water-borne diseases during monsoon period. Courses of Action:   The question should be raised in the Legislative Assembly. The Government should disseminate adequate information regarding the pure drinking water to people. All the hospitals in the city should be equipped properly for the treatment of patients during monsoon period.  ","options":{"A":"Allfollow","B":"OnlyIandIIfollow","C":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","D":"OnlyIandIIIfollow","E":"Nonefollows"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow"},{"question":"Statement:  Residents from Model Colony coming under North Ward of City X have complained to the Ward Officer that for last three days the tap water in the ward is contaminated and no action is being initiated by municipal staff. Courses of Action:   The Ward Officer of North Ward should initiate action against residents who have lodged complaints against municipal staff. The Ward Officer should ask his junior officer to visit Model Colony to assess the actual condition of water with his staff and to get samples of water tested from laboratories. The Ward Officer should ask Ward Engineer to check water installations and pipelines in the Model Colony area. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIfollow","B":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","C":"OnlyIandIIIfollow","D":"OnlyeitherIorIII,andIIfollow","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow"},{"question":"Statement:  People residing in some tribal areas are far from education. Courses of Action:   Government should render all help to the NGOs to open schools there. A mass awareness programme must be initiated in these areas. Social workers should be entrusted with the job of educating them. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIfollow","B":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","C":"OnlyIandIIIfollow","D":"OnlyeitherIorIII,andIIfollow","E":"Allfollow"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statement:  The exodus from villages to cities is detrimental to both. Courses of Action:   Rural postings must be made mandatory. There should be fewer trains linking cities to smaller places. Employment generation scheme should be launched in rural areas. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIIfollows","B":"OnlyIandIIfollow","C":"OnlyIIIfollows","D":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyIIIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  Major part of the rabi crop in the district is damaged due to unseasonal heavy rains during the last few days. Courses of Action:   The government should grant relief to the affected farmers to compensate their loss. The government should provide free seed and fertilizer to the farmers for the kharif season. The government should waive all the loans taken for the rabi crop by the affected farmers. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIfollow","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","D":"OnlyIIIfollows","E":"Allfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Allfollow"},{"question":"Statement:  Large number of people have become critically ill after consuming spurious liquor from a local shop. Courses of Action:   I. The Government should immediately close down all the shops selling liquor till the stocks are tested for presence of toxicity. II. The owner of the liquor shop should be asked to leave the town and open a shop elsewhere. III. The owner of the liquor shop should immediately be arrested and tried for criminal negligence. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIfollow","B":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","C":"OnlyIIIfollows","D":"OnlyIandIIIfollow","E":"Allfollow"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"OnlyIandIIIfollow"},{"question":"Statement:  Every year thousands of eligible students do not get admission in colleges both in urban and rural areas after passing their school leaving certificate examination. Courses of Action:   More colleges should be set up in both urban and rural areas. The number of schools in both urban and rural areas should be reduced. More schools should offer vocational courses to equip students for taking up their vocation after completing their school education. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","C":"OnlyIandIIIfollow","D":"Allfollow","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyIandIIIfollow"},{"question":"Statement:  According to the officials, paucity of funds with the organisation has led to the pathetic condition of this brilliant architectural structure. Courses of Action:   Anew architectural structure for the building should be designed. The reasons for the poor condition of the structure should be found out. Grant should be given to improve the condition of the structure. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"OnlyIIIfollows","D":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","E":"OnlyIandIIIfollow"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyIIIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  Nuclear power cannot make a country secure. Courses of Action:   We must stop further expenses on increasing our nuclear power. We must destroy our nuclear capability. We must concentrate on improving our diplomatic relations. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"OnlyIIIfollows","D":"OnlyIandIIIfollow"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyIIIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  There has been an unprecedented increase in use of malpractices by the students during various examinations held in the country this year. Courses of Action:   All the concerned authorities conducting these examinations should immediately take effective measures to curb this menace. All those students who are detected to have used unfair means should be debarred from appearing in any of these examinations for the next three years. Using unfair means should immediately be made cognizable offence by passing necessary legislations. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIandIIfollow","C":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","D":"OnlyIandIIIfollow","E":"Allfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statement:  In one of the worst accidents in railway level crossing, fifty people died when a bus carrying them collided on to a running train. Courses of Action:   The train driver should immediately be suspended. The driver of the bus should be tried in court for negligence on his part. The railway authority should be asked to man all its level crossings. ","options":{"A":"Nonefollows","B":"OnlyIandIIfollow","C":"OnlyIIIfollows","D":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyIIIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  A mass mortality of shrimps in ponds on entire Andhra coast has recently been reported due to the presence of a virus. Courses of Action:   The water of the ponds affected should immediately be treated for identifying the nature of the virus. The catching of shrimps from the ponds should temporarily be stopped. The fishermen should be asked to watch for the onset of such phenomenon in nature. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIandIIfollow","C":"Allfollow","D":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyIfollows"},{"question":"Statement:  Drinking water supply to New Bombay has been suspended till further orders from Maharashtra Pollution Control Board following pollution of Patalganga river, caused by discharge of effluents from some chemical industries. Courses of Action:   The industries responsible for discharging effluents into the river should be asked to close down immediately. The river water should immediately be treated chemically before resuming supply. The Pollution Control Board should check the nature of effluents being discharged into the river by industries at regular intervals. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","C":"OnlyIIIfollows","D":"Allfollow","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow"},{"question":"Statement:  The Management of School M has decided to give free breakfast from next academic year to all the students in its primary section through its canteen even though they will not get any government grant. Courses of Action:   The school will have to admit many poor students who will seek admission for the next academic year. The canteen facilities and utensils have to be checked and new purchases to be made to equip it properly. Funds will have to be raised to support the scheme for years to come. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyeitherIorIIfollows","C":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","D":"Allfollow","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow"},{"question":"Statement:  The day time temperatures in this summer have been four to five degree Celsius above the normal temperature across the country. Courses of Action:   All the district headquarters should be alerted to send prompt reports of death due to heat waves in their jurisdiction. The Government machinery should be put on high alert and provided with necessary equipments to prevent any untoward incident. The Government should make necessary arrangements to provide drinking water in all the areas affected due to extreme heat waves. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIandIIfollow","C":"Allfollow","D":"OnlyIIIfollows","E":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow"},{"question":"Statement:  The meteorological department has reported that a severe storm is likely to hit the city during the next forty-eight hours. Courses of Action:   The administration should advise all the business and educational establishments to close down for two days. The administration should not make the information public as it could create panic among the residents of the city. The administration should activate its disaster management program to tackle any possible emergency situation. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIfollow","B":"OnlyIIIfollows","C":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","D":"OnlyIandIIIfollow","E":"Allfollow"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"OnlyIandIIIfollow"},{"question":"Statement:  In the city, over 75 percent of the people are living in slums and sub-standard houses which is a reflection on the housing and urban development policies of the Government. Courses of Action:   I. There should be a separate department looking after housing and urban development. II. The policies in regard to urban housing should be reviewed. III. The policies regarding rural housing should also be reviewed so that such problems could be avoided in rural areas. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIandIIfollow","C":"OnlyIIfollows","D":"EitherIIorIIIfollows","E":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statement:  It is estimated that about twenty lakh people will visit the city during the ensuing festival. Courses of Action:   The civic authority should monitor the crowd and restrict entry of the people beyond a manageable number. The local police authority should be put on high alert to maintain law and order during the festival. All the hospitals in the city should be put on high alert in case of any eventuality. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIfollow","B":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","C":"OnlyIandIIIfollow","D":"Allfollow","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow"},{"question":"Statement:  The Company X has rejected first lot of values supplied by Company A and has cancelled its entire huge order quoting use of inferior quality material and poor craftsmanship. Courses of Action:   The Company A needs to investigate functioning of its purchase, production and quality control departments. The Company A should inspect all the valves rejected by Company X. The Company A should inform Company X that steps have been taken for improvement and renegotiate schedule of supply. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIfollow","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"II,andeitherIorIIIfollow","D":"AllI,IIandIIIfollow","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyIandIIfollow"}],"essential-part":[{"question":"harvest","options":{"A":"autumn","B":"stockpile","C":"tractor","D":"crop"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"crop"},{"question":"desert","options":{"A":"cactus","B":"arid","C":"oasis","D":"flat"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"arid"},{"question":"book","options":{"A":"fiction","B":"pages","C":"pictures","D":"learning"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"pages"},{"question":"language","options":{"A":"tongue","B":"slang","C":"writing","D":"words"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"words"},{"question":"school","options":{"A":"student","B":"reportcard","C":"test","D":"learning"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"student"},{"question":"ovation","options":{"A":"outburst","B":"bravo","C":"applause","D":"encore"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"applause"},{"question":"bonus","options":{"A":"reward","B":"raise","C":"cash","D":"employer"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"reward"},{"question":"antique","options":{"A":"rarity","B":"artifact","C":"aged","D":"prehistoric"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"aged"},{"question":"culture","options":{"A":"civility","B":"education","C":"agriculture","D":"customs"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"customs"},{"question":"knowledge","options":{"A":"school","B":"teacher","C":"textbook","D":"learning"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"learning"},{"question":"domicile","options":{"A":"tenant","B":"dwelling","C":"kitchen","D":"house"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"dwelling"},{"question":"vertebrate","options":{"A":"backbone","B":"reptile","C":"mammal","D":"animal"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"backbone"},{"question":"itinerary","options":{"A":"map","B":"route","C":"travel","D":"guidebook"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"route"},{"question":"orchestra","options":{"A":"violin","B":"stage","C":"musician","D":"soloist"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"musician"},{"question":"facsimile","options":{"A":"picture","B":"image","C":"mimeograph","D":"copier"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"image"},{"question":"provisions","options":{"A":"groceries","B":"supplies","C":"gear","D":"caterers"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"supplies"},{"question":"sustenance","options":{"A":"nourishment","B":"water","C":"grains","D":"menu"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"nourishment"},{"question":"infirmary","options":{"A":"surgery","B":"disease","C":"patient","D":"receptionist"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"patient"},{"question":"purchase","options":{"A":"trade","B":"money","C":"bank","D":"acquisition"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"acquisition"},{"question":"dimension","options":{"A":"compass","B":"ruler","C":"inch","D":"measure"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"measure"},{"question":"wedding","options":{"A":"love","B":"church","C":"ring","D":"marriage"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"marriage"},{"question":"faculty","options":{"A":"buildings","B":"textbooks","C":"teachers","D":"meetings"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"teachers"},{"question":"recipe","options":{"A":"desserts","B":"directions","C":"cookbook","D":"utensils"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"directions"},{"question":"autograph","options":{"A":"athlete","B":"actor","C":"signature","D":"pen"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"signature"},{"question":"cage","options":{"A":"enclosure","B":"prisoner","C":"animal","D":"zoo"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"enclosure"},{"question":"champion","options":{"A":"running","B":"swimming","C":"winning","D":"speaking"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"winning"},{"question":"saddle","options":{"A":"horse","B":"seat","C":"stirrups","D":"horn"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"seat"},{"question":"dome","options":{"A":"rounded","B":"geodesic","C":"governmental","D":"coppery"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"rounded"},{"question":"glacier","options":{"A":"mountain","B":"winter","C":"prehistory","D":"ice"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"ice"},{"question":"directory","options":{"A":"telephone","B":"listing","C":"computer","D":"names"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"listing"},{"question":"contract","options":{"A":"agreement","B":"document","C":"written","D":"attorney"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"agreement"},{"question":"hurricane","options":{"A":"beach","B":"cyclone","C":"damage","D":"wind"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"wind"},{"question":"town","options":{"A":"residents","B":"skyscrapers","C":"parks","D":"libraries"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"residents"},{"question":"vibration","options":{"A":"motion","B":"electricity","C":"science","D":"sound"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"motion"}],"letter-and-symbol-series":[{"question":"SCD, TEF, UGH, ____, WKL","options":{"A":"CMN","B":"UJI","C":"VIJ","D":"IJT"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"VIJ"},{"question":"B2CD, _____, BCD4, B5CD, BC6D","options":{"A":"B2C2D","B":"BC3D","C":"B2C3D","D":"BCD7"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"BC3D"},{"question":"FAG, GAF, HAI, IAH, ____","options":{"A":"JAK","B":"HAL","C":"HAK","D":"JAI"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"JAK"},{"question":"ELFA, GLHA, ILJA, _____, MLNA","options":{"A":"OLPA","B":"KLMA","C":"LLMA","D":"KLLA"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"KLLA"},{"question":"CMM, EOO, GQQ, _____, KUU","options":{"A":"GRR","B":"GSS","C":"ISS","D":"ITT"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"ISS"},{"question":"","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"3"},{"question":"","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"2"},{"question":"","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"1"},{"question":"","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"4"},{"question":"","options":{"A":"1","B":"2","C":"3","D":"4"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"1"}],"logical-deduction":[{"question":"Statement: Are nuclear families better than joint families? Arguments:     No. Joint families ensure security and also reduce the burden of work.     Yes. Nuclear families ensure greater freedom. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIarestrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should government stop spending huge amounts of money on international sports? Arguments:     Yes. This money can be utilized for upliftment of the poor.     No. Sports persons will be frustrated and will not get international exposure. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should the railways immediately stop issuing free passes to all its employees? Arguments:     No. The employees have the right to travel free.     Yes. This will help railways to provide better facility. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should there be compulsory medical examination of both the man and the woman before they marry each other? Arguments:     No. This is an intrusion to the privacy of an individual and hence cannot be tolerated.     Yes. This will substantially reduce the risk of giving birth to children with serious ailments. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should there be a ban on product advertising? Arguments:     No. It is an age of advertising. Unless your advertisement is better than your other competitors, the product will not be sold.     Yes. The money spent on advertising is very huge and it inflates the cost of the product. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIarestrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should luxury hotels be banned in India? Arguments:     Yes. They are places from where international criminals operate.     No. Affluent foreign tourists will have no place to stay. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should shifting agriculture be practised? Arguments:     No. It is a wasteful practice.     Yes. Modern methods of farming are too expensive. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should our country extend generous behaviour and goodwill to our erring and nagging neighbours? Arguments:     Yes. Goodwill always pays dividend.     No. Our generous behaviour and goodwill will be considered as our weakness. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIarestrong"},{"question":"Statement: Is pen mightier than a sword? Arguments:     Yes. Writers influence the thinking of the people.     No. With the help of physical force one can conquer all. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should the sex determination test during pregnancy be completely banned? Arguments:     Yes. This leads to indiscriminate female foeticide and eventually will lead to social imbalance.     No. People have a right to know about their unborn child. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should persons convicted of criminal offences in the past be allowed to contest elections in India? Arguments:     No. Such persons cannot serve the cause of the people and country.     Yes. It is democracy - let people decide whom to vote. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should officers accepting bribe be punished? Arguments:     No. Certain circumstances may have compelled them to take bribe.     Yes. They should do the job they are entrusted with, honestly. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should there be a complete ban on use of all types of chemical pesticides in India? Arguments:     No. The pests will destroy all the crops and the farmers will have nothing to harvest.     Yes. The chemical pesticides used in agriculture pollute the water underground and this has become a serious health hazard. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIarestrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should cutting of trees be banned altogether? Arguments:     Yes. It is very much necessary to do so to restore ecological balance.     No. A total ban would harm timber based industries. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIarestrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should there be a restriction on the migration of people from one state to another state in India? Arguments:     No. Any Indian citizen has a basic right to stay at any place of his/her choice and hence they cannot be stopped.     Yes. This is the way to effect an equitable distribution of resources across the states in India. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should all refugees, who make unauthorized entry into a country, be forced to go back to their homeland?                                                            Arguments:     Yes. They make their colonies and occupy a lot of land.     No. They leave their homes because of hunger or some terror and on human grounds, should not be forced to go back. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should India create a huge oil reserve like some Western countries to face difficult situations in future? Arguments:     No. There is no need to block huge amount of foreign exchange and keep the money idle.     Yes. This will help India withstand shocks of sudden rise in oil prices due to unforeseen circumstances. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should there be more than one High Court in each state in India? Arguments:     No. This will be a sheer wastage of taxpayers' money.     Yes. This will help reduce the backlog of cases pending for a very long time. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should judiciary be independent of the executive? Arguments:     Yes. This would help curb the unlawful activities of the executive.     No. The executive would not be able to take bold measures. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should all the practising doctors be brought under Government control so that they get salary from the Government and treat patients free of cost? Arguments:     No. How can any country do such an undemocratic thing?     Yes. Despite many problems, it will certainly help minimize, if not eradicate, unethical medical practices. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should students take part in politics? Arguments:     Yes. It inculcates in them qualities of leadership.     No. They should study and build up their career. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"EitherIorIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should the opinion polls predicting outcome of elections before the elections be banned in India? Arguments:     Yes. This may affect the voters mind and may affect the outcome.     No. Such polls are conducted all over the world. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should the political parties be banned? Arguments:     Yes. It is necessary to teach a lesson to the politicians.     No. It will lead to an end of democracy. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should system of offering jobs only to the wards of government employees be introduced in all government offices in India? Arguments:     No. It denies opportunity to many deserving individuals and government may stand to lose in the long run.     No. It is against the principle of equality, does not government owe its responsibility to all its citizens? ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIarestrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should the vehicles older than 15 years be rejected in metros in India? Arguments:     Yes. This is a significant step to lower down the pollution level in metros.     No. It will be very difficult for vehicle owners to shift to other parts in country because they will not get suitable job for their very existence. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should the tuition fees in all post-graduate courses be hiked considerably? Arguments:     Yes. This will bring in some sense of seriousness among the students and will improve the quality.     No. This will force the meritorious poor students to stay away from post-graduate courses. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should the persons below the age of 18 years be allowed to join armed forces? Arguments:     No. Persons below the age of 18 do not attain both physical and mental maturity to shoulder such burden.     Yes. This will help the country develop its armed forces which will serve the country for a longer time. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should all the infrastructural development projects in India be handed over to the private sector? Arguments:     No. The private sector entities are hot equipped to handle such projects.     Yes. Such projects are handled by private sector in the developed countries. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should all the colleges in India be allowed to devise their own curriculum and syllabus for the vocational courses promoting self-employment? Arguments:     Yes. This is an important step to generate employment opportunities.     No. This will affect the quality of education due to lack of uniformity in syllabus. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should agriculture in rural India be mechanized? Arguments:     Yes. It would lead to higher production.     No. Many villagers would be left unemployed. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should there be concentration of foreign investment in only few states? Arguments:     No. It is against the policy of overall development of the country.     Yes. A large number of states lack infrastructure to attract foreign investment. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should the oil companies be allowed to fix the price of petroleum products depending on market conditions? Arguments:     Yes. This is the only way to make the oil companies commercially viable.     No. This will put additional burden on the retail prices of essential commodities and will cause a lot of hardships to the masses. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should the education at all levels be offered only in vernacular medium? Arguments:     Yes. This is the only way to enhance performance of the students.     No. This will severely affect acquiring knowledge for want of good text books in vernacular medium. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should there be only one rate of interest for term deposits of varying durations in banks? Arguments:     No. People will refrain from keeping money for longer duration resulting into reduction of liquidity level of banks.     Yes. This will be much simple for the common people and they may be encouraged to keep more money in banks. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should all news be controlled by Government in a democracy? Arguments:     Yes. Variety of news only confuses people.     No. Controlled news loses credibility. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should taxes on colour television be further increased? Arguments:     Yes, Colour television is a luxury item and only rich people buy them.     No, Televisions are bought by the poor too. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should the educated unemployed youth be paid \"unemployment allowance\" by the Government? Arguments:     Yes. It will provide them some monetary help to either seek employment or to kick-start some 'self-employment' venture.     No. It will dampen their urge to do something to earn their livelihood and thus promote idleness among the unemployed youth. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIarestrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should higher education be restricted to only those who can bear the expenditure? Arguments:     Yes. Higher education is very costly; hence it should not be given free.     No. There are a large number of brilliant students who cannot afford to pay and they should be given higher education. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should those who receive dowry, despite the law prohibiting it, be punished? Arguments:     Yes. Those who violate the law must be punished.     No. Dowry system is firmly rooted in the society since time immemorial. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Is the Government justified in spending so much on defence? Arguments:     Yes. Safety of the country is of prime importance.     No. During peace, this money could be used for the development of the country. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should girls learn arts like judo and karate? Arguments:     Yes. It will enable them to defend themselves from rogues and ruffians.     No. They will lose their feminine grace. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should India develop a national water grid by connecting all the rivers in the country? Arguments:     No. This is not just possible as we do not have the technical knowhow.     Yes, this will greatly help the entire country by effectively channelizing the excess water to the areas having shortage. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should individuals/institutes having treasures of national significance like Nobel Prizes, hand them over to the Central Government for their safe custody? Arguments:     Yes. The individuals or institutions do not have enough resources to protect them.     No. These are the property of the individuals/institutions who win them and should be in their custody. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should there be reservation of seats and posts on communal basis? Arguments:     Yes. It will check most of the inter-communal biases.     No, ours is a secular state. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should octroi be abolished? Arguments:     Yes. It will eliminate an important source of corruption.     No. It will adversely affect government revenues. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIarestrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should public holidays be declared on demise of important national leaders? Arguments:     No. Such unscheduled holidays hamper national progress.     Yes. People would like to pay their homage to the departed soul. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should India support all the international policies of United States of America? Arguments:     No. Many other powerful countries do not support the same.     Yes. This is the only way to gain access to USA developmental funds. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should words like 'Smoking is injurious to health essentially appear on cigarette packs? Arguments:     Yes. It is a sort of brainwash to make the smokers realize that they are inhaling poisonous stuff.     No. It hampers the enjoyment of smoking. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should the council of ministers once appointed be kept the same for the entire period intervening two elections? Arguments:     No. Shuffling of ministers and portfolios is a healthy democratic process.     Yes. The ministers do not get a hold on their portfolio unless they are kept for a longer duration. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statements:  All branches are flowers. All flowers are leaves. Conclusions:   All branches are leaves. All leaves are branches. All flowers are branches. Some leaves are branches. ","options":{"A":"Nonefollows","B":"OnlyIandIVfollow","C":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","D":"Allfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIandIVfollow"},{"question":"Statements:  Some bags are pockets. No pocket is a pouch. Conclusions:   No bag is a pouch. Some bags are not pouches. Some pockets are bags. No pocket is a bag, ","options":{"A":"Nonefollows","B":"OnlyIandIIIfollow","C":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","D":"OnlyeitherIorIVfollows","E":"Allfollow"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow"},{"question":"Statements:  All aeroplanes are trains. Some trains are chairs. Conclusions:   Some aeroplanes are chairs. Some chairs are aeroplanes. Some chairs are trains. Some trains are aeroplanes. ","options":{"A":"Nonefollows","B":"OnlyIandIIfollow","C":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","D":"OnlyIIIandIVfollow"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"OnlyIIIandIVfollow"},{"question":"Statements:  All politicians are honest. All honest are fair. Conclusions:   Some honest are politicians. No honest is politician. Some fair are politicians. All fair are politicians. ","options":{"A":"Nonefollows.","B":"OnlyIfollows.","C":"OnlyIandIIfollow.","D":"OnlyIandIIIfollow"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"OnlyIandIIIfollow"},{"question":"Statements:  Some clothes are marbles. Some marbles are bags. Conclusions:   No cloth is a bag. All marbles are bags. Some bags are clothes. No marble is a cloth. ","options":{"A":"OnlyeitherIorIVfollows","B":"OnlyeitherIorIIfollows","C":"Nonefollows","D":"OnlyeitherIorIIIfollows"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"OnlyeitherIorIIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements:  Some tables are TVs. Some TVs are radios. Conclusions:   Some tables are radios. Some radios are tables. All radios are TVs. All TVs are tables. ","options":{"A":"Nonefollows","B":"Allfollow","C":"OnlyIandIIIfollow","D":"OnlyIIandIVfollow"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Nonefollows"},{"question":"Statements:  All terrorists are guilty. All terrorists are criminals. Conclusions:   Either all criminals are guilty or all guilty are criminals. Some guilty persons are criminals. Generally criminals are guilty. Crime and guilt go together. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIandIIIfollow","C":"OnlyIIfollows","D":"OnlyIIandIVfollow"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements:  Some books are pens. No pen is pencil. Conclusions:   Some pens are books. Some pencils are books. Some books are not pencils. All pencils are books. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","C":"OnlyIandIIIfollow","D":"OnlyIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyIandIIIfollow"},{"question":"Statements:  Some bottles are drinks. All drinks are cups. Conclusions:   Some bottles are cups. Some cups are drinks. All drinks are bottles. All cups are drinks. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIfollow","B":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","C":"OnlyIIandIVfollow","D":"OnlyIIIandIVfollow","E":"OnlyIandIVfollow"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statements:  Some houses are offices. Some offices are schools. Conclusions:   Some schools are houses. Some offices are houses. No house is school. Some schools are offices. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","B":"OnlyIandIVfollow","C":"OnlyeitherIIIorIV,andIfollow","D":"OnlyIIandIVandeitherIorIIIfollow."},"answer_option":"D","answer":"OnlyIIandIVandeitherIorIIIfollow."},{"question":"Statements:  Some taxis have horns. Some taxis have lights. Conclusions:   Every taxi has either horn or light. Some taxis have neither light nor horn. Some taxis have horns as well as lights. No taxi has horn as well as light. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIfollow","B":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","C":"OnlyIIandIVfollow","D":"EitherIIIorIVfollows","E":"Allfollow"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"EitherIIIorIVfollows"},{"question":"Statements: All fruits are vegetables. All pens are vegetables. All vegetables are rains. Conclusions:   All fruits are rains. All pens are rains. Some rains are vegetables. ","options":{"A":"Nonefollows","B":"OnlyIandIIfollow","C":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","D":"OnlyIandIIIfollow","E":"Allfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Allfollow"},{"question":"Statements:  Some towels are brushes. No brush is soap. All soaps are rats. Conclusions:   Some rats are brushes. No rat is brush. Some towels are soaps. ","options":{"A":"Nonefollows","B":"OnlyeitherIorIIfollows","C":"OnlyIIfollows","D":"OnlyIandIIIfollow","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyeitherIorIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements:  Some pictures are frames. Some frames are idols. All idols are curtains. Conclusions:   Some curtains are pictures. Some curtains are frames. Some idols are frames. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIfollow","B":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","C":"OnlyIandIIIfollow","D":"Allfollow","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow"},{"question":"Statements:  Some hills are rivers. Some rivers are deserts. All deserts are roads. Conclusions:   Some roads are rivers. Some roads are hills. Some deserts are hills. ","options":{"A":"Nonefollows","B":"OnlyIfollows","C":"OnlyIandIIfollow","D":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","E":"Allfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIfollows"},{"question":"Statements:  Some saints are balls. All balls are bats. Some tigers are balls. Conclusions:   Some bats are tigers. Some saints are bats. All bats are balls. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIfollow","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"OnlyIandIIIfollow","D":"OnlyIIIfollows","E":"Noneofthese."},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statements:  Some pens are books. All schools are books. Some colleges are schools. Conclusions:   Some colleges are pens. Some pens are schools. Some colleges are books. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIfollow","B":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","C":"OnlyIandIIIfollow","D":"Allfollow","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Noneofthese"},{"question":"Statements:  All trains are buses. No room is bus. All boats are rooms. Conclusions:   No boat is train. No bus is boat. No train is room. ","options":{"A":"Nonefollows","B":"OnlyIandIIfollow","C":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","D":"OnlyIandIIIfollow","E":"Allfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Allfollow"},{"question":"Statements:  Some mountains are hillocks. Some mountains are rivers. Some mountains are valleys. Conclusions:   All mountains are either hillocks or rivers or valleys. No valley is river. Some river are valleys. ","options":{"A":"Nonefollows","B":"OnlyIfollows","C":"OnlyeitherIIorIIIfollows","D":"OnlyIIIfollows","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyeitherIIorIIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements:  Some blades are hammers. Some hammers are knives. Some knives are axes. Conclusions:   Some axes are hammers. Some knives are blades. Some axes are blades. ","options":{"A":"Nonefollows","B":"OnlyIfollows","C":"OnlyIIfollows","D":"OnlyIIIfollows","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Nonefollows"},{"question":"Statements:  Some boxes are hammers. Some hammers are beads. All beads are rings. Conclusions:   Some rings are hammers. Some hammers are boxes. Some rings are boxes. ","options":{"A":"Nonefollows","B":"OnlyIfollows","C":"OnlyIandIIfollow","D":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","E":"Allfollow"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statements:  Some blankets are beds. Some pillows are blankets. All beds are pillows. Conclusions:   Some blankets are pillows. Some pillows are beds. Some beds are blankets. ","options":{"A":"OnlyeitherIorIIfollows","B":"OnlyIandeitherIIorIIIfollow","C":"OnlyIIIandeitherIorIIfollow","D":"AllI,IIandIIIfollow","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"AllI,IIandIIIfollow"},{"question":"Statements:  All dolls are windows. All bottles are windows. All cars are bottles. Conclusions:   All cars are windows. Some cars are dolls. Some windows are cars. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIfollow","B":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","C":"OnlyIandIIIfollow","D":"Allfollow","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyIandIIIfollow"},{"question":"Statements:  All tigers are lions. No cow is lion. Some camels are cows. Conclusions:   Some lions are camels. No camel- is tiger. Some tigers are cows. ","options":{"A":"Nonefollows","B":"OnlyIfollows","C":"OnlyIIfollows","D":"OnlyIIIfollows","E":"EitherIorIIfollows"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Nonefollows"},{"question":"Statements:  All flowers are toys. Some toys are trees. Some angels are trees. Conclusions:   Some angels are toys. Some trees are flowers. Some flowers are angels. ","options":{"A":"Nonefollows","B":"OnlyIfollows","C":"OnlyIIfollows","D":"OnlyIIIfollows","E":"OnlyIandIIIfollow"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Nonefollows"},{"question":"Statements:  Some rats are cats. Some cats are dogs. No dog is cow. Conclusions:   No cow is cat. No dog is rat. Some cats are rats. ","options":{"A":"Nonefollows","B":"OnlyIandIIfollow","C":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","D":"OnlyIIIfollows","E":"AllI,IIandIIIfollow"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"OnlyIIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements:  All tigers are jungles. No jungle is bird. Some birds are rains. Conclusions:   No rain is jungle. Some rains are jungles. No bird is tiger. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIfollow","B":"OnlyIIIfollows","C":"OnlyeitherIorII,andIIIfollow","D":"Allfollow","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyeitherIorII,andIIIfollow"},{"question":"Statements:  All snakes are trees. Some trees are roads. All roads are mountains. Conclusions:   Some mountains are snakes. Some roads are snakes. Some mountains are trees. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"OnlyIIIfollows","D":"BothIandIIfollow","E":"Nonefollows"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyIIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements:  All trees are flowers. No flower is fruit. All branches are fruits. Conclusions:   Some branches are trees. No fruit is tree. No tree is branch. ","options":{"A":"Nonefollows","B":"OnlyeitherIorIIIfollows","C":"OnlyIIfollows","D":"OnlyeitherIorIII,andIIfollow","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Noneofthese"},{"question":"Statements:  Some uniforms are covers. All covers are papers. All papers are bags. Conclusions:   All covers are bags. Some bags are covers, papers and uniforms. Some uniforms are not papers. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIfollows","B":"OnlyIandIIfollow","C":"OnlyIIIfollows","D":"AllI,IIandIIIfollow","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statements:  No rabbit is lion. Some horses are lions. All rabbits are tables. Conclusions:   Some tables are lions. Some horses are rabbits. No lion is table. ","options":{"A":"Nonefollows","B":"OnlyeitherIorIIIfollows","C":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","D":"OnlyIIIfollows","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyeitherIorIIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements:  All benches are desks. Some desks are roads. All roads are pillars. Conclusions:   Some pillars are benches. Some pillars are desks. Some roads are benches. No pillar is bench. ","options":{"A":"Nonefollows","B":"OnlyeitherIorIV,andIIIfollow","C":"OnlyeitherIorIVfollows","D":"OnlyeitherIorIV,andIIfollow","E":"Allfollow"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"OnlyeitherIorIV,andIIfollow"},{"question":"Statements:  Some dogs are rats. All rats are trees. Some trees are not dogs. Conclusions:   Some trees are dogs. All dogs are trees. All rats are dogs. No tree is dog. ","options":{"A":"Nonefollows","B":"OnlyIfollows","C":"OnlyIandIIfollow","D":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","E":"Allfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIfollows"},{"question":"Statements:  Some bricks are trees. All trees are pens. All pens are boats. Conclusions:   Some boats are bricks. Some pens are bricks. Some trees are bricks. Some bricks are boats. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIfollow","B":"OnlyIIIandIVfollow","C":"Nonefollows","D":"Allfollow","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Allfollow"},{"question":"Statements:  All cups are glasses. Some glasses are bowls. No bowl is a plate. Conclusions:   No cup is a plate. No glass is a plate. Some plates are bowls. Some cups are not glasses. ","options":{"A":"Nonefollows","B":"OnlyeitherIorIIIfollows","C":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","D":"OnlyIIIandIVfollow","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Nonefollows"},{"question":"Statements:  Some trains are roads. No road is jungle. All flowers are jungles. Conclusions:   Some trains are flowers. Some trains are jungles. Some flowers are trains. No road is flower. ","options":{"A":"Nonefollows","B":"OnlyIIfollows","C":"OnlyIIIfollows","D":"OnlyIVfollows","E":"Allfollow"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"OnlyIVfollows"},{"question":"Statements:  All doors are buses. All buses are leaves. No leaf is a flower. Conclusions:   No flower is a door. No flower is a bus. Some leaves are doors. Some leaves are buses. ","options":{"A":"Nonefollows","B":"OnlyIandIIfollow","C":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","D":"OnlyII,IIIandIVfollow","E":"Allfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Allfollow"},{"question":"Statements:  All oceans are rivers. Some springs are rivers. All wells are springs. Conclusions:   Some springs are oceans. Some wells are rivers. Some rivers are oceans. No well is river. ","options":{"A":"Nonefollows","B":"OnlyeitherIorIII,andIVfollow","C":"OnlyeitherIIorIV,andIIIfollow","D":"Allfollow","E":"OnlyeitherIIorIV,andIfollow"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyeitherIIorIV,andIIIfollow"},{"question":"Statements:  Some tigers are lions. Some lions are rabbits. Some rabbits are horses. Conclusions:   Some tigers are horses. Some rabbits are tigers. Some horses are lions. All horses are rabbits. ","options":{"A":"Allfollow","B":"Nonefollows","C":"OnlyIandIIfollow","D":"OnlyIIandIVfollow","E":"OnlyIVfollows"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"Nonefollows"},{"question":"Statements:  Some spoons are bowls. All bowls are knives. All knives are forks. Conclusions:   All spoons are forks. All bowls are forks. Some knives are bowls. Some forks are spoons. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","B":"OnlyIIandIVfollow","C":"OnlyIIIandIVfollow","D":"Allfollow","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Noneofthese"},{"question":"Statements:  All pencils are birds. All birds are skies. All skies are hills. Conclusions:   All pencils are hills. All hills are birds All skies are pencils. All birds are hills. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIfollow","B":"OnlyIandIIIfollow","C":"OnlyIIIandIVfollow","D":"Allfollow","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Noneofthese"},{"question":"Statements:  No tree is fruit. All fruits are stones. All stones are rains. Conclusions:   No stone is tree. No rain is tree. Some rains are fruits. Some rains are trees. ","options":{"A":"OnlyeitherIIorIII,andIfollow","B":"Nonefollows","C":"OnlyeitherIIorIV,andIIIfollow","D":"Allfollow","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyeitherIIorIV,andIIIfollow"},{"question":"Statements:  All players are spectators. Some spectators are theatres. Some theatres are dramas. Conclusions:   Some dramas are spectators. Some players are dramas. Some theatres are players. All spectators are players. ","options":{"A":"Nonefollows","B":"OnlyIandIIIfollow","C":"OnlyIIfollows","D":"OnlyIIandIVfollow","E":"Allfollow"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Nonefollows"},{"question":"Statements:  All doors are roads. No road is fruit. Some flowers are doors. Conclusions:   Some fruits are doors. Some fruits are flowers. Some roads are flowers. No fruit is flower. ","options":{"A":"OnlyeitherIIorIII,andIVfollow","B":"OnlyeitherIIorIV,andIIIfollow","C":"OnlyeitherIIorIV,andIfollow","D":"OnlyeitherIIorIVfollows","E":"Allfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyeitherIIorIV,andIIIfollow"},{"question":"Statements:  All needles are threads. All threads are boxes. All trees are boxes. Conclusions:   No needle is tree. Some trees are threads. Some boxes are needles. Some trees are needles. ","options":{"A":"Nonefollows","B":"OnlyeitherIorIVfollows","C":"OnlyeitherIorIV,andIIfollow","D":"OnlyIIIfollows","E":"OnlyeitherIorIV,andIIIfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"OnlyeitherIorIV,andIIIfollow"},{"question":"Statements:  No house is school. All colleges are schools. All schools are teachers. Conclusions:   No house is teacher. All colleges are teachers. Some teachers are not houses. No college is house. ","options":{"A":"Nonefollows","B":"OnlyeitherIorIVfollows","C":"OnlyII,IIIandIVfollow","D":"Allfollow","E":"OnlyeitherIorIV,andIIIfollow"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyII,IIIandIVfollow"},{"question":"Statements:  Some pearls are stones. Some stones are diamonds. No diamond is a gem. Conclusions:   Some gems are pearls. Some gems are diamonds. No gem is a diamond. No gem is a pearl. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIfollow","B":"OnlyIIIandIVfollow","C":"OnlyeitherIorIVandeitherIIorIIIfollow","D":"OnlyIIIandeitherIorIVfollow","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"OnlyIIIandeitherIorIVfollow"},{"question":"Statements:  All rods are bricks. Some bricks are ropes. All ropes are doors. Conclusions:   Some rods are doors. Some doors are bricks. Some rods are not doors. All doors are ropes. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIfollow","B":"OnlyI,IIandIIIfollow","C":"OnlyeitherIorIII,andIIfollow","D":"OnlyeitherIorIII,andIVfollow","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Noneofthese"},{"question":"Statements:  All myths are fictions. No fiction is novel. All novels are stories. Conclusions:   No myth is novel. Some fictions are novels. Some fictions are myths. Some myths are novels. ","options":{"A":"OnlyeitherIorIIandbothIIIandIVfollow","B":"OnlyeitherIorIVandIIfollow","C":"OnlyeitherIorIVandbothIIandIIIfollow","D":"Allfollow","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Noneofthese"},{"question":"Statements:  No paper is pen. No pen is pencil. All erasers are papers. Conclusions:   Some papers are erasers. No pencil is eraser. No pen is eraser. All papers are erasers. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIfollow","B":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","C":"OnlyI,IIandIIIfollow","D":"Allfollow","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Noneofthese"},{"question":"Statements:  No man is sky. No sky is road. Some men are roads. Conclusions:   No road is man. No road is sky. Some skies are men. All roads are men. ","options":{"A":"Nonefollows","B":"OnlyIfollows","C":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","D":"OnlyIandIIIfollow","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Noneofthese"},{"question":"Statements:  All buildings are windows. No toys is building. Some tigers are toys. Conclusions:   Some tigers are buildings. Some windows are tigers. All toys are tigers. Some windows are toys. ","options":{"A":"Nonefollows","B":"OnlyIandIIfollow","C":"OnlyIIIandIVfollow","D":"OnlyIandIIIfollow","E":"Allfollow"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Nonefollows"},{"question":"Statements:  Some papers are cats. All cats are bats. No bat is horse. Conclusions:   Some papers are horses. No horse is cat. Some bats are papers. All papers are bats. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIfollow","B":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow","C":"OnlyIIIandIVfollow","D":"OnlyIandIVfollow","E":"Allfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIIandIIIfollow"},{"question":"Statements:  Some tapes are discs. Some discs are cassettes. Some cassettes are songs. Conclusions:   Some songs are discs. Some cassettes are tapes. Some songs are tapes. No song is a disc. ","options":{"A":"OnlyeitherIorIVfollows","B":"OnlyeitherIIorIVfollows","C":"OnlyIIIandIVfollow","D":"OnlyIIIandeitherIIorIVfollows","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyeitherIorIVfollows"},{"question":"Statements:  No table is fruit. No fruit is window. All windows are chairs. Conclusions:   No window is table. No chair is fruit. No chair is table. All chairs are windows. ","options":{"A":"Nonefollows","B":"OnlyIandIIfollow","C":"OnlyIIIandIVfollow","D":"Allfollow","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Nonefollows"},{"question":"Statements:  All jungles are buses. All books are buses. All fruits are books. Conclusions:   Some fruits are jungles. Some buses are books. Some buses are jungles. All fruits are buses. ","options":{"A":"OnlyI,IIandIIIfollow","B":"OnlyI,IIandIVfollow","C":"OnlyII,IIIandIVfollow","D":"Allfollow","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyII,IIIandIVfollow"}],"logical-games":[{"question":"Senators from urban areas are very concerned about assuring that there will be funding for a new international airport. Senators from rural areas refuse to fund anything until money for agricultural subsidies is appropriated. If the legislature funds these two programs, on which of the following could they spend the rest of the money?","options":{"A":"theschoolmusicprogramandnationalradio","B":"hurricanepreparedness","C":"harborimprovementsandtheschoolmusicprogram","D":"smallbusinessloanprogram","E":"nationalradioandsenateofficebuildingremodeling"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"theschoolmusicprogramandnationalradio"},{"question":"If the legislature decides to fund the agricultural subsidy program, national radio, and the small business loan program, what two other programs could they fund?","options":{"A":"harborimprovementsandinternationalairport","B":"harborimprovementsandschoolmusicprogram","C":"hurricanepreparednessandschoolmusicprogram","D":"hurricanepreparednessandinternationalairport","E":"harborimprovementsandhurricanepreparedness"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"harborimprovementsandschoolmusicprogram"},{"question":"If the legislature decides to fund the agricultural subsidy program, national radio, and the small business loan program, the only other single program that can be funded is","options":{"A":"hurricanepreparedness.","B":"harborimprovements.","C":"schoolmusicprogram.","D":"senateofficebuildingremodeling.","E":"internationalairport."},"answer_option":"D","answer":"senateofficebuildingremodeling."},{"question":"Who is the secretary?","options":{"A":"Enid","B":"David","C":"Cheryl","D":"Bert","E":"Alice"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Alice"},{"question":"Who is the CEO ?","options":{"A":"Alice","B":"Bert","C":"Cheryl","D":"David","E":"Enid"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"Cheryl"},{"question":"What color is the vice president's car?","options":{"A":"green","B":"yellow","C":"blue","D":"purple","E":"red"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"green"},{"question":"Which city got the most rain?","options":{"A":"LastStand","B":"MileCity","C":"NewTown","D":"Olliopolis","E":"Polberg"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"LastStand"},{"question":"How much rain did Mile City get?","options":{"A":"12inches","B":"27inches","C":"32inches","D":"44inches","E":"65inches"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"27inches"},{"question":"Which city is in the desert ?","options":{"A":"LastStand","B":"MileCity","C":"NewTown","D":"Olliopolis","E":"Polberg"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Polberg"},{"question":"Where is Olliopolis located?","options":{"A":"themountains","B":"thecoast","C":"inavalley","D":"thedesert","E":"theforest"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"inavalley"},{"question":"What task does Terry do on Wednesday?","options":{"A":"vacuuming","B":"dusting","C":"mopping","D":"sweeping","E":"laundry"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"sweeping"},{"question":"What day does Uma do her task?","options":{"A":"Monday","B":"Tuesday","C":"Wednesday","D":"Thursday","E":"Friday"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Thursday"},{"question":"What task does Vernon do?","options":{"A":"vacuuming","B":"dusting","C":"mopping","D":"sweeping","E":"laundry"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"laundry"},{"question":"What day is the vacuuming done?","options":{"A":"Friday","B":"Monday","C":"Tuesday","D":"Wednesday","E":"Thursday"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"Monday"},{"question":"When does Sally do the dusting?","options":{"A":"Friday","B":"Monday","C":"Tuesday","D":"Wednesday","E":"Thursday"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"Tuesday"}],"logical-problems":[{"question":"Tanya is older than Eric.Cliff is older than Tanya.Eric is older than Cliff.If the first two statements are true, the third statement is","options":{"A":"true","B":"false","C":"uncertain"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"false"},{"question":"Blueberries cost more than strawberries.Blueberries cost less than raspberries.Raspberries cost more than strawberries and blueberries.If the first two statements are true, the third statement is","options":{"A":"true","B":"false","C":"uncertain"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"true"},{"question":"All the trees in the park are flowering trees.Some of the trees in the park are dogwoods.All dogwoods in the park are flowering trees.If the first two statements are true, the third statement is","options":{"A":"true","B":"false","C":"uncertain"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"true"},{"question":"Mara runs faster than Gail.Lily runs faster than Mara.Gail runs faster than Lily.If the first two statements are true, the third statement is","options":{"A":"true","B":"false","C":"uncertain"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"false"},{"question":"Apartments in the Riverdale Manor cost less than apartments in The Gaslight Commons.Apartments in the Livingston Gate cost more than apartments in the The Gaslight Commons.Of the three apartment buildings, the Livingston Gate costs the most.If the first two statements are true, the third statement is","options":{"A":"true","B":"false","C":"uncertain"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"true"},{"question":"The Kingston Mall has more stores than the Galleria.The Four Corners Mall has fewer stores than the Galleria.The Kingston Mall has more stores than the Four Corners Mall.If the first two statements are true, the third statement is","options":{"A":"true","B":"false","C":"uncertain"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"true"},{"question":"All the tulips in Zoe's garden are white.All the pansies in Zoe's garden are yellow.All the flowers in Zoe's garden are either white or yellowIf the first two statements are true, the third statement is","options":{"A":"true","B":"false","C":"uncertain"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"uncertain"},{"question":"During the past year, Josh saw more movies than Stephen.Stephen saw fewer movies than Darren.Darren saw more movies than Josh.If the first two statements are true, the third statement is","options":{"A":"true","B":"false","C":"uncertain"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"uncertain"},{"question":"Rover weighs less than Fido.Rover weighs more than Boomer.Of the three dogs, Boomer weighs the least.If the first two statements are true, the third statement is","options":{"A":"true","B":"false","C":"uncertain"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"true"},{"question":"All the offices on the 9th floor have wall-to-wall carpeting.No wall-to-wall carpeting is pink.None of the offices on the 9th floor has pink wall-to-wall carpeting.If the first two statements are true, the third statement is","options":{"A":"true","B":"false","C":"uncertain"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"true"},{"question":"Class A has a higher enrollment than Class B.Class C has a lower enrollment than Class B.Class A has a lower enrollment than Class C.If the first two statements are true, the third statement is","options":{"A":"true","B":"false","C":"uncertain"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"false"},{"question":"A fruit basket contains more apples than lemons.There are more lemons in the basket than there are oranges.The basket contains more apples than oranges.If the first two statements are true, the third statement is","options":{"A":"true","B":"false","C":"uncertain"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"true"},{"question":"The Shop and Save Grocery is south of Greenwood Pharmacy.Rebecca's house is northeast of Greenwood Pharmacy.Rebecca's house is west of the Shop and Save Grocery.If the first two statements are true, the third statement is","options":{"A":"true","B":"false","C":"uncertain"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"false"},{"question":"Joe is younger than Kathy.Mark was born after Joe.Kathy is older than Mark.If the first two statements are true, the third statement is","options":{"A":"true","B":"false","C":"uncertain"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"true"},{"question":"On the day the Barton triplets are born,Jenna weighs more than Jason.Jason weighs less than Jasmine.Of the three babies, Jasmine weighs the most.If the first two statements are true, the third statement is","options":{"A":"true","B":"false","C":"uncertain"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"uncertain"},{"question":"The temperature on Monday was lower than on Tuesday.The temperature on Wednesday was lower than on Tuesday.The temperature on Monday was higher than on WednesdayIf the first two statements are true, the third statement is","options":{"A":"true","B":"false","C":"uncertain"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"uncertain"},{"question":"Oat cereal has more fiber than corn cereal but less fiber than bran cereal.Corn cereal has more fiber than rice cereal but less fiber than wheat cereal.Of the three kinds of cereal, rice cereal has the least amount of fiber.If the first two statements are true, the third statement is","options":{"A":"true","B":"false","C":"uncertain"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"true"},{"question":"Martina is sitting in the desk behind Jerome.Jerome is sitting in the desk behind Bryant.Bryant is sitting in the desk behind Martina.If the first two statements are true, the third statement is","options":{"A":"true","B":"false","C":"uncertain"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"false"},{"question":"Battery X lasts longer than Battery Y.Battery Y doesn't last as long as Battery Z.Battery Z lasts longer than Battery X.If the first two statements are true, the third statement is","options":{"A":"true","B":"false","C":"uncertain"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"uncertain"},{"question":"Spot is bigger than King and smaller than Sugar.Ralph is smaller than Sugar and bigger than Spot.King is bigger than Ralph.If the first two statements are true, the third statement is","options":{"A":"true","B":"false","C":"uncertain"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"false"},{"question":"Middletown is north of Centerville.Centerville is east of Penfield.Penfield is northwest of Middletown.If the first two statements are true, the third statement is","options":{"A":"true","B":"false","C":"uncertain"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"false"},{"question":"All spotted Gangles have long tails.Short-haired Gangles always have short tails.Long-tailed Gangles never have short hair.If the first two statements are true, the third statement is","options":{"A":"true","B":"false","C":"uncertain"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"uncertain"},{"question":"All Lamels are Signots with buttons.No yellow Signots have buttons.No Lamels are yellow.If the first two statements are true, the third statement is","options":{"A":"true","B":"false","C":"uncertain"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"true"},{"question":"The hotel is two blocks east of the drugstore.The market is one block west of the hotel.The drugstore is west of the market.If the first two statements are true, the third statement is","options":{"A":"true","B":"false","C":"uncertain"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"true"},{"question":"A toothpick is useful.Useful things are valuable.A toothpick is valuable.If the first two statements are true, the third statement is","options":{"A":"true","B":"false","C":"uncertain"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"true"},{"question":"Tom puts on his socks before he puts on his shoes.He puts on his shirt before he puts on his jacket.Tom puts on his shoes before he puts on his shirt.If the first two statements are true, the third statement is","options":{"A":"true","B":"false","C":"uncertain"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"uncertain"},{"question":"Three pencils cost the same as two erasers.Four erasers cost the same as one ruler.Pencils are more expensive than rulers.If the first two statements are true, the third statement is","options":{"A":"true","B":"false","C":"uncertain"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"false"},{"question":"Taking the train across town is quicker than taking the bus.Taking the bus across town is slower than driving a car.Taking the train across town is quicker than driving a car.If the first two statements are true, the third statement is","options":{"A":"true","B":"false","C":"uncertain"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"uncertain"},{"question":"Cloudy days tend to be more windy than sunny days.Foggy days tend to be less windy than cloudy days.Sunny days tend to be less windy than foggy days.If the first two statements are true, the third statement is","options":{"A":"true","B":"false","C":"uncertain"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"uncertain"},{"question":"At a parking lot, a sedan is parked to the right of a pickup and to the left of a sport utility vehicle.A minivan is parked to the left of the pickup.The minivan is parked between the pickup and the sedan.If the first two statements are true, the third statement is","options":{"A":"true","B":"false","C":"uncertain"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"false"},{"question":"The bookstore has a better selection of postcards than the newsstand does.The selection of postcards at the drugstore is better than at the bookstore.The drugstore has a better selection of postcards than the bookstore or the newsstand.If the first two statements are true, the third statement is","options":{"A":"true","B":"false","C":"uncertain"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"true"},{"question":"A jar of jelly beans contains more red beans than green.There are more yellow beans than red.The jar contains fewer yellow jelly beans than green ones.If the first two statements are true, the third statement is","options":{"A":"true","B":"false","C":"uncertain"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"false"},{"question":"         Fact 1:      All dogs like to run.            Fact 2:      Some dogs like to swim.            Fact 3:      Some dogs look like their masters.   If the first three statements are facts, which of the following statements must also be a fact?         I:      All dogs who like to swim look like their masters.            II:      Dogs who like to swim also like to run.            III:      Dogs who like to run do not look like their masters.   ","options":{"A":"Ionly","B":"IIonly","C":"IIandIIIonly","D":"Noneofthestatementsisaknownfact."},"answer_option":"B","answer":"IIonly"},{"question":"         Fact 1:      Jessica has four children            Fact 2:      Two of the children have blue eyes and two of the children have brown eyes.            Fact 3:      Half of the children are girls.   If the first three statements are facts, which of the following statements must also be a fact?         I:      At least one girl has blue eyes.            II:      Two of the children are boys.            III:      The boys have brown eyes.   ","options":{"A":"Ionly","B":"IIonly","C":"IIandIIIonly","D":"Noneofthestatementsisaknownfact."},"answer_option":"B","answer":"IIonly"},{"question":"         Fact 1:      All drink mixes are beverages.            Fact 2:      All beverages are drinkable.            Fact 3:      Some beverages are red.   If the first three statements are facts, which of the following statements must also be a fact?         I:      Some drink mixes are red.            II:      All beverages are drink mixes.            III:      All red drink mixes are drinkable.   ","options":{"A":"IandIIonly","B":"IIonly","C":"IandIIIonly","D":"IIIonly","E":"Noneofthestatementsisaknownfact."},"answer_option":"D","answer":"IIIonly"},{"question":"         Fact 1:      All chickens are birds.            Fact 2:      Some chickens are hens.            Fact 3:      Female birds lay eggs.   If the first three statements are facts, which of the following statements must also be a fact?         I:      All birds lay eggs.            II:      Some Hens are birds.            III:      Some chickens are not hens.   ","options":{"A":"Ionly","B":"IIonly","C":"IIandIIIonly","D":"Noneofthestatementsisaknownfact."},"answer_option":"C","answer":"IIandIIIonly"},{"question":"         Fact 1:      All hats have brims.            Fact 2:      There are black hats and blue hats.            Fact 3:      Baseball caps are hats.   If the first three statements are facts, which of the following statements must also be a fact?         I:      All caps have brims.            II:      Some baseball caps are blue.            III:      Baseball caps have no brims.   ","options":{"A":"Ionly","B":"IIonly","C":"IIandIIIonly","D":"Noneofthestatementsisaknownfact."},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Noneofthestatementsisaknownfact."},{"question":"         Fact 1:      Eyeglass frames cost between $35 and $350.            Fact 2:      Some eyeglass frames are made of titanium.            Fact 3:      Some eyeglass frames are made of plastic.   If the first three statements are facts, which of the following statements must also be a fact?         I:      Titanium eyeglass frames cost more than plastic frames.            II:      Expensive eyeglass frames last longer than cheap frames.            III:      Only a few eyeglass frames cost less than $35.   ","options":{"A":"Ionly","B":"IIonly","C":"IIandIIIonly","D":"Noneofthestatementsisaknownfact."},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Noneofthestatementsisaknownfact."},{"question":"         Fact 1:      Most stuffed toys are stuffed with beans.            Fact 2:      There are stuffed bears and stuffed tigers.            Fact 3:      Some chairs are stuffed with beans.   If the first three statements are facts, which of the following statements must also be a fact?         I:      Only children's chairs are stuffed with beans.            II:      All stuffed tigers are stuffed with beans.            III:      Stuffed monkeys are not stuffed with beans.   ","options":{"A":"Ionly","B":"IIonly","C":"IIandIIIonly","D":"Noneofthestatementsisaknownfact."},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Noneofthestatementsisaknownfact."},{"question":"         Fact 1:      Mary said, \"Ann and I both have cats.\"            Fact 2:      Ann said, \"I don't have a cat.\"            Fact 3:      Mary always tells the truth, but Ann sometimes lies.   If the first three statements are facts, which of the following statements must also be a fact?         I:      Ann has a cat.            II:      Mary has a cat.            III:      Ann is lying.   ","options":{"A":"Ionly","B":"IIonly","C":"IandIIonly","D":"Allthestatementsarefacts."},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Allthestatementsarefacts."},{"question":"         Fact 1:      Pictures can tell a story.            Fact 2:      All storybooks have pictures.            Fact 3:      Some storybooks have words.   If the first three statements are facts, which of the following statements must also be a fact?         I:      Pictures can tell a story better than words can.            II:      The stories in storybooks are very simple.            III:      Some storybooks have both words and pictures.   ","options":{"A":"Ionly","B":"IIonly","C":"IIIonly","D":"Noneofthestatementsisaknownfact."},"answer_option":"C","answer":"IIIonly"},{"question":"         Fact 1:      Some pens don't write.            Fact 2:      All blue pens write.            Fact 3:      Some writing utensils are pens.   If the first three statements are facts, which of the following statements must also be a fact?         I:      Some writing utensils don't write.            II:      Some writing utensils are blue.            III:      Some blue writing utensils don't write.   ","options":{"A":"Ionly","B":"IandIIonly","C":"IIandIIIonly","D":"Noneofthestatementsisaknownfact."},"answer_option":"B","answer":"IandIIonly"},{"question":"         Fact 1:      Islands are surrounded by water.            Fact 2:      Maui is an island.            Fact 3:      Maui was formed by a volcano.   If the first three statements are facts, which of the following statements must also be a fact?         I:      Maui is surrounded by water.            II:      All islands are formed by volcanoes.            III:      All volcanoes are on islands.   ","options":{"A":"Ionly","B":"IIonly","C":"IIandIIIonly","D":"Noneofthestatementsisaknownfact."},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Ionly"},{"question":"         Fact 1:      Robert has four vehicles.            Fact 2:      Two of the vehicles are red.            Fact 3:      One of the vehicles is a minivan.   If the first three statements are facts, which of the following statements must also be a fact?         I:      Robert has a red minivan.            II:      Robert has three cars.            III:      Robert's favorite color is red.   ","options":{"A":"Ionly","B":"IIonly","C":"IIandIIIonly","D":"Noneofthestatementsisaknownfact."},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Noneofthestatementsisaknownfact."},{"question":"Four defensive football players are chasing the opposing wide receiver, who has the ball. Calvin is directly behind the ball carrier. Jenkins and Burton are side by side behind Calvin. Zeller is behind Jenkins and Burton. Calvin tries for the tackle but misses and falls. Burton trips. Which defensive player tackles the receiver?","options":{"A":"Burton","B":"Zeller","C":"Jenkins","D":"Calvin"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"Jenkins"},{"question":"A four-person crew from Classic Colors is painting Mr. Field's house. Michael is painting the front of the house. Ross is in the alley behind the house painting the back. Jed is painting the window frames on the north side, Shawn is on the south. If Michael switches places with Jed, and Jed then switches places with Shawn, where is Shawn?","options":{"A":"inthealleybehindthehouse","B":"onthenorthsideofthehouse","C":"infrontofthehouse","D":"onthesouthsideofthehouse"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"infrontofthehouse"},{"question":"In a four-day period Monday through Thursday each of the following temporary office workers worked only one day, each a different day. Ms. Johnson was scheduled to work on Monday, but she traded with Mr. Carter, who was originally scheduled to work on Wednesday. Ms. Falk traded with Mr. Kirk, who was originally scheduled to work on Thursday. After all the switching was done, who worked on Tuesday?","options":{"A":"Mr.Carter","B":"Ms.Falk","C":"Ms.Johnson","D":"Mr.Kirk"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Mr.Kirk"},{"question":"Four people witnessed a mugging. Each gave a different description of the mugger. Which description is probably right?","options":{"A":"Hewasaverageheight,thin,andmiddle-aged.","B":"Hewastall,thin,andmiddle-aged.","C":"Hewastall,thin,andyoung.","D":"Hewastall,ofaverageweight,andmiddle-aged."},"answer_option":"B","answer":"Hewastall,thin,andmiddle-aged."},{"question":"Ms. Forest likes to let her students choose who their partners will be; however, no pair of students may work together more than seven class periods in a row. Adam and Baxter have studied together seven class periods in a row. Carter and Dennis have worked together three class periods in a row. Carter does not want to work with Adam. Who should be assigned to work with Baxter?","options":{"A":"Carter","B":"Adam","C":"Dennis","D":"Forest"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Carter"},{"question":"At the baseball game, Henry was sitting in seat 253. Marla was sitting to the right of Henry in seat 254. In the seat to the left of Henry was George. Inez was sitting to the left of George. Which seat is Inez sitting in?","options":{"A":"251","B":"254","C":"255","D":"256"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"251"},{"question":"As they prepare for the state championships, one gymnast must be moved from the Level 2 team to the Level 1 team. The coaches will move the gymnast who has won the biggest prize and who has the most experience. In the last competition, Roberta won a bronze medal and has competed seven times before. Jamie has won a silver medal and has competed fewer times than Roberta. Beth has won a higher medal than Jamie and has competed more times than Roberta. Michele has won a bronze medal, and it is her third time competing. Who will be moved to the Level 1 team?","options":{"A":"Roberta","B":"Beth","C":"Michele","D":"Jamie"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"Beth"},{"question":"Four friends in the sixth grade were sharing a pizza. They decided that the oldest friend would get the extra piece. Randy is two months older than Greg, who is three months younger than Ned. Kent is one month older than Greg. Who should get the extra piece of pizza?","options":{"A":"Randy","B":"Greg","C":"Ned","D":"Kent"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"Ned"},{"question":"The high school math department needs to appoint a new chairperson, which will be based on seniority. Ms. West has less seniority than Mr. Temple, but more than Ms. Brody. Mr. Rhodes has more seniority than Ms. West, but less than Mr. Temple. Mr. Temple doesn't want the job. Who will be the new math department chairperson?","options":{"A":"Mr.Rhodes","B":"Mr.Temple","C":"Ms.West","D":"Ms.Brody"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Mr.Rhodes"},{"question":"Danielle has been visiting friends in Ridge-wood for the past two weeks. She is leaving tomorrow morning and her flight is very early. Most of her friends live fairly close to the airport. Madison lives ten miles away. Frances lives five miles away, Samantha, seven miles. Alexis is farther away than Frances, but closer than Samantha. Approximately how far away from the airport is Alexis?","options":{"A":"ninemiles","B":"sevenmiles","C":"eightmiles","D":"sixmiles"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"sixmiles"},{"question":"Nurse Kemp has worked more night shifts in a row than Nurse Rogers, who has worked five. Nurse Miller has worked fifteen night shifts in a row, more than Nurses Kemp and Rogers combined. Nurse Calvin has worked eight night shifts in a row, less than Nurse Kemp. How many night shifts in a row has Nurse Kemp worked?","options":{"A":"eight","B":"nine","C":"ten","D":"eleven"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"nine"},{"question":"Children are in pursuit of a dog whose leash has broken. James is directly behind the dog. Ruby is behind James. Rachel is behind Ruby. Max is ahead of the dog walking down the street in the opposite direction. As the children and dog pass, Max turns around and joins the pursuit. He runs in behind Ruby. James runs faster and is alongside the dog on the left. Ruby runs faster and is alongside the dog on the right. Which child is directly behind the dog?","options":{"A":"James","B":"Ruby","C":"Rachel","D":"Max"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Max"}],"making-judgments":[{"question":"A Guarantee is a promise or assurance that attests to the quality of a product that is either (1) given in writing by the manufacturer or (2) given verbally by the person selling the product. Which situation below is the best example of a Guarantee?","options":{"A":"MelissapurchasesaDVDplayerwiththehighestconsumerratingsinitscategory.","B":"ThesalespersonadvisesCurttobesurethathebuysanairconditionerwithaguarantee.","C":"Thelocalautobodyshopspecializesinrefurbishingandsellingusedcars.","D":"LoribuysauseddigitalcamerafromhercoworkerwhosaysthatshewillrefundLori'smoneyifthecamera'sperformanceisnotofthehighestquality."},"answer_option":"D","answer":"LoribuysauseddigitalcamerafromhercoworkerwhosaysthatshewillrefundLori'smoneyifthecamera'sperformanceisnotofthehighestquality."},{"question":"The rules of baseball state that a batter Legally Completes His Time at Bat when he is put out or becomes a base runner. Which situation below is the best example of a batter Legally Completing His Time at Bat?","options":{"A":"Jared'sblooperovertheheadoftheshort-stopputshiminscoringposition.","B":"Theumpirecallsastrike,eventhoughthelastpitchwaswayoutside.","C":"Thepitcherthrowshisfamousknuckleball,Joeswingsandmisses,andtheumpirecallsastrike.","D":"ThecountistwoballsandtwostrikesasMariowaitsforthenextpitch."},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Jared'sblooperovertheheadoftheshort-stopputshiminscoringposition."},{"question":"Erratic Behavior occurs when an individual acts in a manner that lacks consistency, regularity, and uniformity. Which situation below is the best example of Erratic Behavior?","options":{"A":"Juliacannotcontainherangerwheneverthesubjectoflocalpoliticsisdiscussed.","B":"Martinhasjustbeentoldthatheisbeinglaidoff.Beforeleavinghissupervisor'soffice,hepunchesaholeinthedoor.","C":"Rhondahasvisitedthedealershipseveraltimes,butshestillcannotdecidewhichcartobuy.","D":"Inthepastmonth,Jeffrey,whohasbeenamodelemployeeforthreeyears,hasrepeatedlycalledinsick,forgottenimportantmeetings,andbeenverballyabusivetocolleagues."},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Inthepastmonth,Jeffrey,whohasbeenamodelemployeeforthreeyears,hasrepeatedlycalledinsick,forgottenimportantmeetings,andbeenverballyabusivetocolleagues."},{"question":"A Tiebreaker is an additional contest or period of play designed to establish a winner among tied contestants. Which situation below is the best example of a Tiebreaker?","options":{"A":"Athalftime,thescoreistiedat28.","B":"MaryandMeganhaveeachscoredthreegoalsinthegame.","C":"Therefereetossesacointodecidewhichteamwillhavepossessionoftheballfirst.","D":"TheSharksandtheBearseachfinishedwith14points,andtheyarenowbattlingitoutinafive-minuteovertime."},"answer_option":"D","answer":"TheSharksandtheBearseachfinishedwith14points,andtheyarenowbattlingitoutinafive-minuteovertime."},{"question":"In the Maple Hill school district, a Five-Day Suspension occurs when a student is not permitted to attend school for five days for  (1) physically assaulting another student, a teacher, or a school employee or (2) willfully destructing or defacing school property. Which situation below is the best example of a Five-Day Suspension?","options":{"A":"Lilliangetscaughtcheatingonamathtestforthesecondtimeandissuspendedfromschool.","B":"Marcisaskedtoleavetheclassroomduetohisconstantdisruptions.","C":"Frannyusesspraypainttowritederogatorycommentsonthelockerroomwallandsheisgivenasuspension.","D":"Ms.Farmertellsherclassthatstudentswhofailthemidtermexamwillbeexpectedtostayafterschoolfortutoringhelp."},"answer_option":"C","answer":"Frannyusesspraypainttowritederogatorycommentsonthelockerroomwallandsheisgivenasuspension."},{"question":"It is appropriate to compensate someone if you have damaged his or her property in some way. This is called Restitution. Which situation below is the best example of Restitution?","options":{"A":"JakeborrowsLeslie'scameraandthelensshatterswhenitfallsonthegroundbecausehefailstozipperthecase.WhenJakereturnsthecamera,hetellsLesliethathewillpayfortherepair.","B":"Rebeccaborrowsherneighbor'scar,andwhenshereturnsit,thegastankispracticallyempty.Sheapologizesprofuselyandtellsherneighborshewillbemoreconsideratethenexttime.","C":"AaronasksTomtocheckinonhisapartmentwhileheisoutoftown.WhenTomarrives,hediscoversthatapipehasburstandthereisaconsiderableamountofwaterdamage.Hecallsaplumbertorepairthepipe.","D":"Lisasuspectsthatthepotholeinhercompany'sparkinglotcausedherflattire.Shetellsherbossthatshethinksthecompanyshouldpayfortherepair."},"answer_option":"A","answer":"JakeborrowsLeslie'scameraandthelensshatterswhenitfallsonthegroundbecausehefailstozipperthecase.WhenJakereturnsthecamera,hetellsLesliethathewillpayfortherepair."},{"question":"Reentry occurs when a person leaves his or her social system for a period of time and then returns. Which situation below best describes Reentry ?","options":{"A":"Whenheisofferedabetterpayingposition,Jacobleavestherestauranthemanagestomanageanewrestaurantontheothersideoftown.","B":"CatherineisspendingherjunioryearofcollegestudyingabroadinFrance.","C":"Malcolmisreadjustingtocivilianlifeaftertwoyearsofoverseasmilitaryservice.","D":"Afterseveralmiserablemonths,SharondecidesthatshecannolongershareanapartmentwithherroommateHilary."},"answer_option":"C","answer":"Malcolmisreadjustingtocivilianlifeaftertwoyearsofoverseasmilitaryservice."},{"question":"Embellishing the Truth occurs when a person adds fictitious details or exaggerates facts or true stories. Which situation below is the best example of Embellishing the Truth?","options":{"A":"Isabelgoestothetheater,andthenextday,shetellshercoworkersshethoughttheplaywasexcellent.","B":"Therealtordescribesthehouse,whichiselevenblocksawayfromtheocean,asprimewaterfrontproperty.","C":"Duringthejobinterview,Fred,whohasbeenteachingelementaryschoolfortenyears,describeshimselfasaveryexperiencedteacher.","D":"Thebasketballcoachsaysitislikelythatonlythemosttalentedplayerswillgetacollegescholarship."},"answer_option":"B","answer":"Therealtordescribesthehouse,whichiselevenblocksawayfromtheocean,asprimewaterfrontproperty."},{"question":"Establishing a Power of Attorney occurs when a legal document is created that gives one individual the authority to act for another. Which situation below is the best example of Establishing a Power of Attorney?","options":{"A":"Louiseissellingherhouseandshehiresalawyertoreviewthecontract.","B":"Simone'smothercannolongergettothebanktocashherchecksandmakedeposits,soshehastakenlegalstepstoenableSimonetodothesethingsforher.","C":"Jack'sfatheriselderlyandJackthinksheisnolongerabletomakedecisionsforhimself.","D":"Atherdaughter'surging,Mrs.Lenoxopensuparetirementaccountwiththelocalbank."},"answer_option":"B","answer":"Simone'smothercannolongergettothebanktocashherchecksandmakedeposits,soshehastakenlegalstepstoenableSimonetodothesethingsforher."},{"question":"Mark is working with a realtor to find a location for the toy store he plans to open in his town. He is looking for a place that is either in, or not too far from, the center of town and one that would attract the right kind of foot traffic. Which of the following locations should Mark's realtor call to his attention?","options":{"A":"astorefrontinanewhigh-risebuildingnearthetrainstationinthecenteroftownwhoseoccupantsaremainlyyoung,childlessprofessionalswhousethetraintocommutetotheirofficeseachday.","B":"alittleshopthreeblocksawayfromthetown'smainstreet,locatedacrossthestreetfromanelementaryschoolandnextdoortoanicecreamstore","C":"astand-alonestorefrontonaquietresidentialstreettenblocksawayfromthetown'scenter","D":"astorefrontinasmallstripmalllocatedontheoutskirtsoftownthatisalsooccupiedbyapharmacyandadrycleaner"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"alittleshopthreeblocksawayfromthetown'smainstreet,locatedacrossthestreetfromanelementaryschoolandnextdoortoanicecreamstore"},{"question":"The neighborhood block association has received many complaints about people knocking on doors and soliciting money for an unknown charity organization even though door-to-door solicitation is prohibited by local laws. Three residents have provided descriptions of individuals who have come to their door asking for money.Solicitor #1 is a white male, 20-25 years old,5'9\", 145 pounds, with very short brown hair.He was wearing a dark blue suit and carryinga brown leather briefcase.Solicitor #2 is a white male, 25-30 years old,6'2\", 200 pounds, with a shaved-head. He waswearing a red T-shirt and jeans.Solicitor #3 is a white male, approximately23 years old, 5'10\", slight build, with shortbrown hair. He was wearing a blue suit.Three days after the block association meet-ing, a resident noticed a man knocking ondoors in the neighborhood and phoned thepolice to report the illegal activity. This solic-itor was described as follows:Solicitor #4 is a white male, 22 years old, 140pounds, about 5'10\", with short brown hair.He was carrying a briefcase and wearing adark suit.Based on this description, which of the threesolicitations was also likely carried out bySolicitor #4?","options":{"A":"#1,#2,and#3","B":"#1,butnot#2and#3","C":"#1and#3,butnot#2","D":"#1and#2,butnot#3"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"#1and#3,butnot#2"},{"question":"Rita, an accomplished pastry chef who is well known for her artistic and exquisite wedding cakes, opened a bakery one year ago and is surprised that business has been so slow. A consultant she hired to conduct market research has reported that the local population doesn't think of her shop as one they would visit on a daily basis but rather a place they'd visit if they were celebrating a special occasion. Which of the following strategies should Rita employ to increase her daily business?","options":{"A":"makingcouponsavailablethatentitlethecouponholdertoreceivea25%discountonwedding,anniversary,orbirthdaycakes","B":"exhibitingatthenextBridalExpoandhavingpiecesofoneofherweddingcakesavailablefortasting","C":"placingaseriesofadsinthelocalnewspaperthatadvertisethewidearrayofbreads","D":"movingthebakerytotheothersideoftown"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"placingaseriesofadsinthelocalnewspaperthatadvertisethewidearrayofbreads"},{"question":"Dr. Miller has a busy pediatric dentistry practice and she needs a skilled, reliable hygienist to keep things running smoothly. The last two people she hired were recommended by top dentists in the area, but they each lasted less than one month. She is now in desperate need of a hygienist who can competently handle the specific challenges of her practice. Which one of the following candidates should Dr. Miller consider most seriously?","options":{"A":"Marilynhasbeenahygienistforfifteenyears,andhercurrentemployer,whoisabouttoretire,sayssheisthebestinthebusiness.Theclienteleshehasworkedwithconsistsofsomeofthewealthiestandmostpowerfulcitizensinthecounty.","B":"Lindyrecentlygraduatedatthetopofherclassfromoneofthebestdentalhygieneprogramsinthestate.Priortobecomingadentalhygienist,Lindyspenttwoyearsworkinginadaycarecenter.","C":"Jameshasworkedasadentalhygienistforthreeyearsinapublichealthclinic.Heisveryinterestedinsecuringapositioninaprivatedentaloffice.","D":"Kathyisanexperiencedandhighlyrecommendeddentalhygienistwhoisalsofinishingupadegreeinearlychildhoodeducation,whichshehopeswillgetherajobasapreschoolteacher.Sheiseagertofindajobinapediatricpractice,sinceshehasalwayswantedtoworkwithchildren."},"answer_option":"B","answer":"Lindyrecentlygraduatedatthetopofherclassfromoneofthebestdentalhygieneprogramsinthestate.Priortobecomingadentalhygienist,Lindyspenttwoyearsworkinginadaycarecenter."},{"question":"Mrs. Jansen recently moved to Arizona. She wants to fill her new backyard with flowering plants. Although she is an experienced gardener, she isn't very well-versed in what plants will do well in the Arizona climate. Also, there is a big tree in her backyard making for shady conditions and she isn't sure what plants will thrive without much direct sunlight. Her favorite gardening catalog offers several backyard seed packages. Which one should Mrs. Jansen choose?","options":{"A":"TheRainbowCollectionisidealforNorth-eastgardens.Itincludesavarietyofcolorfulperennialsthatthriveincool,moistconditions.","B":"TheGreenhouseCollectionwillblossomyearafteryearifplantedinbrightlylitlocationsandwateredregularly.","C":"TheTreehouseCollectionwillprovidelushgreenplantswithdelicatecolorfulflowersthatthriveinshadyandpartiallyshadylocations.","D":"TheOasisCollectionincludesavarietyofperennialsthatthriveindryclimatesandbrightsunlight."},"answer_option":"C","answer":"TheTreehouseCollectionwillprovidelushgreenplantswithdelicatecolorfulflowersthatthriveinshadyandpartiallyshadylocations."}],"matching-definitions":[{"question":"Applying for Seasonal Employment occurs when a person requests to be considered for a job that is dependent on a particular season or time of year. Which situation below is the best example of Applying for Seasonal Employment?","options":{"A":"TheskiinstructorsatTopofthePeakSkiSchoolworkfromDecemberthroughMarch.","B":"Matthewprefersjobsthatallowhimtoworkoutdoors.","C":"Lucindamakesanappointmentwiththebeachresortrestaurantmanagertointerviewforthesummerwaitressingpositionthatwasadvertisedinthenewspaper.","D":"Doug'sicecreamshopstaysopenuntil11p.m.duringthesummermonths."},"answer_option":"C","answer":"Lucindamakesanappointmentwiththebeachresortrestaurantmanagertointerviewforthesummerwaitressingpositionthatwasadvertisedinthenewspaper."},{"question":"Violating an Apartment Lease occurs when a tenant does something prohibited by the legally binding document that he or she has signed with a landlord. Which situation below is the best example of Violating an Apartment Lease?","options":{"A":"Timhasdecidedtomovetoanothercity,sohecallshislandlordtotellhimthatheisnotinterestedinrenewinghisleasewhenitexpiresnextmonth.","B":"Valerierecentlylostherjoband,forthelastthreemonths,hasneglectedtopayherlandlordthemonthlyrenttheyagreeduponinwritingwhenshemovedintoherapartmenteightmonthsago.","C":"Markwritesalettertohislandlordthatlistsnumerouscomplaintsabouttheapartmenthehasagreedtorentfortwoyears.","D":"Lesliethinksthatherlandlordisneglectingthebuildinginwhichsherentsanapartment.Shecallsherattorneytoaskforadvice."},"answer_option":"B","answer":"Valerierecentlylostherjoband,forthelastthreemonths,hasneglectedtopayherlandlordthemonthlyrenttheyagreeduponinwritingwhenshemovedintoherapartmenteightmonthsago."},{"question":"An Informal Gathering occurs when a group of people get together in a casual, relaxed manner. Which situation below is the best example of an Informal Gathering?","options":{"A":"ThebookclubmeetsonthefirstThursdayeveningofeverymonth.","B":"Afterfindingoutabouthispromotion,Jeremyandafewcoworkersdecidetogooutforaquickdrinkafterwork.","C":"Marysendsout25invitationsforthebridalshowersheisgivingforhersister.","D":"WheneversheeatsattheMexicanrestaurant,ClaraseemstorunintoPeter."},"answer_option":"B","answer":"Afterfindingoutabouthispromotion,Jeremyandafewcoworkersdecidetogooutforaquickdrinkafterwork."},{"question":"People speculate when they consider a situation and assume something to be true based on inconclusive evidence. Which situation below is the best example of Speculation ?","options":{"A":"FrancinedecidesthatitwouldbeappropriatetowearjeanstohernewofficeonFridayafterreadingabout\"CasualFridays\"inheremployeehandbook.","B":"Maryspendsthirtyminutessittingintrafficandwishesthatshetookthetraininsteadofdriving.","C":"Afterconsultingseveralguidebooksandhertravelagent,Jenniferfeelsconfidentthatthehotelshehaschosenisfirst-rate.","D":"WhenEmilyopensthedoorintears,Theoguessesthatshe'shadadeathinherfamily."},"answer_option":"D","answer":"WhenEmilyopensthedoorintears,Theoguessesthatshe'shadadeathinherfamily."},{"question":"Posthumous Publication occurs when a book is published after the author's death. Which situation below is the best example of Posthumous Publication ?","options":{"A":"Richard'sillnesstookhislifebeforehewasabletoenjoytheamazingearlyreviewsofhisnovel.","B":"Melissa'spublishercancelsherbookcontractaftershefailstodeliverthemanuscriptontime.","C":"Clarenceneverthoughthe'dlivetoseethethirdbookinhistrilogypublished.","D":"Elizabethishonoredwithaprestigiousliteraryawardforherwritingcareerandherdaughteracceptstheawardonbehalfofherdeceasedmother."},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Richard'sillnesstookhislifebeforehewasabletoenjoytheamazingearlyreviewsofhisnovel."},{"question":"A Guarantee is a promise or assurance that attests to the quality of a product that is either (1) given in writing by the manufacturer or (2) given verbally by the person selling the product. Which situation below is the best example of a Guarantee?","options":{"A":"MelissapurchasesaDVDplayerwiththehighestconsumerratingsinitscategory.","B":"ThesalespersonadvisesCurttobesurethathebuysanairconditionerwithaguarantee.","C":"Thelocalautobodyshopspecializesinrefurbishingandsellingusedcars.","D":"LoribuysauseddigitalcamerafromhercoworkerwhosaysthatshewillrefundLori'smoneyifthecamera'sperformanceisnotofthehighestquality."},"answer_option":"D","answer":"LoribuysauseddigitalcamerafromhercoworkerwhosaysthatshewillrefundLori'smoneyifthecamera'sperformanceisnotofthehighestquality."},{"question":"The rules of baseball state that a batter Legally Completes His Time at Bat when he is put out or becomes a base runner. Which situation below is the best example of a batter Legally Completing His Time at Bat?","options":{"A":"Jared'sblooperovertheheadoftheshort-stopputshiminscoringposition.","B":"Theumpirecallsastrike,eventhoughthelastpitchwaswayoutside.","C":"Thepitcherthrowshisfamousknuckleball,Joeswingsandmisses,andtheumpirecallsastrike.","D":"ThecountistwoballsandtwostrikesasMariowaitsforthenextpitch."},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Jared'sblooperovertheheadoftheshort-stopputshiminscoringposition."},{"question":"Erratic Behavior occurs when an individual acts in a manner that lacks consistency, regularity, and uniformity. Which situation below is the best example of Erratic Behavior?","options":{"A":"Juliacannotcontainherangerwheneverthesubjectoflocalpoliticsisdiscussed.","B":"Martinhasjustbeentoldthatheisbeinglaidoff.Beforeleavinghissupervisor'soffice,hepunchesaholeinthedoor.","C":"Rhondahasvisitedthedealershipseveraltimes,butshestillcannotdecidewhichcartobuy.","D":"Inthepastmonth,Jeffrey,whohasbeenamodelemployeeforthreeyears,hasrepeatedlycalledinsick,forgottenimportantmeetings,andbeenverballyabusivetocolleagues."},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Inthepastmonth,Jeffrey,whohasbeenamodelemployeeforthreeyears,hasrepeatedlycalledinsick,forgottenimportantmeetings,andbeenverballyabusivetocolleagues."},{"question":"A Tiebreaker is an additional contest or period of play designed to establish a winner among tied contestants. Which situation below is the best example of a Tiebreaker?","options":{"A":"Athalftime,thescoreistiedat28.","B":"MaryandMeganhaveeachscoredthreegoalsinthegame.","C":"Therefereetossesacointodecidewhichteamwillhavepossessionoftheballfirst.","D":"TheSharksandtheBearseachfinishedwith14points,andtheyarenowbattlingitoutinafive-minuteovertime."},"answer_option":"D","answer":"TheSharksandtheBearseachfinishedwith14points,andtheyarenowbattlingitoutinafive-minuteovertime."},{"question":"In the Maple Hill school district, a Five-Day Suspension occurs when a student is not permitted to attend school for five days for  (1) physically assaulting another student, a teacher, or a school employee or (2) willfully destructing or defacing school property. Which situation below is the best example of a Five-Day Suspension?","options":{"A":"Lilliangetscaughtcheatingonamathtestforthesecondtimeandissuspendedfromschool.","B":"Marcisaskedtoleavetheclassroomduetohisconstantdisruptions.","C":"Frannyusesspraypainttowritederogatorycommentsonthelockerroomwallandsheisgivenasuspension.","D":"Ms.Farmertellsherclassthatstudentswhofailthemidtermexamwillbeexpectedtostayafterschoolfortutoringhelp."},"answer_option":"C","answer":"Frannyusesspraypainttowritederogatorycommentsonthelockerroomwallandsheisgivenasuspension."},{"question":"It is appropriate to compensate someone if you have damaged his or her property in some way. This is called Restitution. Which situation below is the best example of Restitution?","options":{"A":"JakeborrowsLeslie'scameraandthelensshatterswhenitfallsonthegroundbecausehefailstozipperthecase.WhenJakereturnsthecamera,hetellsLesliethathewillpayfortherepair.","B":"Rebeccaborrowsherneighbor'scar,andwhenshereturnsit,thegastankispracticallyempty.Sheapologizesprofuselyandtellsherneighborshewillbemoreconsideratethenexttime.","C":"AaronasksTomtocheckinonhisapartmentwhileheisoutoftown.WhenTomarrives,hediscoversthatapipehasburstandthereisaconsiderableamountofwaterdamage.Hecallsaplumbertorepairthepipe.","D":"Lisasuspectsthatthepotholeinhercompany'sparkinglotcausedherflattire.Shetellsherbossthatshethinksthecompanyshouldpayfortherepair."},"answer_option":"A","answer":"JakeborrowsLeslie'scameraandthelensshatterswhenitfallsonthegroundbecausehefailstozipperthecase.WhenJakereturnsthecamera,hetellsLesliethathewillpayfortherepair."},{"question":"Reentry occurs when a person leaves his or her social system for a period of time and then returns. Which situation below best describes Reentry ?","options":{"A":"Whenheisofferedabetterpayingposition,Jacobleavestherestauranthemanagestomanageanewrestaurantontheothersideoftown.","B":"CatherineisspendingherjunioryearofcollegestudyingabroadinFrance.","C":"Malcolmisreadjustingtocivilianlifeaftertwoyearsofoverseasmilitaryservice.","D":"Afterseveralmiserablemonths,SharondecidesthatshecannolongershareanapartmentwithherroommateHilary."},"answer_option":"C","answer":"Malcolmisreadjustingtocivilianlifeaftertwoyearsofoverseasmilitaryservice."},{"question":"Embellishing the Truth occurs when a person adds fictitious details or exaggerates facts or true stories. Which situation below is the best example of Embellishing the Truth?","options":{"A":"Isabelgoestothetheater,andthenextday,shetellshercoworkersshethoughttheplaywasexcellent.","B":"Therealtordescribesthehouse,whichiselevenblocksawayfromtheocean,asprimewaterfrontproperty.","C":"Duringthejobinterview,Fred,whohasbeenteachingelementaryschoolfortenyears,describeshimselfasaveryexperiencedteacher.","D":"Thebasketballcoachsaysitislikelythatonlythemosttalentedplayerswillgetacollegescholarship."},"answer_option":"B","answer":"Therealtordescribesthehouse,whichiselevenblocksawayfromtheocean,asprimewaterfrontproperty."},{"question":"Establishing a Power of Attorney occurs when a legal document is created that gives one individual the authority to act for another. Which situation below is the best example of Establishing a Power of Attorney?","options":{"A":"Louiseissellingherhouseandshehiresalawyertoreviewthecontract.","B":"Simone'smothercannolongergettothebanktocashherchecksandmakedeposits,soshehastakenlegalstepstoenableSimonetodothesethingsforher.","C":"Jack'sfatheriselderlyandJackthinksheisnolongerabletomakedecisionsforhimself.","D":"Atherdaughter'surging,Mrs.Lenoxopensuparetirementaccountwiththelocalbank."},"answer_option":"B","answer":"Simone'smothercannolongergettothebanktocashherchecksandmakedeposits,soshehastakenlegalstepstoenableSimonetodothesethingsforher."}],"number-series":[{"question":"Look at this series: 2, 1, (1/2), (1/4), ... What number should come next?","options":{"A":"(1/3)","B":"(1/8)","C":"(2/8)","D":"(1/16)"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"(1/8)"},{"question":"Look at this series: 7, 10, 8, 11, 9, 12, ... What number should come next?","options":{"A":"7","B":"10","C":"12","D":"13"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"10"},{"question":"Look at this series: 36, 34, 30, 28, 24, ... What number should come next?","options":{"A":"20","B":"22","C":"23","D":"26"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"22"},{"question":"Look at this series: 22, 21, 23, 22, 24, 23, ... What number should come next?","options":{"A":"22","B":"24","C":"25","D":"26"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"25"},{"question":"Look at this series: 53, 53, 40, 40, 27, 27, ... What number should come next?","options":{"A":"12","B":"14","C":"27","D":"53"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"14"},{"question":"28 25 5 21 18 5 14","options":{"A":"11/5","B":"10/7","C":"11/8","D":"5/10","E":"10/5"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"11/5"},{"question":"8 11 21 15 18 21 22","options":{"A":"25/18","B":"25/21","C":"25/29","D":"24/21","E":"22/26"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"25/21"},{"question":"9 16 23 30 37 44 51","options":{"A":"59/66","B":"56/62","C":"58/66","D":"58/65","E":"54/61"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"58/65"},{"question":"2 8 14 20 26 32 38","options":{"A":"2/46","B":"44/50","C":"42/48","D":"40/42","E":"32/26"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"44/50"},{"question":"9 11 33 13 15 33 17","options":{"A":"19/33","B":"33/35","C":"33/19","D":"15/33","E":"19/21"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"19/33"},{"question":"42 40 38 35 33 31 28","options":{"A":"25/22","B":"26/23","C":"26/24","D":"25/23","E":"26/22"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"26/24"},{"question":"6 10 14 18 22 26 30","options":{"A":"36/40","B":"33/37","C":"38/42","D":"34/36","E":"34/38"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"34/38"},{"question":"8 12 9 13 10 14 11","options":{"A":"14/11","B":"15/12","C":"8/15","D":"15/19","E":"8/5"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"15/12"},{"question":"36 31 29 24 22 17 15","options":{"A":"13/11","B":"10/5","C":"13/8","D":"12/7","E":"10/8"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"10/8"},{"question":"3 5 35 10 12 35 17","options":{"A":"22/35","B":"35/19","C":"19/35","D":"19/24","E":"22/24"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"19/35"},{"question":"Look at this series: F2, __, D8, C16, B32, ... What number should fill the blank?","options":{"A":"A16","B":"G4","C":"E4","D":"E3"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"E4"},{"question":"Look at this series: 664, 332, 340, 170, ____, 89, ... What number should fill the blank?","options":{"A":"85","B":"97","C":"109","D":"178"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"178"},{"question":"Look at this series: V, VIII, XI, XIV, __, XX, ... What number should fill the blank?","options":{"A":"IX","B":"XXIII","C":"XV","D":"XVII"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"XVII"},{"question":"Look at this series: 70, 71, 76, __, 81, 86, 70, 91, ... What number should fill the blank?","options":{"A":"70","B":"71","C":"80","D":"96"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"70"},{"question":"Look at this series: 8, 43, 11, 41, __, 39, 17, ... What number should fill in the blank?","options":{"A":"8","B":"14","C":"43","D":"44"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"14"}],"statement-and-argument":[{"question":"Statement: Should India encourage exports, when most things are insufficient for internal use itself? Arguments:     Yes. We have to earn foreign exchange to pay for our imports.     No. Even selective encouragement would lead to shortages. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should all the drugs patented and manufactured in Western countries be first tried out on sample basis before giving licence for sale to general public in India? Arguments:     Yes. Many such drugs require different doses and duration for Indian population and hence it is necessary.     No. This is just not feasible and hence cannot be implemented. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should India make efforts to harness solar energy to fulfil its energy requirements? Arguments:     Yes, Most of the energy sources used at present is exhaustible.     No. Harnessing solar energy requires a lot of capital, which India lacks in. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should there be students union in college/university? Arguments:     No. This will create a political atmosphere in the campus.     Yes, it is very necessary Students are future political leaders. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIarestrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should India give away Kashmir to Pakistan? Arguments:     No. Kashmir is a beautiful state. It earns a lot of foreign exchange for India.     Yes. This would help settle conflicts. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should cottage industries be encouraged in rural areas? Arguments:     Yes. Rural people are creative.     Yes. This would help to solve the problem of unemployment to some extent. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should young entrepreneurs be encouraged? Arguments:     Yes. They will help in industrial development of the country.     Yes. They will reduce the burden on employment market. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIarestrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should all the annual examinations up to Std. V be abolished? Arguments:     Yes. The young students should not be burdened with such examinations which hampers their natural growth.     No. The students will not study seriously as they will get automatic promotion to the next class and this will affect them in future. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIarestrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should Indian scientists working abroad be called back to India? Arguments:     Yes. They must serve the motherland first and forget about discoveries, honours, facilities and all.     No. We have enough talent; let them stay where they want. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should we scrap the system of formal education beyond graduation? Arguments:     Yes. It will mean taking employment at an early date.     No. It will mean lack of depth of knowledge. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should there be an upper age limit of 65 years for contesting Parliamentary/ Legislative Assembly elections? Arguments:     Yes. Generally, people above the age of 65 lose their dynamism and will power.     No. The life span is so increased that people remain physically and mentally active even up to the age of 80. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should new big industries be started in Mumbai? Arguments:     Yes. It will create job opportunities.     No. It will further add to the pollution of the city. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"EitherIorIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should high chimneys be installed in industries? Arguments:     Yes. It reduces pollution at ground level.     No. It increases pollution in upper atmosphere. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Does India need so many plans for development? Arguments:     Yes. Nothing can be achieved without proper planning.     No. Too much time, money and energy is wasted on planning. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should articles of only deserving authors be allowed to be published? Arguments:     Yes. It will save a lot of paper which is in short supply.     No. It is not possible to draw a line between the deserving and the undeserving. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should colleges be given the status of a university in India? Arguments:     Yes. Colleges are in a better position to assess the student's performance and therefore the degrees will be more valid.     No. It is Utopian to think that there will not be nepotism and corruption in awarding degrees by colleges. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should the prestigious people who have committed crime unknowingly, be met with special treatment? Arguments:     Yes. The prestigious people do not commit crime intentionally.     No. It is our policy that everybody is equal before the law. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Can pollution be controlled? Arguments:     Yes. If everyone realizes the hazards it may create and cooperates to get rid of it, pollution may be controlled.     No. The crowded highways, factories and industries and an ever-growing population eager to acquire more and more land for constructing houses are beyond control. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"EitherIorIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should the railways in India be privatized in a phased manner like other public sector enterprises? Arguments:     Yes. This is the only way to bring in competitiveness and provide better services to the public.     No. This will pose a threat to the national security of our country as multinationals will enter into the fray. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should internal assessment in colleges be abolished? Arguments:     Yes. This will help in reducing the possibility of favouritism.     No, teaching faculty will lose control over students. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should all the unauthorized structures in the city be demolished? Arguments:     No. Where will the people residing in such houses live?     Yes. This will give a clear message to general public and they will refrain from constructing unauthorized buildings. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should there be a maximum limit for the number of ministers in the Central Government? Arguments:     No. The political party in power should have the freedom to decide the number of ministers to be appointed.     Yes. The number of ministers should be restricted to a certain percentage of the total number of seats in the parliament to avoid unnecessary expenditure. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should foreign films be banned in India? Arguments:     Yes. They depict an alien culture which adversely affects our values.     No. Foreign films are of a high artistic standard. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Is buying things on instalments profitable to the customer? Arguments:     Yes. He has to pay less.     No, paying instalments upsets the family budget. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should Doordarshan be given autonomous status? Arguments:     Yes. It will help Doordarshan to have fair and impartial coverage of all important events.     No. The coverage of events will be decided by a few who may not have healthy outlook. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should adult education programme be given priority over compulsory education programme? Arguments:     No. It will also help in success of compulsory education programme.     Yes. It will help to eliminate the adult illiteracy. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should new universities be established in India? Arguments:     No. We have still not achieved the target for literacy.     No. We will have to face the problem of unemployed but highly qualified people. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIarestrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should non-vegetarian food be totally banned in our country? Arguments:     Yes. It is expensive and therefore it is beyond the means of most people in our country.     No. Nothing should be banned in a democratic country like ours. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should a total ban be put on trapping wild animals? Arguments:     Yes. Trappers are making a lot of money;     No. Bans on hunting and trapping are not effective. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should Government close down loss-making public sector enterprises? Arguments:     No. All employees will lose their jobs, security and earning, what would they do?     Yes. In a competitive world the rule is 'survival of the fittest'. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should government jobs in rural areas have more incentives? Arguments:     Yes. Incentives are essential for attracting government servants there.     No. Rural areas are already cheaper, healthier and less complex than big cities. So ? Why offer extra incentives! ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should there be a cap on maximum number of contestants for parliamentary elections in any constituency? Arguments:     Yes. This will make the parliamentary elections more meaningful as the voters can make a considered judgement for casting their vote.     No. In a democracy any person fulfilling the eligibility criteria can contest parliamentary elections and there should be no restrictions. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIarestrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should so much money be spent on advertisements? Arguments:     Yes. It is an essential concomitant in a capitalist economy.     No. It leads to wastage of resources. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should all the legislators be forced to resign from their profession? Arguments:     Yes. They will be able to devote more time for the country.     No, nobody will contest election. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should 'computer knowledge' be made a compulsory subject for all the students at secondary school level? Arguments:     No, our need is 'bread' for everyone, we cannot follow western models.     Yes. We cannot compete in the international market without equipping our children with computers. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should there be uniforms for students in the colleges in India as in the schools? Arguments:     Yes, this will improve the ambience of the colleges as all the students will be decently dressed.     No. The college students should not be regimented and they should be left to choose their clothes for coming to the college. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should India engage into a dialogue with neighbouring countries to stop cross border tension? Arguments:     Yes. This is the only way to reduce the cross border terrorism and stop loss of innocent lives.     No. Neighbouring countries cannot be relied upon in such matters, they may still engage in subversive activities. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should there be a world government? Arguments:     Yes. It will help in eliminating tensions among the nations.     No. Then, only the developed countries will dominate in the government. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should the practice of transfers of clerical cadre employees from government offices of one city to those of another be stopped? Arguments:     No. Transfer of employees is a routine administrative matter and we must continue it.     Yes. It involves lot of governmental expenditure and inconvenience too many compared to the benefits it yields. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Is paying ransom or agreeing to the conditions of kidnappers of political figures, a proper course of action? Arguments:     Yes. The victims must be saved at all cost.     No. It encourages the kidnappers to continue their sinister activities. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIarestrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should religion be banned? Arguments:     Yes. It develops fanaticism in people.     No, Religion binds people together. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"EitherIorIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should India become a permanent member of UN's Security Council? Arguments:     Yes. India has emerged as a country which loves peace and amity.     No. Let us first solve problems of our own people like poverty, malnutrition. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should fashionable dresses be banned? Arguments:     Yes. Fashions keep changing and hence consumption of cloth increases.     No. Fashionable clothes are a person's self expression and therefore his/her fundamental right. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should an organization like UNO be dissolved? Arguments:     Yes. With cold war coming to an end, such organizations have no role to play     No, In the absence of such organizations there may be a world war. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should there be no place of interview in selection? Arguments:     Yes, it is very subjective in assessment.     No. It is the only instrument to judge candidates' motives and personality. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should family planning be made compulsory in India? Arguments:     Yes. Looking to the miserable conditions in India, there is no other go.     No. In India there are people of various religions and family planning is against the tenets of some of the religions. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIarestrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should income tax be abolished in India? Arguments:     Yes. It is an unnecessary burden on the wage earners.     No. It is a good source of revenue. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should there be a ceiling on the salary of top executives of multinationals in our country? Arguments:     Yes. Otherwise it would lead to unhealthy competition and our own industry would not be able to withstand that.     No. With the accent on liberalization of economy, any such move would be counter-productive. Once the economy picks up, this disparity will be reduced. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIarestrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should school education be made free in India? Arguments:     Yes. This is the only way to improve the level of literacy.     No. It would add to the already heavy burden on the exchequer. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should import duty on all the electronic goods be dispensed with? Arguments:     No. This will considerably reduce the income of the government and will adversely affect the developmental activities.     No. The local manufacturers will not be able to compete with the foreign manufacturers who are technologically far superior. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should children be legally made responsible to take care of their parents during their old age? Arguments:     Yes. Such matter can only be solved by legal means.     Yes. Only this will bring some relief to poor parents. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should there be reservation in Government jobs for candidates from single child family? Arguments:     No. This is not advisable as the jobs should be offered to only deserving candidates without any reservation for a particular group.     Yes. This will help reduce the growing population in India as the parents will be encouraged to adopt single child norm. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should higher education be completely stopped for some time? Arguments:     No. It will hamper the country's future progress.     Yes. It will reduce the educated unemployment. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should we scrap the 'Public Distribution System' in India? Arguments:     Yes, Protectionism is over, everyone must get the bread on his/her own.     Yes. The poor do not get any benefit because of corruption. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should India have no military force at all? Arguments:     No. Other countries in the world do not believe in non-violence.     Yes. Many Indians believe in non-violence. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Are nuclear families better than joint families? Arguments:     No. Joint families ensure security and also reduce the burden of work.     Yes. Nuclear families ensure greater freedom. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIarestrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should government stop spending huge amounts of money on international sports? Arguments:     Yes. This money can be utilized for upliftment of the poor.     No. Sports persons will be frustrated and will not get international exposure. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should the railways immediately stop issuing free passes to all its employees? Arguments:     No. The employees have the right to travel free.     Yes. This will help railways to provide better facility. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should there be compulsory medical examination of both the man and the woman before they marry each other? Arguments:     No. This is an intrusion to the privacy of an individual and hence cannot be tolerated.     Yes. This will substantially reduce the risk of giving birth to children with serious ailments. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should there be a ban on product advertising? Arguments:     No. It is an age of advertising. Unless your advertisement is better than your other competitors, the product will not be sold.     Yes. The money spent on advertising is very huge and it inflates the cost of the product. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIarestrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should luxury hotels be banned in India? Arguments:     Yes. They are places from where international criminals operate.     No. Affluent foreign tourists will have no place to stay. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should shifting agriculture be practised? Arguments:     No. It is a wasteful practice.     Yes. Modern methods of farming are too expensive. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should our country extend generous behaviour and goodwill to our erring and nagging neighbours? Arguments:     Yes. Goodwill always pays dividend.     No. Our generous behaviour and goodwill will be considered as our weakness. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIarestrong"},{"question":"Statement: Is pen mightier than a sword? Arguments:     Yes. Writers influence the thinking of the people.     No. With the help of physical force one can conquer all. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should the sex determination test during pregnancy be completely banned? Arguments:     Yes. This leads to indiscriminate female foeticide and eventually will lead to social imbalance.     No. People have a right to know about their unborn child. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should persons convicted of criminal offences in the past be allowed to contest elections in India? Arguments:     No. Such persons cannot serve the cause of the people and country.     Yes. It is democracy - let people decide whom to vote. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should officers accepting bribe be punished? Arguments:     No. Certain circumstances may have compelled them to take bribe.     Yes. They should do the job they are entrusted with, honestly. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should there be a complete ban on use of all types of chemical pesticides in India? Arguments:     No. The pests will destroy all the crops and the farmers will have nothing to harvest.     Yes. The chemical pesticides used in agriculture pollute the water underground and this has become a serious health hazard. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIarestrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should cutting of trees be banned altogether? Arguments:     Yes. It is very much necessary to do so to restore ecological balance.     No. A total ban would harm timber based industries. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIarestrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should there be a restriction on the migration of people from one state to another state in India? Arguments:     No. Any Indian citizen has a basic right to stay at any place of his/her choice and hence they cannot be stopped.     Yes. This is the way to effect an equitable distribution of resources across the states in India. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should all refugees, who make unauthorized entry into a country, be forced to go back to their homeland?                                                            Arguments:     Yes. They make their colonies and occupy a lot of land.     No. They leave their homes because of hunger or some terror and on human grounds, should not be forced to go back. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should India create a huge oil reserve like some Western countries to face difficult situations in future? Arguments:     No. There is no need to block huge amount of foreign exchange and keep the money idle.     Yes. This will help India withstand shocks of sudden rise in oil prices due to unforeseen circumstances. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should there be more than one High Court in each state in India? Arguments:     No. This will be a sheer wastage of taxpayers' money.     Yes. This will help reduce the backlog of cases pending for a very long time. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should judiciary be independent of the executive? Arguments:     Yes. This would help curb the unlawful activities of the executive.     No. The executive would not be able to take bold measures. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should all the practising doctors be brought under Government control so that they get salary from the Government and treat patients free of cost? Arguments:     No. How can any country do such an undemocratic thing?     Yes. Despite many problems, it will certainly help minimize, if not eradicate, unethical medical practices. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should students take part in politics? Arguments:     Yes. It inculcates in them qualities of leadership.     No. They should study and build up their career. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"EitherIorIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should the opinion polls predicting outcome of elections before the elections be banned in India? Arguments:     Yes. This may affect the voters mind and may affect the outcome.     No. Such polls are conducted all over the world. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should the political parties be banned? Arguments:     Yes. It is necessary to teach a lesson to the politicians.     No. It will lead to an end of democracy. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should system of offering jobs only to the wards of government employees be introduced in all government offices in India? Arguments:     No. It denies opportunity to many deserving individuals and government may stand to lose in the long run.     No. It is against the principle of equality, does not government owe its responsibility to all its citizens? ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIarestrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should the vehicles older than 15 years be rejected in metros in India? Arguments:     Yes. This is a significant step to lower down the pollution level in metros.     No. It will be very difficult for vehicle owners to shift to other parts in country because they will not get suitable job for their very existence. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should the tuition fees in all post-graduate courses be hiked considerably? Arguments:     Yes. This will bring in some sense of seriousness among the students and will improve the quality.     No. This will force the meritorious poor students to stay away from post-graduate courses. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should the persons below the age of 18 years be allowed to join armed forces? Arguments:     No. Persons below the age of 18 do not attain both physical and mental maturity to shoulder such burden.     Yes. This will help the country develop its armed forces which will serve the country for a longer time. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should all the infrastructural development projects in India be handed over to the private sector? Arguments:     No. The private sector entities are hot equipped to handle such projects.     Yes. Such projects are handled by private sector in the developed countries. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should all the colleges in India be allowed to devise their own curriculum and syllabus for the vocational courses promoting self-employment? Arguments:     Yes. This is an important step to generate employment opportunities.     No. This will affect the quality of education due to lack of uniformity in syllabus. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should agriculture in rural India be mechanized? Arguments:     Yes. It would lead to higher production.     No. Many villagers would be left unemployed. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should there be concentration of foreign investment in only few states? Arguments:     No. It is against the policy of overall development of the country.     Yes. A large number of states lack infrastructure to attract foreign investment. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should the oil companies be allowed to fix the price of petroleum products depending on market conditions? Arguments:     Yes. This is the only way to make the oil companies commercially viable.     No. This will put additional burden on the retail prices of essential commodities and will cause a lot of hardships to the masses. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should the education at all levels be offered only in vernacular medium? Arguments:     Yes. This is the only way to enhance performance of the students.     No. This will severely affect acquiring knowledge for want of good text books in vernacular medium. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should there be only one rate of interest for term deposits of varying durations in banks? Arguments:     No. People will refrain from keeping money for longer duration resulting into reduction of liquidity level of banks.     Yes. This will be much simple for the common people and they may be encouraged to keep more money in banks. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should all news be controlled by Government in a democracy? Arguments:     Yes. Variety of news only confuses people.     No. Controlled news loses credibility. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should taxes on colour television be further increased? Arguments:     Yes, Colour television is a luxury item and only rich people buy them.     No, Televisions are bought by the poor too. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should the educated unemployed youth be paid \"unemployment allowance\" by the Government? Arguments:     Yes. It will provide them some monetary help to either seek employment or to kick-start some 'self-employment' venture.     No. It will dampen their urge to do something to earn their livelihood and thus promote idleness among the unemployed youth. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIarestrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should higher education be restricted to only those who can bear the expenditure? Arguments:     Yes. Higher education is very costly; hence it should not be given free.     No. There are a large number of brilliant students who cannot afford to pay and they should be given higher education. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should those who receive dowry, despite the law prohibiting it, be punished? Arguments:     Yes. Those who violate the law must be punished.     No. Dowry system is firmly rooted in the society since time immemorial. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Is the Government justified in spending so much on defence? Arguments:     Yes. Safety of the country is of prime importance.     No. During peace, this money could be used for the development of the country. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should girls learn arts like judo and karate? Arguments:     Yes. It will enable them to defend themselves from rogues and ruffians.     No. They will lose their feminine grace. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should India develop a national water grid by connecting all the rivers in the country? Arguments:     No. This is not just possible as we do not have the technical knowhow.     Yes, this will greatly help the entire country by effectively channelizing the excess water to the areas having shortage. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should individuals/institutes having treasures of national significance like Nobel Prizes, hand them over to the Central Government for their safe custody? Arguments:     Yes. The individuals or institutions do not have enough resources to protect them.     No. These are the property of the individuals/institutions who win them and should be in their custody. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should there be reservation of seats and posts on communal basis? Arguments:     Yes. It will check most of the inter-communal biases.     No, ours is a secular state. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should octroi be abolished? Arguments:     Yes. It will eliminate an important source of corruption.     No. It will adversely affect government revenues. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIarestrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should public holidays be declared on demise of important national leaders? Arguments:     No. Such unscheduled holidays hamper national progress.     Yes. People would like to pay their homage to the departed soul. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should India support all the international policies of United States of America? Arguments:     No. Many other powerful countries do not support the same.     Yes. This is the only way to gain access to USA developmental funds. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should words like 'Smoking is injurious to health essentially appear on cigarette packs? Arguments:     Yes. It is a sort of brainwash to make the smokers realize that they are inhaling poisonous stuff.     No. It hampers the enjoyment of smoking. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyargumentIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement: Should the council of ministers once appointed be kept the same for the entire period intervening two elections? Arguments:     No. Shuffling of ministers and portfolios is a healthy democratic process.     Yes. The ministers do not get a hold on their portfolio unless they are kept for a longer duration. ","options":{"A":"OnlyargumentIisstrong","B":"OnlyargumentIIisstrong","C":"EitherIorIIisstrong","D":"NeitherInorIIisstrong","E":"BothIandIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement:  Should people with educational qualification higher than the optimum requirements be debarred from seeking jobs? Arguments:   No. It will further aggravate the problem of educated unemployment. Yes. It creates complexes among employees and affects the work adversely. No. This goes against the basic rights of the individuals.Yes. This will increase productivity.   ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIIarestrong","B":"Allarestrong","C":"OnlyIIandIVarestrong","D":"OnlyIIIisstrong","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"OnlyIIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement:  Should India go in for computerization in all possible sectors? Arguments:   Yes. It will bring efficiency and accuracy in the work. No. It will be an injustice to the monumental human resources which are at present underutilized. No. Computerization demands a lot of money. We should not waste money on it.Yes. When advanced countries are introducing computers in every field, how can India afford to lag behind?   ","options":{"A":"OnlyIisstrong","B":"OnlyIandIIarestrong","C":"OnlyIandIIIarestrong","D":"OnlyIIandIIIarestrong","E":"Allarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement:  Should all the school teachers be debarred from giving private tuitions? Arguments:   No. The needy students will be deprived of the expertise of these teachers. Yes. This is an injustice to the unemployed educated people who can earn their living by giving tuitions. Yes. Only then the quality of teaching in schools will improve.Yes. Now salary of these teachers is reasonable.   ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIIarestrong","B":"OnlyI,IIandIIIarestrong","C":"OnlyIIIandIVarestrong","D":"OnlyII,IIIandIVarestrong","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Noneofthese"},{"question":"Statement:  Should education be made compulsory for all children up to the age of 14? Arguments:   Yes. This will help to eradicate the system of forced employment of these children. Yes. This is an effective way to make the entire population educated. No. We do not have adequate infrastructure to educate the entire population.Yes. This would increase the standard of living.   ","options":{"A":"Allarestrong","B":"OnlyI,IIandIIIarestrong","C":"OnlyI,IIandIVarestrong","D":"OnlyIIisstrong","E":"OnlyIIandIIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"OnlyIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement:  Should trade unions be banned completely? Arguments:   Yes. Workers can concentrate on production. No. This is the only way through which employees can put their demands before the management. Yes. Employees get their illegal demands fulfilled through these unions.No. Trade unions are not banned in other economically advanced countries.   ","options":{"A":"OnlyIisstrong","B":"OnlyIIisstrong","C":"OnlyIandIIarestrong","D":"OnlyI,IIandIIIarestrong","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement:  Should the public sector undertakings be kilo wed to adopt hire and fire policy? Arguments:   Yes. This will help the public sector undertakings to get rid of non-performing employees and reward the performing employees. No. This will give an unjust handle to the management and they may use it indiscriminately.  Yes. This will help increase the level of efficiency of these organizations and these will become profitable establishments.   ","options":{"A":"Noneisstrong","B":"OnlyIandIIarestrong","C":"OnlyIIandIIIarestrong","D":"OnlyIandIIIarestrong","E":"Allarestrong"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"OnlyIandIIIarestrong"},{"question":"Statement:  Is caste-based reservation policy in professional colleges justified? Arguments:   Yes. The step is a must to bring the underprivileged at par with the privileged ones. No. It obstructs the establishment of a classless society. Yes. This will help the backward castes and classes of people to come out of the oppression of upper caste people.   ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIarestrong","B":"OnlyIIisstrong","C":"OnlyIIandIIIarestrong","D":"OnlyIandIIIarestrong","E":"Allarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement:  Should there be a complete ban on genetically modified imported seeds? Arguments:   Yes. This will boost the demand of domestically developed seeds. No. This is the only way to increase production substantially. Yes. Genetically modified products will adversely affect the health of those who consume these products.   ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIarestrong","B":"OnlyIIisstrong","C":"OnlyIIandIIIarestrong","D":"OnlyIandIIIarestrong","E":"Allarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement:  Should the income generated out of agricultural activities be taxed? Arguments:   No. Farmers are otherwise suffering from natural calamities and low yield coupled with low procurement price and their income should not be taxed. Yes. Majority of the population is dependent on agriculture and hence their income should be taxed to augment the resources. Yes. Many big farmers earn much more than the majority of the service earners and they should be taxed to remove the disparity.   ","options":{"A":"OnlyIisstrong","B":"OnlyIandIIarestrong","C":"OnlyIIandIIIarestrong","D":"Allarestrong","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyIIandIIIarestrong"},{"question":"Statement:  Should all the management institutes in the country be brought under government control? Arguments:   No. The government does not have adequate resources to run such institutes effectively. No. Each institute should be given freedom to function on its own. Yes. This will enable to have standardized education for all the students.Yes. Only then the quality of education would be improved.   ","options":{"A":"Noneisstrong","B":"OnlyI,IIandIIIarestrong","C":"OnlyIandIIIarestrong","D":"Allarestrong","E":"OnlyIIIisstrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Noneisstrong"},{"question":"Statement:  Should the system of Lok Adalats and mobile courts be encouraged in India? Arguments:   Yes. It helps to grant speedy justice to the masses. Yes. The dispensing of minor cases at this level would reduce the burden on the higher courts. No. These courts are usually partial in justice.   ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIarestrong","B":"OnlyIIandIIIarestrong","C":"OnlyIandIIIarestrong","D":"Allarestrong","E":"OnlyIisstrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyIandIIarestrong"},{"question":"Statement:  Should India acquire/manufacture the latest nuclear weapons? Arguments:   Yes. The enemies of India are improving their weapons continuously and it becomes imperative to protect the sovereignty and integrity of the country. No. Instead the money should be diverted to development activities. No. The international community will isolate Indians and this will bring a setback to Indian economy.No. It will be against our policy of maintaining world peace.   ","options":{"A":"OnlyIisstrong","B":"OnlyIandIVarestrong","C":"OnlyI,IIandIVarestrong","D":"Allarestrong","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement:  Should there be a complete ban on manufacture and use of firecrackers? Arguments:   No. This will render thousands of workers jobless. Yes. The firecracker manufacturers use child labour to a large extent. Yes. This will be a concrete step to reduce noise and air pollution.No. Use of firecrackers makes certain special occasions more lively and joyful.   ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIarestrong","B":"OnlyIandIIIarestrong","C":"OnlyIIIandIVarestrong","D":"OnlyI,IIandIIIarestrong","E":"OnlyI,IIIandIVarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIandIIIarestrong"},{"question":"Statement:  Should \"literacy\" be the minimum criterion for becoming a voter in India? Arguments:   No. Mere literacy is no guarantee of political maturity of an individual. Yes. Illiterate people are less likely to make politically wiser decisions of voting for a right candidate or party. No. Voting is the constitutional right of every citizen.   ","options":{"A":"Noneisstrong","B":"OnlyIandIIarestrong","C":"OnlyIIIisstrong","D":"OnlyIIandIIIarestrong","E":"Allarestrong"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Allarestrong"},{"question":"Statement:  Should there be only few banks in place of numerous smaller banks in India? Arguments:   Yes. This will help secure the investor's money as these big banks will be able to withstand intermittent market related shocks. No. A large number of people will lose their jobs as after the merger many employees will be redundant. Yes. This will help consolidate the entire banking industry and will lead to healthy competition.   ","options":{"A":"Noneisstrong","B":"OnlyIandIIarestrong","C":"OnlyIIandIIIarestrong","D":"OnlyIandIIIarestrong","E":"Allarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Noneisstrong"},{"question":"Statement:  Should religion be taught in our schools? Arguments:   No. Ours is a secular state. Yes. Teaching religion helps inculcate moral values among children. No. How can one dream of such a step when we want the young generation to fulfil its role in the 21st century.   ","options":{"A":"Allarestrong","B":"Noneisstrong","C":"OnlyIisstrong","D":"OnlyIIisstrong","E":"OnlyIandIIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"OnlyIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement:  Should the parliamentary elections in India be held every three years as against five years at present? Arguments:   No. This will enhance wastage of money and resources. Yes. This will help the voters to change non-performing representatives without much delay. No. The elected representatives will not have enough time to settle and concentrate on developmental activities.                                                               ","options":{"A":"Noneisstrong","B":"OnlyIandIIarestrong","C":"OnlyIIandIIIarestrong","D":"OnlyIandIIIarestrong","E":"Allarestrong"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"OnlyIandIIIarestrong"},{"question":"Statement:  Should the number of holidays of government employees be reduced? Arguments:   Yes. Our government employees are having the maximum number of holidays among the countries of the world. Yes. It is a sign of British legacy, why should we carry it further? Yes. It will speed up work and all the pending jobs can be completed well in time.No. Employees must be given ample spare time to spend with their family.   ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIIarestrong","B":"OnlyIIIisstrong","C":"OnlyI,IIIandIVarestrong","D":"Noneisstrong","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement:  Should class IV children have Board examination? Arguments:   Yes. This will motivate the children to study and get higher marks, and thus more knowledge can be imbibed at a younger age. No. The children will be forced to study and won't enjoy the process. Yes. In today's competitive world the children need to be prepared right from the beginning to face such difficult examinations.No. This will add pressure on tender aged children and leave very little time for them to play.   ","options":{"A":"Allarestrong","B":"OnlyI,IIandIVarestrong","C":"OnlyII,IIIandIVarestrong","D":"OnlyIandIIIarestrong","E":"OnlyIandIVarestrong"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyII,IIIandIVarestrong"},{"question":"Statement:  Should the rule of wearing helmet for both driver and pillion rider while driving a motor bike be enforced strictly? Arguments:   Yes. It is a rule and rules should be followed strictly by all. No. Each individual knows how to protect his own life and it should be left to his discretion. No. It does not ensure safety as only the head is protected and rest of the body is not.Yes. It is a necessity as head, being the most sensitive organ, is protected by the helmet.   ","options":{"A":"Noneisstrong","B":"OnlyIandIIIarestrong","C":"OnlyIandIVarestrong","D":"OnlyIIandIVarestrong","E":"Allarestrong"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyIandIVarestrong"},{"question":"Statement:  Should all the students graduating in any discipline desirous of pursuing post-graduation of the subjects of their choice be allowed to enrol in the post-graduate courses? Arguments:   Yes. The students are the best judge of their capabilities and there should not be restrictions for joining post-graduate courses. No. The students need to study relevant subjects in graduate courses to enrol in post-graduate courses and the students must fulfil such conditions. No. There are not enough institutes offering post-graduate courses which can accommodate all the graduates desirous of seeking post-graduate education of their own choice.   ","options":{"A":"Noneisstrong","B":"OnlyIandIIarestrong","C":"Allarestrong","D":"OnlyIandIIIarestrong","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Noneofthese"},{"question":"Statement:  Should we impart sex education in schools? Arguments:   Yes. All the progressive nations do so. No. We cannot impart it in co-educational schools. Yes. It would certainly help in eradicating the existing misunderstanding and make the younger generation physically and mentally healthier.It will destroy the moral fibre and the highly esteemed value system which we have inherited from our forefathers.   ","options":{"A":"Noneisstrong","B":"OnlyI,IIIandIVarestrong","C":"OnlyII,IIIandIVarestrong","D":"OnlyIIandIVarestrong","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Noneofthese"},{"question":"Statement:  Should coal engines be replaced by electric engines in trains? Arguments:   Yes. Coal engines cause a lot of pollution. Yes. Electric engines are good on performance, easy to operate and low on maintenance. No. India does not produce enough electricity to fulfil its domestic needs also.   ","options":{"A":"Allarestrong","B":"OnlyIandIIarestrong","C":"OnlyIIandIIIarestrong","D":"OnlyIandIIIarestrong","E":"OnlyIisstrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIandIIarestrong"},{"question":"Statement:  Should all those who are convicted for heinous crimes like murder or rape, beyond all reasonable doubts be given capital punishment or death penalty? Arguments:   No. The death penalty should be given only in very rare and exceptional cases. Yes. This is the only way to punish such people who take others' lives or indulge in inhuman activities. Yes. Such severe punishments only will make people refrain from such heinous acts and the society will be safer.No. Those who are repentant for the crime they committed should be given a chance to improve and lead a normal life.   ","options":{"A":"OnlyIIandIVarestrong","B":"Allarestrong","C":"OnlyIIIisstrong","D":"OnlyIIandIIIarestrong","E":"OnlyI,IIandIIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyIIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement:  Should all the profit making public sector units be sold to private companies? Arguments:   Yes. This will help the government to augment its resources for implementing the development programmes. No. The private companies will not be able to run these units effectively. Yes. There will be a significant improvement in the quality of services.No. There would not be job security for the employees at all the levels.   ","options":{"A":"OnlyIIandIIIarestrong","B":"Allarestrong","C":"OnlyIIIandIVarestrong","D":"OnlyI,IIandIIIarestrong","E":"OnlyII,IIIandIVarestrong"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyIIIandIVarestrong"},{"question":"Statement:  Should all the youngsters below 21 years of age be disallowed from going to a beer bar? Arguments:   No. It is not correct to prevent matured youngsters above 18 years of age who can vote, from having fun. Yes. The entry fee to such pubs should also be hiked. No. There is no such curb in western countries.Yes. This will help in preventing youngsters from getting into bad company and imbibing bad habits.   ","options":{"A":"OnlyIisstrong","B":"OnlyIandIIIarestrong","C":"OnlyIIIandIVarestrong","D":"OnlyIandIVarestrong","E":"Noneisstrong"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"OnlyIandIVarestrong"},{"question":"Statement:  Should the government ban all forms of protests including strikes and processions? Arguments:   Yes. This is the only way to teach discipline to the employees. No. Government cannot deprive its citizens of their basic rights. Yes. This is the only way to ensure maximum productivity without disruption of work.   ","options":{"A":"Noneisstrong","B":"OnlyIandIIarestrong","C":"OnlyIIandIIIarestrong","D":"OnlyIandIIIarestrong","E":"Allarestrong"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyIIandIIIarestrong"},{"question":"Statement:  Should children be prevented completely from watching television? Arguments:   No. We get vital information regarding education through television. Yes. It hampers the study of children. Yes. Young children are misguided by certain programmes featuring sex and violence.No. This is the only way to educate the masses.   ","options":{"A":"OnlyI,IIandIIIarestrong","B":"OnlyIisstrong","C":"OnlyI,IIandIVarestrong","D":"OnlyIandIIarestrong","E":"OnlyI,IIIandIVarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement:  Should mercy death be legalized, i.e., all those who are suffering from terminal diseases be allowed to end their lives if they so desire? Arguments:   No. Nobody should be allowed to end his/her life at his/her will as this goes against the basic tenets of humanity. Yes. Patients undergoing terrible suffering and having absolutely no chance of recovery should be liberated from suffering through mercy death. No. Even mercy death is a sort of killing and killing can never be legalized.   ","options":{"A":"Noneisstrong","B":"OnlyIandIIarestrong","C":"OnlyIIandIIIarestrong","D":"OnlyIandIIIarestrong","E":"Allarestrong"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Allarestrong"},{"question":"Statement:  Should seniority be the only criterion for the promotion? Arguments:   No. It would be an injustice to those juniors who are more deserving and suitable for higher positions than their senior counterparts. Yes. Otherwise senior employees do feel humiliated. Yes. Senior employees are more experienced and must be rewarded for the same.   ","options":{"A":"Noneisstrong","B":"OnlyIisstrong","C":"OnlyIandIIIarestrong","D":"OnlyIandIIarestrong","E":"Allarestrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement:  Should admission to all professional courses be made on the basis of past academic performance rather than through entrance tests? Arguments:   Yes. It will be beneficial for those candidates who are unable to bear the expenses of entrance tests. Yes. Many deserving candidates securing high marks in their qualifying academic examinations do not perform well on such entrance tests. No. The standard of examinations and assessment conducted by different Boards and universities are not comparable and hence there is a need to conduct entrance tests to calibrate them on a common yardstick.   ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIarestrong","B":"OnlyIIandIIIarestrong","C":"OnlyIandIIIarestrong","D":"OnlyIIIisstrong","E":"Allarestrong"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"OnlyIIIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement:  Should there be reservation of jobs in the organizations in the private sector also as in the public sector undertakings in India? Arguments:   Yes. This would give more opportunities of development to the weaker sections of the society and thus help reduce the gap between the affluent and the downtrodden in India. No. The private sector does not get any government assistance and therefore they should not be saddled with such policies. No. Nowhere else in the world such a practice is being followed.No. The management of the private sector undertaking would not agree to such compulsions.   ","options":{"A":"OnlyIisstrong","B":"OnlyIandIIarestrong","C":"OnlyI,IIandIVarestrong","D":"OnlyIandIVarestrong","E":"Allarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement:  Should workers/employees be allowed to participate in the management of factories in India? Arguments:   Yes. It is the present management theory. No. Many workers are illiterate and so their contributions will not be of any value. Yes. Employees-owned companies generally have higher productivity.No. Employee-union ownership drives up salaries and wages.   ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIarestrong","B":"Noneisstrong","C":"OnlyIIandIIIarestrong","D":"Allarestrong","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyIIandIIIarestrong"},{"question":"Statement:  Should women be given equal opportunity in the matter of employment in every field? Arguments:   Yes. They are equally capable. No. They have to shoulder household responsibilities. Yes. They should also go into the outside world.   ","options":{"A":"OnlyIisstrong","B":"OnlyIandIIarestrong","C":"OnlyIIandIIIarestrong","D":"OnlyIandIIIarestrong","E":"Allarestrong"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"OnlyIandIIIarestrong"},{"question":"Statement:  Should government established higher level Institutes of Technology (IIT's) be privatized? Arguments:   Yes. Privatization will make these institutes financially healthy, competitive and quality conscious. Yes. Privatization is the key of the new era - can we survive without it? No. Standard of education of these institutes will fall.   ","options":{"A":"Noneisstrong","B":"Allarestrong","C":"OnlyIisstrong","D":"OnlyIandIIIarestrong","E":"OnlyIIandIIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyIisstrong"},{"question":"Statement:  Should there be only one university throughout India? Arguments:   Yes. This is the only way to bring about uniformity in the educational standards. No. This is administratively impossible. Yes. This will make the degrees procured by students, comparable for offering jobs.   ","options":{"A":"Noneisstrong","B":"OnlyIandIIarestrong","C":"OnlyIIandIIIarestrong","D":"OnlyIandIIIarestrong","E":"Allarestrong"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyIIandIIIarestrong"},{"question":"Statement:  Should India immediately stop digging coal from its mines? Arguments:   Yes. The present stock of coal will not last long if we continue mining at the present rate.                                             No. We do not have alternate energy source of sufficient quantity. No. This will put millions of people at a disadvantage and their lives will get adversely affected and also the industry.   ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIarestrong","B":"OnlyIIandIIIarestrong","C":"OnlyIandIIIarestrong","D":"Allarestrong","E":"Noneisstrong"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIIandIIIarestrong"},{"question":"Statement:  Should all the indirect taxes in India be combined into a single tax on all commodities? Arguments:   Yes. This will considerably simplify the tax collection mechanism and the cost of collecting tax will also reduce. Yes. The manufacturers and traders will be benefited by this which in turn will boost tax collection. No. No other country has adopted such system.   ","options":{"A":"Noneisstrong","B":"OnlyIandIIIarestrong","C":"OnlyIIisstrong","D":"OnlyIIandIIIarestrong","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Noneofthese"},{"question":"Statement:  Should there be complete ban on Indian professionals seeking jobs elsewhere after getting their education in India? Arguments:   Yes. This is the only way to sustain present rate of technological development in India. No. The Indians settled abroad send huge amount of foreign exchange and this constitutes a significant part of foreign exchange reserve. No. The practical knowledge gained by Indians by working in other countries help India develop its economy.   ","options":{"A":"Noneisstrong","B":"Allarestrong","C":"OnlyIandIIarestrong","D":"OnlyIIIisstrong","E":"OnlyIIandIIIarestrong"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Noneisstrong"},{"question":"Statement:  Should there be a total ban on tobacco products and smoking in India? Arguments:   Yes. It is wrong to smoke away millions of money. No. It will throw thousands of workers in the tobacco industry out of employment. No. The government will lose huge amount of money as it will not earn by way of taxes on these products.   ","options":{"A":"Noneisstrong","B":"OnlyIandIIarestrong","C":"OnlyIIisstrong","D":"OnlyIIandIIIarestrong","E":"Allarestrong"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"OnlyIIandIIIarestrong"},{"question":"Statement:  Should administrative officers be transferred after one or two years? Arguments:   Yes. They get friendly with local people and are manipulated by them. No. By the time their policies and schemes start taking shape, they have to leave. No. This will create a lot of administrative hassles and cause a lot of inconvenience to the officers.   ","options":{"A":"OnlyIIisstrong","B":"OnlyIandIIarestrong","C":"OnlyIIandIIIarestrong","D":"OnlyIandIIIarestrong","E":"Allarestrong"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyIIandIIIarestrong"},{"question":"Statement:  Should the consumption of aerated drinks be banned in India? Arguments:   Yes. This is the only way to reduce the risk of exposing people to some diseases. No. Each individual should have right to choose what he wants. No. There is no confirmed evidence that such products have adverse effects on human body.Yes. It is banned in many other countries also.   ","options":{"A":"OnlyIisstrong","B":"OnlyIandIIarestrong","C":"OnlyIIIisstrong","D":"OnlyIandIVarestrong","E":"Allarestrong"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyIIIisstrong"}],"statement-and-assumption":[{"question":"Statement:  \"You are hereby appointed as a programmer with a probation period of one year and your performance will be reviewed at the end of the period for confirmation.\" - A line in an appointment letter. Assumptions: The performance of an individual generally is not known at the time of appointment offer. Generally an individual tries to prove his worth in the probation period. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  It is desirable to put the child in school at the age of 5 or so. Assumptions: At that age the child reaches appropriate level of development and is ready to learn. The schools do not admit children after six years of age. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"In order to bring punctuality in our office, we must provide conveyance allowance to our employees.\" - In charge of a company tells Personnel Manager. Assumptions: Conveyance allowance will not help in bringing punctuality. Discipline and reward should always go hand in hand. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Unemployment allowance should be given to all unemployed Indian youth above 18 years of age. Assumptions: There are unemployed youth in India who needs monetary support. The government has sufficient funds to provide allowance to all unemployed youth. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"If you trouble me, I will slap you.\" - A mother warns her child. Assumptions: With the warning, the child may stop troubling her. All children are basically naughty. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The State government has decided to appoint four thousand primary school teachers during the next financial year. Assumptions: There are enough schools in the state to accommodate four thousand additional primary school teachers. The eligible candidates may not be interested to apply as the government may not finally appoint such a large number of primary school teachers. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  A warning in a train compartment - \"To stop train, pull chain. Penalty for improper use Rs. 500.\" Assumptions: Some people misuse the alarm chain. On certain occasions, people may want to stop a running train. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  If it is easy to become an engineer, I don't want to be an engineer. Assumptions: An individual aspires to be professional. One desires to achieve a thing which is hard earned. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The concession in rail fares for the journey to hill stations has been cancelled because it is not needed for people who can spend their holidays there. Assumptions: Railways should give concession only to needy persons. Railways should not encourage people to spend their holidays at hill stations. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"The bridge was built at the cost of Rs. 128 crores and even civil bus service is not utilizing it, what a pity to see it grossly underutilized.\" - A citizen's view on a new flyover linking east and west sides of a suburb. Assumptions: The building of such bridges does not serve any public objective. There has to be some accountability and utility of money spent on public projects. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The Government has decided to levy 2 percent on the tax amount payable for funding drought relief programmes. Assumptions: The Government does not have sufficient money to fund drought relief programmes. The amount collected by way of surcharge may be adequate to fund these drought relief programmes. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Detergents should be used to clean clothes. Assumptions: Detergents form more lather. Detergents help to dislodge grease and dirt. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  It will be a substantial achievement in the field of education if one provides one school for every village in our country and enforce attendance. Assumptions: Children in villages do not attend school regularly. Providing school to every village is desirable. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The government has decided to disinvest large chunk of its equity in select public sector undertakings for a better fiscal management. Assumptions: The amount generated out of the disinvestment process may reduce substantially the mounting fiscal deficits. There will be enough demand in the market for the shares of these undertakings. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Never before such a lucid book was available on the topic. Assumptions: Some other books were available on this topic. You can write lucid books on very few topics. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Please do not use lift while going down - an instruction on the top floor of a five-storey building. Assumptions: While going down, the lift is unable to carry any load. Provision of lift is a matter of facility and not of right. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"I have not received telephone bills for nine months inspite of several complaints\" - A telephone customer's letter to the editor of a daily Assumptions: Every customer has a right to get bills regularly from the telephone company. The customer's complaints point to defect in the services which are expected to be corrected. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"This drink can be had either as it is, or after adding ice to it.\" - An advertisement. Assumptions: People differ in their preferences. Some people will get attracted to the drink as it can be had as it is. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Government has permitted unaided colleges to increase their fees. Assumptions: Unaided colleges are in financial difficulties. Aided colleges do not need to increase fees. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Be humble even after being victorious. Assumptions: Many people are humble after being victorious. Generally people are not humble. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The government has decided to pay compensation to the tune of Rs. 1 lakh to the family members of those who are killed in railway accidents. Assumptions: The government has enough funds to meet the expenses due to compensation. There may be reduction in incidents of railway accidents in near future. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Films have become indispensable for the entertainment of people. Assumptions: Films are the only media of entertainment. People enjoy films. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Of all the newspapers published in Mumbai, readership of the \"Times\" is the largest in the Metropolis. Assumptions: 'Times' is not popular in mofussil areas. 'Times' has the popular feature of cartoons on burning social and political issues. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Apart from the entertainment value of television, its educational value cannot be ignored. Assumptions: People take television to be a means of entertainment only. The educational value of television is not realised properly. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Children are influenced more by their teachers nowadays. Assumptions: The children consider teachers as their models. A large amount of children's time is spent in school. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  You know that your suit is excellent when people ask about your tailor who tailored the suit. Assumptions: People do not ask about your tailor if your suit is not good. The people want to know the criterion of an excellent suit. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  His recent investment in the shares of Company A is only a gamble. Assumptions: He may incur loss on his investment. He may gain from his investment. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"EitherIorIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Why don't you go to the court if the employer does not pay you the Provident Fund contribution? Assumptions: Courts can intervene in matters of dispute between employer and employees. It is obligatory for the employer to pay the Provident Fund contribution to the employees. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  'Double your money in five months.' - An advertisement. Assumptions: The assurance is not genuine. People want their money to grow. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The education of a student at collegiate level, not taking into account maintenance expenses, costs four hundred rupees a year. Collegiate education is thus drawing heavily upon the national resources of an impoverished community. So college education should be restricted to a brilliant few. Assumptions: Our resources are very limited. Only a few students should be admitted to the colleges. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  A's advice to B - \"Go to Jammu via Amritsar - the shortest route\". Assumptions: B wishes to go to Jammu. A gives advice to everybody. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  All existing inequalities can be reduced, if not utterly eradicated, by action of governments or by revolutionary change of government. Assumptions: Inequality is a man-made phenomenon. No person would voluntarily part with what he possesses. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The campaign of 'Keep your city clean' started by the Civil Council did not evoke any response from the citizens. Assumptions: People do not desire to keep their city clean. The Civil Council has failed in its campaign. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The district administration has issued a circular to all the farmers under its jurisdiction advising them for not using pesticides indiscriminately as it may pollute the ground water. Assumptions: People may stop using ground water if the farmers continue to use pesticides indiscriminately. Farmers may refrain from using pesticides indiscriminately. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The coffee powder of company X is quite better in taste than the much advertised coffee of company Y. Assumptions: If your product is not good, your spend more on advertisement. Some people are tempted to buy a product by the advertisement. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Of all the radio sets manufactured in India, the 'X' brand has the largest sale. Assumptions: The sale of all the radio sets manufactured in India is known. The manufacturing of no other radio set in India is as large as 'X' brand radio. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"You should not grant him leave in this week due to exigency of work.\" - A supervisor advises the administrative officer. Assumptions: Request for leave can be turned down also. The supervisor has reviewed the work required to be done during the said period. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Like a mad man, I decided to follow him. Assumptions: I am not a mad man. I am a mad man. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"EitherIorIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The first step in treating addicts is to re-establish their lost ties, for which a continuous personal attention should be paid to the addicts under treatment. Assumptions: Addicts under treatment respond better when shown personal interest. Addiction and strained relationships are intimately connected. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Beware of dogs, our dogs do not bark, but they are trained to distinguish between genuine guests and intruders. Assumptions: Barking dogs bite rarely. Our dogs could be dangerous for intruders. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Because of the large number of potholes in road X, reaching airport in time has become difficult. Assumptions: Reaching airport in time may not be always necessary. There is no other convenient road to the airport. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Safety and health practices in many Indian companies are well below the international standards. Assumptions: International standards of health and safety are ideal and unrealistic. Indian organizations do not consider safety and health management as their prime social responsibility. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Greater public participation results in good civic governance. - Statement of Municipal Commissioner of City A. Assumptions: The municipal office is not competent to effect good civic administration. Good civic governance is a matter of collective will and effort of the people and administration. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The regulatory authority has set up a review committee to find out the reasons for unstable stock prices. Assumptions: The investors may regain confidence in stock market by this decision. The review committee has the expertise to find out the causes for volatility in the stock market. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Please note that the company will provide accommodation to only outside candidates if selected.' - A condition in an advertisement. Assumptions: The local candidates would be having some other arrangement for their stay. The company plans to select only local candidates. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Cases of food poisoning due to consumption of liquor are increasing in rural areas. Assumptions: Percentage of people consuming liquor is more in rural areas. There are many unauthorized spurious liquor shops in the rural areas. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Lack of stimulation in the first four or five years of life can have adverse consequences. Assumptions: A great part of the development of observed intelligence occurs in the earliest years of life 50 percent of the measurable intelligence at age of 17 is already predictable by the age of four. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The X-Airlines has decided to increase the passenger fare by 15 percent with immediate effect. Assumptions: The demand for seats of X-Airlines may remain unchanged even after the hike of fare. Other airline companies may also hike the passenger fares. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Shalini made an application to the bank for a loan of Rs. 1,80,000 by mortgaging her house to the bank and promised to repay it within five years. Assumptions: The bank has a practice of granting loans for Rs. 1,00,000 and above. The bank accepts house as collateral security against such loans. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Many historians have done more harm than good by distorting truth. Assumptions: People believe what is reported by the historians. Historians are seldom expected to depict the truth. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"As there is a great demand, every person seeking tickets of the programme will be given only five tickets.\" Assumptions: The organizers are not keen on selling the tickets. No one is interested in getting more than five tickets. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"Computer education should start at schools itself.\" Assumptions: Learning computers is easy. Computer education fetches jobs easily. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  If he is intelligent, he will pass the examination. Assumptions: To pass, he must be intelligent. He will pass the examination. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Today I must satisfy myself only by looking at a pink headed duck in an encyclopaedia. Assumptions: Pink headed ducks are as good as extinct now. People refer to encyclopaedia to know only about things which do not exist now. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The organization should promote employees on the basis of merit alone and not on the basis of length of service or seniority. Assumptions: Length of service or seniority does not alone reflect merit of an employee. It is possible to determine and measure merit of an employee. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"But out of A, B, C and D products, you buy B which alone is based on the international technology.\"-  A shopkeeper tells a customer. Assumptions: The customers normally accept the recommendation of the shopkeeper. Use of international technology is supposed to ensure better quality standards. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"If you want to give any advertisement, give it in the newspaper X.\" - A tells B. Assumptions: B wants to publicise his products. Newspaper X has a wide circulation. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Kartik left for Delhi on Tuesday by train to attend a function to be held on Friday at his uncle's house in Delhi. Assumptions: Kartik may reach Delhi on Wednesday. Kartik may reach Delhi before Friday. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"Avon Cycles - Fast, easy to ride, impressive, reliable, crafted and up-to-date automation.\" - An advertisement. Assumptions: There is no other cycle with any of these features. People do not bother about the cost. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"Private property, trespassers will be prosecuted\" - A notice on a plot of land. Assumptions: The passerby may read the notice and may not trespass. The people are scared of prosecution. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Without reforming the entire administrative system, we cannot eradicate corruption and prejudice from the society. Assumptions: The existence of corruption and prejudice is good. There is enough flexibility to change the administrative system. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The civic authority has advised the residents in the area to use mosquito repellents or sleep inside nets as large number of people are suffering from malaria. Assumptions: Local residents have enough money to arrange for the repellents or nets. People may ignore and continue to get mosquito bites as they have other pressing needs. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Vitamin E tablets improve circulation, keep your complexion in a glowing condition. Assumptions: People like a glowing complexion. Complexion becomes dull in the absence of circulation. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"Ensure a good Slight's sleeps for your family with safe and effective X mosquito coil.\" - An advertisement. Assumptions: X mosquito coil is better than any other mosquito coil. A good night's sleep is desirable. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"Please do not wait for me, I may be late, start taking lunch as soon as the guests arrive. - A message from a Director of a Company to his office managers. Assumptions: Keeping guests waiting is not desirable. Lunch may not be ready in time. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  If you have any problems, bring them to me. Assumptions: You have some problems. I can solve any problem. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  A sentence in the letter to the candidates called for written examination - 'You have to bear your expenses on travel etc'. Assumptions: If not clarified all the candidates may claim reimbursement of expenses. Many organizations reimburse expenses on travel to candidates called for written examination. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The State Government has abolished the scheme of providing concessional air ticket to students. Assumptions: Students will not travel by air in future. The students who resort to travel by air can bear the expenses of air ticket. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"To buy a X - T.V, contact Y - the sole agent of X-T.V.\" - An advertisement. Assumptions: People generally prefer to buy T.V. through sole agent. The T.V. producing companies do not sell their products directly. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Why don't you invite Anthony for the Christmas party this year? Assumptions: Anthony is not from the same city. Unless invited Anthony will not attend the party. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Sachin wrote to his brother at Bangalore to collect personally the application form from the University for the Post-graduation Course in Mathematics. Assumptions: The University may issue application forms to a person other than the prospective student. Sachin's brother may receive the letter well before the last date of collecting application forms. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"Apply nets on windows to prevent the entrance of mosquitoes in the house.\" Assumptions: The entering of mosquitoes from entrances other than windows is desirable. Nets are not available to apply on doors. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Among all the articles, the prices of personal computers show the highest decline from June 2005 to December 2005. Assumptions: Comparative prices of all the articles in June and December 2005 were available. Prices of personal computers were higher in the first six months than the last six months of 2005. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Most people who stop smoking gain weight. Assumptions: If one stops smoking, one will gain weight. If one does not stop smoking, one will not gain weight. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Please consult us before making any decision on investment. Assumptions: You may take a wrong decision if you don't consult us. It is important to take a right decision. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The Parent Teacher Association (PTA) of a school has informed the Principal that they will not send their children to the school unless the school - authority reduces the fees with immediate effect. Assumptions: Majority of the parents may agree with the PTA and may not send their wards with the school The school authority may accede to the demand of the PTA and reduce the fees. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"Those who are appearing for this examination for the first time should be helped in filling up the form.\" - An instruction to invigilating staff. Assumptions: The form is somewhat complicated. Candidates can appear more than once for this examination. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Success is how much a person bounces up after hitting the bottom. Assumptions: Success requires conscious efforts without being discouraged by failure. Failure cannot be considered an acceptable thing. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The company has the right to reject any application form without furnishing any reason while sorting the list of candidates for interview - A condition mentioned in the employment notice. Assumptions: It is desirable to call only eligible candidates for interview. The company believes in following impartial practice in all its functions. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The government has set up a fact finding mission to look into the possible reasons for the recent violence in the area. Assumptions: The mission may be able to come up with credible information about the incidents. The people in the area may cooperate with the mission and come forward to give detailed information related to the incidents. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  I cannot contact you on phone from Karshik. Assumptions: Telephone facility is not available at Karshik. Nowadays it is difficult to contact on phone. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  I have written several letters to the branch manager regarding my account in the bank but did not receive any reply so far. Assumptions: Branch manager is expected to read letters received from the customer. Branch manager is expected to reply to the letters received from the customers. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"Use our product to improve memory of our child. It is based on natural herbs and has no harmful side effects.\" -  An advertisement of a pharmaceutical company. Assumptions: People generally opt for a medical product which is useful and has no harmful side effects. Improving memory of child is considered as important by many parents. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"If I am not well you will have to go for the meeting.\" - A manager tells his subordinate. Assumptions: It is not necessary that only manager level personnel attend the meeting. If the manager is well, he would himself like to go for the meeting. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The Principal instructed all the teachers to be careful in class because some students may disturb other students. Assumptions: The teachers will handle the situation properly and they will point out the naughty students.  The students will welcome the decision of the Principal. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The present examination system needs overhauling thoroughly. Assumptions: The present examination system is obsolete. Overhauling results in improvement. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Read this book to get detailed and most comprehensive information on this issue. Assumptions: The person who wants this information can read. There are other books available on this issue. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Traffic jams on most of the roads in the city have become a regular feature during monsoon. Assumptions: Material used for road construction cannot withstand the fury of monsoon resulting into innumerable pot holes on the roads. Number of vehicles coming on the roads is much more in monsoon as compared to other seasons. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  'Guests should be provided lunch.' - A tells B. Assumptions: Unless told, lunch may not be provided. Guests will stay during lunch time. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The city bus transport corporation has decided to change routes of three buses plying between paints A and B in the city to make them economically viable. Assumptions: These buses may get more passengers on the revised routes. Many people residing on the old routes may not avail bus services. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The patient's condition would improve after operation. Assumptions: The patient can be operated upon in this condition. The patient cannot be operated upon in this condition. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Provide mid-day meals to the children in primary schools to increase the number of students attending schools. Assumptions: Mid-day meals will attract the children to the schools. Those children who are otherwise deprived of good food will attend the schools. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  This year most of the shops and departmental stores are offering prizes and discounts on purchases to attract customers. Assumptions: The shops and departmental stores have so far earned a lot of profit, so now they have started sharing it with the customers. Lots of goods are available but the sale is not shooting up. There is no cheer for the customers. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  In case of any difficulty about this case, you may contact our company's lawyer. Assumptions: Each company has a lawyer of its own. The company's lawyer is thoroughly briefed about this case. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Imprisonment for 27 years made Nelson Mandela, the President. Assumptions: Only who will be imprisoned for 27 years will become the President. To become the President, imprisonment is a qualification. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Nobody can predict as to how long our country would take to contain the unfortunate and disastrous terrorist activities. Assumptions: It is impossible to put on end to terrorist activities Efforts to control the terrorist activities are on. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The management of XYZ Pvt. Ltd. asked the workers' union to call off strike immediately otherwise the management would be forced to close down the factory. Assumptions: No alternative other than closing down the factory is left for the management of XYZ Pvt. Ltd Such threat may have some effect on the workers' union. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The end of a financial year is the ideal time to take a look at the performance of various companies. Assumptions: All the companies take such a review at the end of a financial year. The performance data of various companies is available. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The party president has directed that no member of the party will give press briefing or interviews to governments and private T.V. channels about the discussion in scheduled meeting of the party. Assumptions: Party members will observe this directive of the president. The general public will not come to know about the happenings in the scheduled meeting of the party. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"To keep myself up-to-date, I always listen to 9.00 p.m. news on radio.\"- A candidate tells the interview board. Assumptions: The candidate does not read newspaper. Recent news is broadcast only on radio. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The entire north India, including Delhi and the neighbouring states remained 'powerless' the whole day of 19th December as the northern grid supplying electricity to the seven states collapsed yet again. Assumptions: The northern grid had collapsed earlier. The grid system of providing electricity to a group of states is an ineffective type of power supply system. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Believe me, I have read it in newspaper X. Assumptions: Newspaper X gives reliable information/news. I am reporting exactly as it is given in newspaper X. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Many people have expressed surprise as the princess has broken the royal tradition of marriage by choosing a commoner as her life partner. Assumptions: People expect royal families to observe customs and traditions. People still value 'purity of royal blood' and 'status' when it comes to a marriage of members of royal family. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Highly brilliant and industrious students do not always excel in the written examination. Assumptions: The written examination is good mainly for mediocre students. The brilliant and industrious students cannot always write good answers in the exam ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  All the employees are notified that the organisation will provide transport facilities at half cost from the nearby railway station to the office except those who have been provided with travelling allowance. Assumptions: Most of the employees will travel by the office transport. Those who are provided with travelling allowance will not read such notice. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The government has decided to hold the employers responsible for deducting tax at source for all its employees. Assumptions: The employers may still not arrange to deduct tax at source for its employees. The employees may not allow the employers to deduct tax at source. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Whenever you have any doubt on this subject, you may refer to the book by Enn and Enn. Assumptions: The book by Enn and Enn is available. There is no other book on this subject. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  I can take you quickly from Kanpur to Lucknow by my cab but then you must pay me double the normal charges, Assumptions: Normally, it will take more time to reach Lucknow from Kanpur. People want to reach quickly but they will not pay extra money for it. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"I would like to study the impact of pay revision on job satisfaction of employees.\" - A tells B. Assumptions: Job satisfaction can be measured. A has necessary competence to undertake such study. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"In the recently imposed war, global public opinion was dishonoured by the economically strong and scientifically advanced superpower.\" Assumptions: Superpowers need not take any heed of global public opinion. Global public opinion must have been against the imposition of war. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  How is it that the village is not shown in this so-called official map of this district? Assumptions: The official district map is expected to show all the villages of that district. This is not an authentic and official map. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The cost of living has gone up in India. Assumptions: The price of essential commodities has gone up in recent times. Many luxury goods are available in plenty in the country. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  No budgetary provision for the purpose of appointing additional faculty would be made in the context of institute's changed financial priorities. Assumptions: Appointment of faculty requires funds. There are areas other than appointment of faculty which require more financial attention. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The economic condition of the country has gone from bad to worse. Assumptions: The government has failed to tackle economic problems. People are not cooperating with the government. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Science is a sort of news agency comparable in principle to other new agencies. But this news agency gives us information which is reliable to an extraordinary high degree due to elaborate techniques of verification and its capacity to survive centuries. So, science should be read with as much interest as we read news. Assumptions: Science encourages investigative spirit. People read news out of interest. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Deepak has a large collection of books and he keeps on purchasing new books to add to his collection. Assumptions: Deepak loves and cares for books. Deepak has read each and every book that he has purchased. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  An advertisement in a newspaper - \"Wanted unmarried, presentable, matriculate girls between 18 and 21, able to speak fluently in English to be taken as models.\" Assumptions: Fluency in English is a pre-requisite for good performance as a model. Height does not matter in performing as a model. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  There has been a remarkable increase in the air traffic in India during the past few years. Assumptions: Travelling by air has become a status symbol now. Large numbers of peoples are able to afford air travel now. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"Blue tie would help us identify our staff from others.\" - A suggestion in a company. Assumptions: The company needs to identify its staff. Blue tie is the latest fashion. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  A's advice to B - \"If you want to study Accounts, join Institute Y.\" Assumptions: Institute Y provides good Accounts education. B listens to As advice. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"You must learn to refer to dictionary if you want to become a good writer.\" - A advises B. Assumptions: Only writers refer to the dictionary. All writers, good or bad, refer to the dictionary. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  It is through participative management policy alone that indiscipline in our industries can be contained and a quality of life ensured to the worker. Assumptions: Quality of life in our industries is better. Indiscipline results in poor quality of life. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  A line in an advertisement in a newspaper - \"You really get your money's worth when you buy from our shop.\" Assumptions: Other shops price goods above their worth. People want full value for their money. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The next meeting of the Governing Board of the Institute will be held after one year. Assumptions: The Institute will remain in function after one year. The Governing Board will be dissolved after one year. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Municipal Corporation has decided to ban the entry of vehicles from sub-urban areas to the main city through main routes during peak hours to avoid traffic congestion. Assumptions: The people of sub-urban areas should not bring their vehicles during peak hours. There is no traffic congestion by the vehicles of people residing in the main city. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  A good book, even if costly, is sold. Assumptions: Some books are better than others. Most of the books are costly. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  World Health Organisation has decided to double its assistance to various health programmes in India as per-capita expenditure on health in India is very low compared to many other countries. Assumptions: The enhanced assistance may substantially increase the per-capita expenditure on health in India and bring it on par with other countries. The Government funding is less than adequate to provide medical facilities in India. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The President assured the people that elections will be held here after every five years, Assumptions: People are afraid that the elections may not be held at all. People are afraid that the elections may not be held after five years. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"EitherIorIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Interview conducted for selecting people for jobs should measure personality characteristics of candidates. Assumptions: Performance on job depends on personality characteristics. Personality characteristics can be measured in interview. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  A Notice Board at a ticket window: Please come in queue.' Assumptions: Unless instructed people will not form queue.  People any way want to purchase tickets. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Children, who get encouragement, usually perform better. - A note by the Principal to the parents. Assumptions: Some parents do not encourage children. Parents may follow Principal's advice. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"According to me, you should get your child examined by a specialist doctor.\" - A tells B. Assumptions: Specialist doctors are able to diagnose better than ordinary doctors. B will certainly not agree with A's advice. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The government is making efforts to boost tourism in State X. Assumptions: Tourism in State X dropped following political unrest. Special discounts in the air fare have been announced. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"Best way to solve this problem of workers' dissatisfaction is to offer them cash rewards. If this type of incentive can solve the problem in CIDCO Company then why not here.\" - A Personnel Manager tells the Chairman of a company. Assumptions: The reason for workers' dissatisfaction in both the companies was similar. Monetary incentives have universal appeal. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Do not copy our software without our permission - A notice. Assumptions: It is possible to copy the software. Such warning will have some effect. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Retired persons should not be appointed for executive posts in other organisations. Assumptions: Retired persons may lack the zeal and commitment to carry out executive's work. Retired persons do not take interest in the work and welfare of the new organisation. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"In my absence, I request you to look after the affairs of our company.\" - B tells C. Assumptions: C may not accept the request of B. C has the expertise to handle the affairs of the company. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  An announcement: Passengers in their own interest are advised to fasten their seat belts while seated in the trolley of the ropeway. Assumptions: People are always careful about their own safety. Unless advised, passengers might not use the seat belts. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"Banking services are fine tuned to meet growing business needs,\" - An advertisement. Assumptions: Banking is a part of business activity Industrialists prefer better banking services. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The 'M' Cooperative Housing Society has put up a notice at its gate those sales persons are not allowed inside the society. Assumptions: All the sales persons will stay away from the 'M' Cooperative Housing Society. The security guard posted at the gate may be able to stop the sales persons entering the society. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  What a fool I am to rely on trickster like Shaleen ! Assumptions: Shaleen is unreliable. I am a fool. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The multinational fast food chains are opening up a large number of Plus Coffee Shops with piped modern music in different cities of India and these are serving various breakfast (snax) with coffee. Assumptions: A large number of persons may become regular customers of these coffee shops. The people will like to enjoy the comfortable environment while drinking coffee with snax. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Market trends are changing continuously and with increasing competitiveness, the consumer's demands with respect to the prices and quality are gradually increasing. Assumptions: The consumers did not care for the prices and quality earlier. Market competitiveness is not favourable for the consumers. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The school authorities have decided to increase the number of students in each classroom to seventy from the next academic session to bridge the gap between the income and the expenditure to a large extent. Assumptions: The income generated by way of fees of the additional students will be sufficient enough to bridge the gap. The school will get all the additional students in each class from the next academic session. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The General Administration Department has issued a circular to all the employees informing them that henceforth the employees can avail their lunch break at any of the half-hour slots between 1.00 p.m. and 2.30 p.m. Assumptions: The employees may welcome the decision and avail lunch break at different time's slots. There may not be any break in the work of the organization as the employees will have their lunch break at different time slots. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Lock your valuables in a cupboard and call everybody gentleman. Assumptions: Valuables locked in cupboard cannot be stolen. Stealing is a crime. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"The function will start at 3 P.M. You are requested to take your seats before 3 P.M.\" - Last sentence in an invitation card. Assumptions: If the invitee is not in his seat before 3 P.M., the function will not start. Function will start as scheduled. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The two countries have signed a fragile pact, but the vital sovereignty issue remains unresolved. Assumptions: The two countries cannot have permanent peace pact. The two countries may become hostile again after a short spell of time. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Government aided schools should have uniformity in charging various fees. Assumptions: The Government's subsidy comes from the money collected by way of taxes from people. The Government while giving subsidy may have stipulated certain uniform conditions regarding fees. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Sachin's mother instructed him to return home by train if it rains heavily. Assumptions: Sachin may not be able to decide himself if it rains heavily. The trains may ply even if it rains heavily. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"Please put more people on the job to make up for the delay.\" Assumptions: Delay is inevitable in most jobs. Output will increase with more number of people on the job. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  In spite of less than normal rainfall in the catchment areas during the first two months of monsoon of the lakes supplying water to the city the authority has not yet affected any cut in the water supply to the city. Assumptions: The rainfall during the remaining part of the monsoon may be adequate for normal water supply. The present water level of the lakes supplying water to the city may be adequate for normal supply. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  If you are an engineer, we have a challenging job for you. Assumptions: We need an engineer. You are an engineer. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  In spite of poor services, the commutators have not complained against it. Assumptions: Generally people do not tolerate poor services. Complaints sometimes improve services. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  In Bombay, railway trains are indispensable for people in the suburbs to reach their places of work on time. Assumptions: Railway trains are the only mode of transport available in the suburbs of Bombay. Only railway trains run punctually. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The government has decided to reduce its subsidy on LPG; however the subsidy on kerosene remains unchanged. Assumptions: Those people who buy LPG can afford to purchase LPG for a higher price. Many people may stop buying LPG and instead use kerosene. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  It is not true that the mightiest superpower always wins wars and gets accolades from other countries. Assumptions: Winners are sometimes admired and appreciated. Winners are occasionally criticized. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  To investigate the murder of the lone resident of a flat, the police interrogated the domestic servant, the watchman of the multi-storeyed buildings and the liftman. Assumptions: The domestic servant, watchman and the liftman can give a clue about the suspected murder. Generally in such cases the persons known to the resident are directly or indirectly involved in the murder. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The integrated steel plants in India would no longer have to depend on imports for continuous casting refractories. Assumptions: Continuous casting refractories are needed by India. Continuous casting refractories are in demand. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The office building needs repairing just as urgently as it needs internal as well as external painting. Assumptions: Efficiency of people working in the office cannot be improved unless office building is repaired. Repairing and painting of office building require funds. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The private bus service in the city has virtually collapsed because of the ongoing strike of its employees. Assumptions: Going on strikes has become the right of every employee. People no more require the services of private bus operators. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Neither fascism nor communism has any chance of succeeding in America. Assumptions: American people are strongly in favour of preserving the rights of the individual. Americans have so far not suffered any pangs of poverty or deprivation. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Amongst newspapers, I always read the National Times. Assumptions: The National Times gives very comprehensive news. Some people prefer other newspapers. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"Get rid of your past for future, get our new generation fridge at a discount in exchange of old\"- An advertisement. Assumptions: The sales of the new fridge may increase in the coming months. People prefer to exchange future with past. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The higher echelons of any organization are expected to be models of observational learning and should not be considered as merely sources of reward and punishments. Assumptions: Employees are likely to be sensitive enough to learn by observing the behaviour of their bosses. Normally bosses are considered as sources of reward and punishment. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The new education policy envisages major modifications in the education system. Assumptions: Present education system is inconsistent with national needs. Present education system needs change. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"Fly X airways whenever you decide to go places. Our fares are less than train fares.\"- An advertisement. Assumptions: People prefer to travel by air when the fares are reasonable. The fares of other airlines are costlier than those of X airways. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"The programme will start at 6 p.m. but you can come there up to 7 p.m. or so and still there is no problem.\" Assumptions: The programme will continue even after 7 p.m. The programme may not even start by that time. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  An advertisement: If you want to follow the footprints of an ideal leader, wear 'X' brand of shoes. Assumptions: Most people like to become ideal leaders. One can't become ideal leader unless one wears X brand of shoes. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The improvement in the quality of T.V. programmes will lead to increase in the sales of T.V. Assumptions: T.V. is a good entertainment medium. The quality of T.V, programmes has improved recently. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  With a sense of sincerity, quality teachers can improve the society. Assumptions: Quality teachers are sincere. Sincerity in teaching pays. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The head of the organization congratulated the entire staff in his speech for their sincere effort to bring down the deficit and urged them to give their best for attaining a more profitable position in future. Assumptions: The employees may get motivated and maintain and if possible enhance their present level of work. The employees may now relax and slow down in their day to day work as there is no immediate threat of huge deficit. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Money is the root cause of all the problems in a family. Assumptions: Every problem is caused by something. There are always some problems in a family. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  An advertisement: \"Our shoes are for the rich.\" Assumptions: Many people like to be labelled as rich. One can't become rich unless one has that brand of shoes. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  In view of the violent situation due to students' agitation the state government has decided to close down all the educational institutions in the state for two weeks with immediate effect. Assumptions: The students' agitation may subside after two weeks. The students may not find a place to come further and continue agitation after the closure of the educational institutions. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The taste of food contributes to the intake of nourishment which is essential for the survival of human beings. Assumptions: Human beings take food for the enjoyment of its taste. Human beings experience the taste of food. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The economic prosperity of any nation is dependent on the quality of its human resources. Assumptions: It is possible to measure the quality of human resources of a nation. Achieving economic prosperity is a cherished goal of every nation. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"Two months ago, it was announced that Central Government pensioners would get dearness relief with immediate effect but till date, banks have not credited the arrears.\" - A statement from a Pensioners' Forum. Assumptions: Most of the banks normally take care of the pensioners. Two months time is sufficient for the government machinery to move and give effect to pensioners. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"If it does not rain throughout this month, most farmers would be in trouble this year.\" Assumptions: Timely rain is essential for farming. Most farmers are generally dependent on rains. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Equality of income throughout a community is the essential condition for maximising the total utility which the total income available could confer on the members of that community. Assumptions: If extra income were taken from the rich and given to the poor, the total utility experienced by the community would increase. Equal pay for equal work. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"Present day education is in shambles and the country is going to the dogs.\" Assumptions: A good education system is essential for the well-being of a nation. A good education alone is sufficient for the well-being of a nation. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  If the city bus which runs between Ram Nagar and Sant Colony is extended to Vasant Vihar, it will be convenient. - Appeal of residents of Ram Nagar to the city bus company. Assumptions: The convenience of the city bus company is much more important than the needs of the consumers. The city bus company is indifferent to the aspirations of the residents of Sant Colony. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  If Rajan has finished reading the instructions, then let him begin the activities accordingly. Assumptions: Rajan would understand the instructions. Rajan is capable of performing the activities. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The civic authority appealed to the people for reduction in usage of water as there may be an acute shortage during the coming weeks. Assumptions: There will be no rain in recent future. The people are ready to follow the advice of the civic authority. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"Everyone desires to buy a personal computer\", statement of a college student. Assumptions: Personal computers are not a need but a luxury. Use of personal computers improves quality of skill. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"It has become a necessity to computerize all the functions of our Institute to maintain the present position.\" - A statement of the Director of XYZ Institute. Assumptions: Unless computerized, the Institute will fall behind the race. The functions of the Institute are too complex to be handled manually. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The product X that you have asked for is not with us but can be made available against firm order from you. Assumptions: The product X is not in great demand. The product X is out of stock as new model is coming up. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"X air-conditioner - the largest selling name with the largest range.\" - An advertisement. Assumptions: X air-conditioner is the only one with wide variations. There is a demand of air-conditioners in the market. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Ministry has announced an economic package to support the voluntary organisations. - An official notice, Assumptions: Voluntary organisations do not need such support. Government was not supporting the voluntary organisations earlier. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"Though the candidates have been instructed to bring pencils, yet provide some pencils with each invigilator.\" - An instruction to test administration staff. Assumptions: Pencils are in short supply. All the candidates will bring the pencil. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"If you want timely completion of work, provide independent cabins,\" - An employee tells the Director of a Company. Assumptions: There are not enough cabins. Others' presence hinders timely completion of work. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  No regular funds have been provided for welfare activities in this year's budget of the factory. Assumptions: The factory does not desire to carry out welfare this year. Budgetary provision is necessary for carrying put welfare activities. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The host in one of the popular T.V. programmes announced that the channel will contact the viewers between 9.00 a.m. to 6.00 p.m. on weekdays and the lucky ones will be given fabulous prizes. Assumptions: The people may remain indoors to receive the phone call. More people may start watching the programme. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The electric supply corporation has decided to open a few more collection centres in the business district area. Assumptions: The people in the area may welcome the decision. Henceforth there may be less time required by the customers for paying electricity bill. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"A visit of school children to forest to widen their knowledge of natural resources has been arranged.\" - A notice in the school. Assumptions: Forests are full of natural resources. Children are likely to learn from their interaction with the new environment. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  There is no reason to rule out the possibility of life on Mars. Therefore the exploration of that planet has to be undertaken. Assumptions: There is life on Mars. The search for life is the sufficient reason for space exploration. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Use PVC pipes which have 10 years longer life to any other. Assumptions: People prefer only those pipes which are durable. Other pipes are not durable. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The Union Government has decided to withdraw existing tax relief on various small savings schemes in a phased manner to augment its tax collection. Assumptions: People may still continue to keep money in small savings schemes and also pay taxes. The total tax collection may increase substantially. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Read this notice before entering the club. Assumptions: People are literate. No blind person comes to the club. ","options":{"A":"OnlyassumptionIisimplicit","B":"OnlyassumptionIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","D":"NeitherInorIIisimplicit","E":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"Wanted a two bedroom flat in the court area for immediate possession.\" - An advertisement. Assumptions:   Flats are available in court area. Some people will respond to the advertisement. It is a practice to give such an advertisement. ","options":{"A":"Allareimplicit","B":"OnlyIIisimplicit","C":"Noneisimplicit","D":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  This book is so prepared that even a layman can study science in the absence of a teacher. Assumptions:   A layman wishes to study science without a teacher. A teacher may not always be available to teach science. A layman generally finds it difficult to learn science on its own. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","B":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","C":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit","D":"Allareimplicit","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"We do not want you to see our product on newspaper, visit our shop to get a full view.\" - An advertisement. Assumptions:   People generally decide to purchase any product after seeing the name in the advertisement. Uncommon appeal may attract the customers. People may come to see the product. ","options":{"A":"Noneisimplicit","B":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","C":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","D":"Allareimplicit","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  There is big boom in drug business and a number of jhuggi-jhopari dwellers in Delhi can be seen pedalling with small pouches of smack and brown sugar. Assumptions:   Drug addiction is increasing in the country, specially in the capital. All the big dons involved in the smuggling of drugs live in jhuggi-jhopari areas. Most of the jhuggi-jhopari dwellers would do anything for money. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIisimplicit","B":"OnlyIIisimplicit","C":"OnlyIIIisimplicit","D":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit","E":"EitherIorIIIisimplicit"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"X-chocolate is ideal as a gift for someone you love.\" - An advertisement. Assumptions:   People generally give gifts to loved ones. Such advertisements generally influence people. Chocolate can be considered as a gift item. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","B":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","C":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit","D":"Allareimplicit","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Allareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"Fly with us and experience the pleasure of flying.\"- An advertisement by an airlines. Assumptions:   More passengers may be attracted to travel by the airline after reading the advertisement. People generally may prefer an enjoyable flight. Other airlines may not be offering the same facilities. ","options":{"A":"Noneisimplicit","B":"OnlyIisimplicit","C":"OnlyIIisimplicit","D":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Noneofthese"},{"question":"Statement:  Bombay people were spellbound, mesmerized and got mad when they saw the famous pop-singer Michael Jackson's hi-tech pulsating megawatt performance. Assumptions:   When a show is accompanied with latest technology, it has a magical effect. Bombay people were never impressed with performances by Indian musicians. Michael Jackson is a super singer. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIisimplicit","B":"OnlyIIisimplicit","C":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit","D":"EitherIIorIIIisimplicit","E":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The residents of the locality wrote a letter to the Corporation requesting to restore normalcy in the supply of drinking water immediately as the supply at present is just not adequate. Assumptions:   The Corporation may not take any action on the letter. The municipality has enough water to meet the demand. The water supply to the area was adequate in the past. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit","B":"OnlyIIisimplicit","C":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","D":"OnlyIIIisimplicit","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"OnlyIIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"We have the distinction of being the only company in India as well as the second in the world to have won an ISO 9002 certification in our line of business.\" - Statement of Company X's Chairman. Assumptions:   There were not many companies in the line of business of Company X. Getting ISO 9002 in the line of business of Company X is not easy. The Company X desires to expand its business. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIisimplicit","B":"OnlyIIisimplicit","C":"OnlyIIIisimplicit","D":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"I want to present a book on techniques of yoga to Ajay on his birthday.\"- A tells B. Assumptions:   A will be invited by Ajay on his birthday. The person, to whom the book is to be presented, is not keeping good health. Book is an acceptable gift for birthday. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","B":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","C":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit","D":"Noneisimplicit","E":"Allareimplicit"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Let us increase the taxes to cover the deficit. Assumptions:   The present taxes are very low. Deficit in a budget is not desirable. If the taxes are not increased, the deficit cannot be met. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","B":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","C":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit","D":"Allareimplicit","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"We must introduce objective type tests to improve our examinations for admission to MBA.\" - The Chairman of the Admission Committee tells the Committee. Assumptions:   The admission at present is directly through the interview. The Admission Committee is desirous of improving the admission examinations. The Chairman himself is an MBA. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit","B":"OnlyIIisimplicit","C":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","D":"OnlyIisimplicit","E":"Noneisimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Use 'X' brand shoes. These are durable and available in all sizes. - An advertisement in the newspaper A. Assumptions:   Normally people like durable shoes. Very few people read advertisement in a newspaper. Very few people read the newspaper A. ","options":{"A":"Noneisimplicit","B":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","C":"OnlyI,andeitherIIorIIIareimplicit","D":"Allareimplicit","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Noneofthese"},{"question":"Statement:  The State Government has unilaterally increased by five percent octroi on all commodities entering into the state without seeking approval of the Central Government. Assumptions:   The State Government may be able to implement its decision. The Central Government may agree to support the State Government's decision. The State Government may be able to earn considerable amount through the additional octroi. ","options":{"A":"Noneisimplicit","B":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","C":"Allareimplicit","D":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"Allareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  In the recently held All India Commerce Conference the session on 'Management of Service Sector in India' surprisingly attracted large number of participants and also received a very good media coverage in the leading newspapers. Assumptions:   People were not expecting such an encouraging response for service sector. Service sector is not managed properly in India. Media is always very positive towards service sector. ","options":{"A":"Noneisimplicit","B":"OnlyIisimplicit","C":"Allareimplicit","D":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","E":"OnlyeitherIorIIIisimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"If you are intelligent, we are the right people for improving your performance.\" - An advertisement of a coaching institute. Assumptions:   Brilliant students prefer to join coaching classes. Coaching classes help the students to improve their performance. No other institute provides such coaching. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","B":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","C":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit","D":"Allareimplicit","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The Reserve Bank of India has directed the banks to refuse fresh loans to major defaulters. Assumptions:   The banks may still give loans to the defaulters. The defaulters may repay the earlier loan to get fresh loan. The banks may recover the bad loans through such harsh measures. ","options":{"A":"Noneisimplicit","B":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","C":"Allareimplicit","D":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"Allareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  We must be prepared to face any eventuality and all the assignments must be completed as per their schedule - Director tells the Faculty members. Assumptions:   There is possibility of any serious eventuality. Dates are fixed for all the assignments. Faculty members are supposed to complete all the assignments. ","options":{"A":"Noneisimplicit","B":"OnlyIisimplicit","C":"DulyIIandIIIareimplicit","D":"OnlyIIIisimplicit","E":"Allareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Allareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  An advertisement of Bank X - \"Want to open a bank account! Just dial our 'home service' and we will come at your doorsteps.\" Assumptions:   No other bank makes available service at the doorstep of the customer. People may choose Bank X for their financial transactions. Nowadays banking has become very competitive. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","B":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","C":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit","D":"Allareimplicit","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Allareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"Do not lean out of the moving train.\" - A warning in the railway compartment. Assumptions:   Such warnings will have some effect. Leaning out of a moving train is dangerous. It is the duty of railway authorities to take care of passengers' safety. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","B":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","C":"OnlyIIisimplicit","D":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit","E":"Allareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Allareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Tender specification will not be issued to the firms where there is 25% or more default in supplies against earlier purchase orders placed on them' - Condition of a Company X inviting tenders for the purchase of material. Assumptions:   The Company X will be watching the quality of performance of its suppliers. This time the firms should keep the percentage of default as less as possible. The Company X expects quality and professional approach from its suppliers. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIisimplicit","B":"OnlyIIisimplicit","C":"EitherIIorIIIisimplicit","D":"OnlyIIIisimplicit","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Noneofthese"},{"question":"Statement:  Items in big showrooms in main markets are costlier than similar items in small shops. Assumptions:   Items in small shops are never reliable. Persons managing big showrooms are cheats. Maintenance of big showrooms is an expensive affair in itself; hence the prices are a little higher. ","options":{"A":"Noneisimplicit","B":"OnlyIisimplicit","C":"OnlyIIisimplicit","D":"OnlyIIIisimplicit","E":"EitherIIorIIIisimplicit"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"OnlyIIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  India's economic growth has come at a terrible price of increased industrial and vehicular pollution. Assumptions:   Pollution is a part of industrial society. Indian economic growth is based on only industrial growth. A country desires economic growth with manageable side effects. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIisimplicit","B":"OnlyIIisimplicit","C":"OnlyIIIisimplicit","D":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The Government of India has set up one-stop facilitation counters manned by trained staff for attending to various needs of the foreign tourists at all the international airports. Assumptions:   There is adequate trained staff available to man these counters in shifts. The services provided by these counters will help boosting inflow of foreign tourists. Majority of the foreign tourists need variety of services when they reach India. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","B":"OnlyIIIisimplicit","C":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","D":"Allareimplicit","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Allareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"Work hard to be successful in the examinations.\" - A advises B. Assumptions: Assumptions:   B listens to As advice. Passing the examination is desirable. Hard practice leads to success. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","B":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","C":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit","D":"Allareimplicit","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"Join X-tuition classes for sure success. Excellent teaching by excellent teachers is our strength.\" - An advertisement. Assumptions:   Sure success is desirable. Students expect sure success when they join any tuition class. Just having excellent teachers does not ensure success. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","B":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","C":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit","D":"OnlyIIisimplicit","E":"Allareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Wars must be discouraged vehemently even though majority of the victims might have been a nuisance to peace loving people. Assumptions:   Wars kill majority of wicked people. Innocent people are also killed in wars. Vehement opposition to wars may have some desirable impact. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","B":"OnlyIIIisimplicit","C":"OnlyIII,andeitherIorIIareimplicit","D":"Allareimplicit","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Allareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"If you are beautiful, we will catch your beauty. If you are not, we will make you beautiful.\" - An advertisement of a photo studio. Assumptions:   How to look beautiful is a problem of youngsters. A photograph can be beautiful even if a person is not. People like to be considered beautiful. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","B":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","C":"OnlyIIIisimplicit","D":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit","E":"Allareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  In view of the recent spurt in sugar prices in the open market, the government has asked the dealers to release a vast quantity of imported sugar in the open market. Assumptions:   The dealers will follow the government directive. The sugar prices will come down. The price of indigenous sugar will remain unchanged. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","B":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","C":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit","D":"Noneisimplicit","E":"Allareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  During pre-harvest kharif season, the government has decided to release vast quantity of food grains from FCI. Assumptions:   There may be a shortage of food grains in the market during this season. The kharif crop may be able to replenish the stock of FCI. There may be a demand from the farmers to procure kharif crop immediately after harvest. ","options":{"A":"Allareimplicit","B":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","C":"Noneisimplicit","D":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Allareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The simplest and the most cost-effective way to upgrade your home Exchange your old furniture and get 25% to 33% off on the new furniture.' - An advertisement of a furniture company. Assumptions:   Nowadays, there is no demand for furniture products unless some attractive scheme is offered. Some customers always desire to have best quality and do not bother either for cost or for convenience. Some customers want to keep their home up-to-date with reasonable cost and with less hassles. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIisimplicit","B":"OnlyIIisimplicit","C":"OnlyIIIisimplicit","D":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyIIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Everybody loves reading adventure stories. Assumptions:   Adventure stories are the only reading material. Nobody loves reading any other material. All are literate. ","options":{"A":"Noneisimplicit","B":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","C":"Allareimplicit","D":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Noneisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Delink degrees with jobs. Then, boys will think twice before joining colleges. Assumptions:   Boys join college education for getting jobs. A degree is of no use for getting a job. Girls do not try for jobs. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIisimplicit","B":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","C":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","D":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit","E":"Allareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  In spite of the heavy rains the traffic has not been disrupted this year. Assumptions:   The traffic is disrupted in rainy seasons only. Rains do not affect traffic movement. Adequate precautions were taken for traffic management during rainy season. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIisimplicit","B":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","C":"OnlyIIIisimplicit","D":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","E":"Noneisimplicit"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyIIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The company has decided to increase the price of all its products to tackle the precarious financial position. Assumptions:   The company may be able to wipe out the entire losses incurred earlier by this decision. The buyers may continue to buy its products even after the increase. The company has adequate resources to continue production for few more months. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit","B":"OnlyIIisimplicit","C":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","D":"Noneisimplicit","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  In order to reduce the gap between income and expenditure, the company has decided to increase the price of its product from next month. Assumptions:   The rate will remain more or less same after the increase. The expenditure will more or less remain the same in near future. The rival companies will also increase the price of the similar product. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","B":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","C":"OnlyIIIisimplicit","D":"Allareimplicit","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Noneofthese"},{"question":"Statement:  'Several labour and industrial courts in this State have no proper premises. Vacancies of judges and stenos are kept pending.' - A statement of a retired judge of State X. Assumptions:   Adequate number of staff and judges helps in the smooth functioning of the industrial and labour courts. The State is not bothered about the condition of the labour and industrial courts. Physical facilities of an office help in increasing efficiency of its employees. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit","B":"OnlyIIisimplicit","C":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","D":"AllI,IIandIIIareimplicit","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"AllI,IIandIIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"A rare opportunity to be a professional while you are at home.\" - An advertisement for computer literate housewives by a computer company. Assumptions:   Some housewives simultaneously desire to become professional. Computer industry is growing at a fast pace. It is possible to be a professional as well as a housewife. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","B":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","C":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit","D":"OnlyIIisimplicit","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Pramod decided to get the railway reservation in May, for the journey he wants to make in July, to Madras. Assumptions:   The railways issues reservations two months in advance. There are more than one trains to Madras. There will be vacancy in the desired class. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIisimplicit","B":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","C":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit","D":"Allareimplicit","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"To make the company commercially viable, there is an urgent need to prune the staff strength and borrow money from the financial institutions.\" - Opinion of a consultant. Assumptions:   The financial institutions lend money for such proposals. The product of the company has a potential market. The employees of the company are inefficient. ","options":{"A":"Noneisimplicit","B":"Allareimplicit","C":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","D":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","E":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The Central Government has directed the State Governments to reduce government expenditure in view of the serious resource crunch and it may not be able to sanction any additional grant to the states for the next six months. Assumptions:   The State Governments are totally dependent on Central Government for its expenditures. The Central Government has reviewed the expenditure account of the State Government. The State Governments will abide by the directive. ","options":{"A":"Noneisimplicit","B":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","C":"OnlyIIIisimplicit","D":"Allareimplicit","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  These apples are too cheap to be good. Assumptions:   When the apple crop is abundant, the prices go down. The lower the selling price, the inferior is the quality of the commodity. Very cheap apples are also good. ","options":{"A":"Noneisimplicit","B":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit","C":"OnlyIIisimplicit","D":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","E":"Allareimplicit"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"All are cordially invited to attend the entertainment programme. It is free.\" - An announcement in a newspaper. Assumptions:   People generally do not go to entertainment programmes which are free. Some people, though interested in entertainment programmes, cannot afford purchasing the tickets. Generally, a free entertainment programme is of a good quality. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIisimplicit","B":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","C":"OnlyIIisimplicit","D":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","E":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Ravi decided to leave office at 4.00 p.m. to catch a flight to Bangalore departing at 6.00 p.m. Assumptions:   The flight to Bangalore may be delayed. He may be able to reach airport well before 6.00 p.m. He may get adequate time to search for a vehicle to go to the airport. ","options":{"A":"Noneisimplicit","B":"OnlyIIisimplicit","C":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","D":"Allareimplicit","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"Put. a notice on the board that all the employees should come on time to office.\" - An officer tells his assistant. Assumptions:   All the employees come late. Employees read such notice on the board. Employees will follow the instructions. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","B":"OnlyIIIisimplicit","C":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","D":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit","E":"Allareimplicit"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The professor announced in the class that the next periodical examination will be held on 15th of the next month. Assumptions:   All the students may appear in the examination. The college will remain open on 15th of the next month. The students can study till 15th of the next month to pass the examination. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","B":"OnlyIIisimplicit","C":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","D":"OnlyIIIisimplicit","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The situation of this area still continues to be tense and out of control. People are requested to be in their homes only. Assumptions:   There had been some serious incidents. People will not go to the office. Normalcy will be restored shortly. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIisimplicit","B":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","C":"Noneisimplicit","D":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit","E":"Allareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"Television X - the neighbour's envy, the owner's pride\" - A T.V. advertisement. Assumptions:   Catchy slogans appeal to people. People are envious of their neighbours superior possessions. People want to be envied by their neighbours. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","B":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","C":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit","D":"Allareimplicit","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Keeping in view the financial constraints, the management institution has decided to charge at the time of providing employment in various organisations, a placement fee of Rs. 25000 from the organisations in which the student will be provided the employment. Assumptions:   It will help in increasing the demand of the students belonging to the management institution. The amount collected in this way will be purposeful. It may be possible that the organisation providing employment may select less number of students in future. ","options":{"A":"Noneisimplicit","B":"OnlyIisimplicit","C":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","D":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"Z-T.V, the only T.V. which gives the viewers a chance to watch two programmes simultaneously.\" - An advertisement. Assumptions:   Sale of Z-T.V will increase because of the advertisement. Some people may be influenced by the advertisement and buy Z-T.V. The sale of Z-T.V. may be on the downward trend. ","options":{"A":"Noneisimplicit","B":"Allareimplicit","C":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","D":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"As our business is expanding, we need to appoint more staff.\"  Owner of a company informs his staff. Assumptions:   The present staff is not competent. More staff will further expand the business. Suitable persons to be taken as staff will be available. ","options":{"A":"Noneisimplicit","B":"OnlyIisimplicit","C":"OnlyIIisimplicit","D":"OnlyIIIisimplicit","E":"Allareimplicit"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"OnlyIIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The address of the Principal to the students, \"Dear students, if you want a healthy mind, listen to music.\" Assumptions:   Normally students like to follow good advice. It is desirable to develop a healthy mind. It is the duty of the Principal to advise the students. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","B":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","C":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit","D":"Noneisimplicit","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The national air carrier has decided to start a weekly air service from town A to town B. Assumptions:   There will be enough passengers to make the operation economically viable. Other carriers may not start such service. The people staying around these towns can afford the cost of air travel. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIisimplicit","B":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","C":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","D":"Allareimplicit","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Noneofthese"},{"question":"Statement:  'Move into the upper echelons without paying a steep price - Book a luxurious flat with us'. An advertisement of a construction company for its prestigious project. Assumptions:   It is possible to join the select band of rich people by hard work. Staying in luxury without paying steep price is the criterion of upper crust of the society. Booking a luxurious flat is very easy now. ","options":{"A":"Noneisimplicit","B":"OnlyIIisimplicit","C":"OnlyIIIisimplicit","D":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyIIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The school authority decided to open a summer school this year in the school compound for the students in the age range of 7 - 14 years. Assumptions:   All the students will attend the summer school. All the parents will prefer to remain in the city than going out of town for enabling their children to attend the summer school. Those who cannot afford to go out of station will send their children to summer school. ","options":{"A":"Noneisimplicit","B":"OnlyIIisimplicit","C":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","D":"OnlyIIIisimplicit","E":"Allareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Noneisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The university Authority has decided to decentralize conduct of terminal examinations and give this responsibility to each college for its students to avoid delay in declaration of results. Assumptions:   The colleges are equipped to carry out this responsibility. There may not be uniformity in evaluation standard across the colleges. The students may welcome this new development. ","options":{"A":"Noneisimplicit","B":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","C":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","D":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Ten candidates, who were on the waiting list, could finally be admitted to the course. Assumptions:   Wait-listed candidates do not ordinarily get admission. A large number of candidates were on the waiting list. The number of candidates to be admitted is small. ","options":{"A":"Noneisimplicit","B":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","C":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","D":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit","E":"Allareimplicit"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Noneisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The successful man has the ability to judge himself correctly. Assumptions:   Inability to judge correctly causes failure. To judge others is of no use to a successful man. The successful man cannot make a wrong judgement. ","options":{"A":"Noneisimplicit","B":"Allareimplicit","C":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","D":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","E":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"Allareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  A State Government suspended two additional district judges. Assumptions:   They were negligent in discharging duties. There was a charge of misconduct against them. The government officials were biased against them. ","options":{"A":"Noneisimplicit","B":"EitherIorIIisimplicit","C":"Anyoneofthethreeisimplicit","D":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit","E":"EitherIorIIIisimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"EitherIorIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Bill Clinton is the second democrat to be re-elected as President of America, the other being the legendary Roosevelt. Assumptions:   Clinton has the same qualities that Roosevelt had. The majority of people in America have faith in Clinton. The election campaign of Clinton's rivals was not impressive. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIisimplicit","B":"OnlyIIisimplicit","C":"OnlyIIIisimplicit","D":"EitherIorIIIisimplicit","E":"EitherIIorIIIisimplicit"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"If you are a mechanical engineer, we want you as our supervisor.\" - An advertisement by Company X. Assumptions:   Mechanical engineers are expected to be better performers by Company X. The Company X needs supervisors. Mechanical engineers may get attracted and apply to Company X. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","B":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","C":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit","D":"Allareimplicit","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Allareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  \"Use Riya cold cream for fair complexion.\" - An advertisement. Assumptions:   People like to use cream for fair complexion. People are easily fooled. People respond to advertisements. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIisimplicit","B":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","C":"OnlyIIisimplicit","D":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Quality of life of a person is not dependent only on his wealth. Assumptions:   The aim of most people is just to acquire more wealth. There are some factors other than wealth which contribute to the quality of life. Wealth does not contribute to the quality of life at all. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIisimplicit","B":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","C":"OnlyIIisimplicit","D":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","E":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The civic authority has decided that all the factories located inside the city limits be shifted outside to reduce the level of environmental pollution in the city. Assumptions:   The pollution level in the city in future may reduce after these factories are shifted outside the city limit. Enough usable land is available outside the city limit for these factories. Many of these factories may shift to some other smaller towns to remain profitable. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIisimplicit","B":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","C":"OnlyIIisimplicit","D":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  State Council For Teacher Education (SCTE) has laid down guidelines in respect of minimum qualifications for a person to be employed as a teacher in universities or in recognised institutions. Assumptions:   The authorities will now appoint only qualified teachers. Only qualified people will apply for the teaching post. SCTE decides all the norms of educational qualifications for teaching faculty. ","options":{"A":"Noneisimplicit","B":"OnlyIisimplicit","C":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","D":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit","E":"Allareimplicit"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Allareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Considering the tickets sold during the last seven days, the circus authorities decided to continue the show for another fortnight which includes two weekends. Assumptions:   People may not turn up on weekdays. The average number of people who will be visiting circus will be more or less same as that of the last seven days. There may not be enough response at other places. ","options":{"A":"Allareimplicit","B":"Noneisimplicit","C":"OnlyIIisimplicit","D":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"OnlyIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Give this packet to Mr. X at his residence and return immediately. In case you are likely to be late inform me - Mr. A tells his clerk. Assumptions:   The clerk never informs about his late coming. The clerk may not obey Mr. As instructions. The clerk may not inform his late coming unless instructed. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","B":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","C":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit","D":"OnlyIIIisimplicit","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"OnlyIIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  An advertisement: Now you can own a new car in just Rs. 1,999 per month. Assumptions:   People aspire for owning a car. People do not want to buy used cars. Most people can afford to pay Rs. 1,999 per month for a new car. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","B":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","C":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit","D":"Allareimplicit","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Allareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The company has recently announced a series of incentives to the employees who are punctual and sincere. Assumptions:   Those who are not punctual at present may get motivated by the announcement. The productivity of the company may increase. The profit earned by the company may be more than the amount to be spent for the incentive programmes. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","B":"Noneisimplicit","C":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","D":"Allareimplicit","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The economic condition continues to be critical even after a good harvest season. Assumptions:   The economic condition was not critical before the harvest season. The economic condition could not have improved without a good harvest season. The economic condition was expected to improve after a good harvest season. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","B":"OnlyIIisimplicit","C":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","D":"OnlyIIIisimplicit","E":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"OnlyIIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The X passenger car manufacturing company announced a sharp reduction in the prices of its luxury cars. Assumptions:   There may be an increase in the sale of luxury cars of Company X. The other such car manufacturers may also reduce their prices. The competitor companies may not reduce their prices. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIisimplicit","B":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","C":"Noneisimplicit","D":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Noneofthese"},{"question":"Statement:  \"Buy pure and natural honey of company X.\" - An advertisement in a newspaper. Assumptions:   Artificial honey can be prepared. People do not mind paying more for pure and natural honey. No other company supplies pure honey. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIisimplicit","B":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","C":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit","D":"Allareimplicit","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  Unable to manage with the present salary, Arun has decided to join another company. Assumptions:   The new company has better work environment. The present company offers moderate pay packets. The new company offers higher salary to all its employees. ","options":{"A":"Noneisimplicit","B":"OnlyIIisimplicit","C":"Allareimplicit","D":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIIisimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  The employees association has appealed to the Managers of Company Z to introduce written examinations for clerical cadre recruitment to prevent selection of incompetent persons. Assumptions:   So far the Company Z used to select candidates without conducting a written examination. A written examination can help to identify competent persons. At higher level, written examination may not be of much use. ","options":{"A":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","B":"OnlyIIandIIIareimplicit","C":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit","D":"OnlyIIIisimplicit","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit"},{"question":"Statement:  To improve the employment situation in India, there is a need to recast the present educational system towards implementation of scientific discoveries in daily life. Assumptions:   The students after completing such education may be able to earn their livelihood. This may bring meaning of education in the minds of the youth. The state may earn more revenue as more and more people will engage themselves in self-employment. ","options":{"A":"Noneisimplicit","B":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit","C":"OnlyIIIisimplicit","D":"OnlyIandIIIareimplicit","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyIandIIareimplicit"}],"statement-and-conclusion":[{"question":"Statements: In a one day cricket match, the total runs made by a team were 200. Out of these 160 runs were made by spinners. Conclusions:     80% of the team consists of spinners.     The opening batsmen were spinners. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: The old order changed yielding place to new. Conclusions:     Change is the law of nature.     Discard old ideas because they are old. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyconclusionIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: Government has spoiled many top ranking financial institutions by appointing bureaucrats as Directors of these institutions. Conclusions:     Government should appoint Directors of the financial institutes taking into consideration the expertise of the person in the area of finance.     The Director of the financial institute should have expertise commensurate with the financial work carried out by the institute. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statements: Population increase coupled with depleting resources is going to be the scenario of many developing countries in days to come. Conclusions:     The population of developing countries will not continue to increase in future.     It will be very difficult for the governments of developing countries to provide its people decent quality of life. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: Prime age school-going children in urban India have now become avid as well as more regular viewers of television, even in households without a TV. As a result there has been an alarming decline in the extent of readership of newspapers. Conclusions:     Method of increasing the readership of newspapers should be devised.      A team of experts should be sent to other countries to study the impact of TV. on the readership of newspapers. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: In Japan, the incidence of stomach cancer is very high, while that of bowel cancer is very low. But Japanese immigrate to Hawaii, this is reversed - the rate of bowel cancer increases but the rate of stomach cancer is reduced in the next generation. All this is related to nutrition - the diets of Japanese in Hawaii are different than those in Japan. Conclusions:     The same diet as in Hawaii should be propagated in Japan also.     Bowel cancer is less severe than stomach cancer. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: The Government run company had asked its employees to declare their income and assets but it has been strongly resisted by employees union and no employee is going to declare his income. Conclusions:     The employees of this company do not seem to have any additional undisclosed income besides their salary.     The employees union wants all senior officers to declare their income first. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: Monitoring has become an integral part in the planning of social development programmes. It is recommended that Management Information System be developed for all programmes. This is likely to give a feedback on the performance of the functionaries and the efficacy with which services are being delivered. Conclusions:     All the social development programmes should be evaluated.     There is a need to monitor the performance of workers. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statements: The T.V. programmes, telecast specially for women are packed with a variety of recipes and household hints. A major portion of magazines for women also contains the items mentioned above. Conclusions:     Women are not interested in other things.     An average woman's primary interest lies in home and specially in the kitchen. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: The distance of 900 km by road between Bombay and Jafra will be reduced to 280 km by sea. This will lead to a saving of Rs. 7.92 crores per annum on fuel.  Conclusions:     Transportation by sea is cheaper than that by road.     Fuel must be saved to the greatest extent ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: The manager humiliated Sachin in the presence of his colleagues. Conclusions:     The manager did not like Sachin.     Sachin was not popular with his colleagues. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: Women's organisations in India have welcomed the amendment of the Industrial Employment Rules 1946 to curb sexual harassment at the work place. Conclusions:     Sexual harassment of women at work place is more prevalent in India as compared to other developed countries.     Many organisations in India will stop recruiting women to avoid such problems. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: Nation X faced growing international opposition for its decision to explode eight nuclear weapons at its test site. Conclusions:     The citizens of the nation favoured the decision.     Some powerful countries do not want other nations to become as powerful as they are. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: In a highly centralised power structure, in which even senior cabinet ministers are prepared to reduce themselves to pathetic countries or yesmen airing views that are primarily intended to anticipate or reflect the Prime Minister's own performances, there can be no place for any consensus that is quite different from real or contrived unanimity of opinion, expressed through a well orchestrated endorsement of the leader's actions. Conclusions:     The Ministers play safe by not giving anti-government views.     The Prime Minister does not encourage his colleagues to render their own views. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyconclusionIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: National Aluminium Company has moved India from a position of shortage to self-sufficiency in the metal. Conclusions:     Previously, India had to import aluminium.     With this speed, it can soon become a foreign exchange earner. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statements: Jade plant has thick leaves and it requires little water. Conclusions:     All plants with thick leaves require little water.     Jade plants may be grown in places where water is not in abundance. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: Use \"Kraft\" colours. They add colour to our life. - An advertisement. Conclusions:     Catchy slogans do not attract people.     People like dark colours. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: All those political prisoners were released on bail who had gone to jail for reasons other than political dharnas. Bail was not granted to persons involved in murders. Conclusions:     No political - prisoner had committed murder.     Some politicians were not arrested. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyconclusionIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: Modern man influences his destiny by the choice he makes unlike in the past. Conclusions:     Earlier there were fewer options available to man.     There was no desire in the past to influence the destiny. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyconclusionIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: Water supply in wards A and B of the city will be affected by about 50% on Friday because repairing work of the main lines is to be carried out. Conclusions:     The residents in these wards should economise on water on Friday.     The residents in these wards should store some water on the previous day. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statements: People who speak too much against dowry are those who had taken it themselves. Conclusions:     It is easier said than done.     People have double standards. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statements: The national norm is 100 beds per thousand populations but in this state, 150 beds per thousand are available in the hospitals. Conclusions:     Our national norm is appropriate.     The state's health system is taking adequate care in this regard. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: Our securities investments carry market risk. Consult your investment advisor or agent before investing. Conclusions:     One should not invest in securities.     The investment advisor calculates the market risk with certainty. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: Money plays a vital role in politics. Conclusions:     The poor can never become politicians.     All the rich men take part in politics. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: Vegetable prices are soaring in the market. Conclusions:     Vegetables are becoming a rare commodity.     People cannot eat vegetables. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: The serious accident in which a person was run down by a car yesterday had again focused attention on the most unsatisfactory state of roads. Conclusions:     The accident that occurred was fatal.     Several accidents have so far taken place because of unsatisfactory state of roads. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statements: In a recent survey report, it has been stated that those who undertake physical exercise for at least half an hour a day are less prone to have any heart ailments. Conclusions:     Moderate level of physical exercise is necessary for leading a healthy life.     All people who do desk-bound jobs definitely suffer from heart ailments. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyconclusionIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: A bird in hand is worth two in the bush. Conclusions:     We should be content with what we have.     We should not crave for what is not. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statements: This world is neither good nor evil; each man manufactures a world for himself. Conclusions:     Some people find this world quite good.     Some people find this world quite bad. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statements: The eligibility for admission to the course is minimum second class Master's degree. However, the candidates who have appeared for the final year examination of Master's degree can also apply. Conclusions:     All candidates who have yet to get their Master's degree will be there in the list of selected candidates.     All candidates having obtained second class Master's degree will be there in the list of selected candidates. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: Any student who does not behave properly while in the school brings bad name to himself and also for the school. Conclusions:     Such student should be removed from the school.     Stricter discipline does not improve behaviour of the students. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: A Corporate General Manager asked four managers to either submit their resignations by the next day or face termination orders from service. Three of them had submitted their resignations by that evening. Conclusions:     The next day, the remaining manager would also resign.     The General Manager would terminate his services the next day. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"EitherIorIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: Only good singers are invited in the conference. No one without sweet voice is a good singer. Conclusions:     All invited singers in the conference have sweet voice.      Those singers who do not have sweet voice are not invited in the conference. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statements: To cultivate interest in reading, the school has made it compulsory from June this year for each student to read two books per week and submit a weekly report on the books. Conclusions:     Interest in reading can be created by force.     Some students will eventually develop interest in reading. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: Applications of applicants who do no fulfil eligibility criteria and/or who do not submit applications before last date will be summarily rejected and will not be called for the written test. Conclusions:     Those who are called for the written test are those who fulfil eligibility criteria and have submitted their applications before last date.     Written test will be held only after scrutiny of applications. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statements: Recent trends also indicate that the number of child migrants in large cities is increasing. These children leave their families to join the ranks of urban poor doing odd jobs in markets, workshops, hotels or in service sectors. Conclusions:     Migration to big cities should be checked.      The plight of poor children should be thoroughly studied. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: No country is absolutely self-dependent these days. Conclusions:     It is impossible to grow and produce all that a country needs.     Countrymen in general have become lazy. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyconclusionIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: The percentage of the national income shared by the top 10 per cent of households in India is 35. Conclusions:     When an economy grows fast, concentration of wealth in certain pockets of population takes place.      The national income is unevenly distributed in India. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: Players who break various records in a fair way get special prizes. Player X broke the world record but was found to be under the influence of a prohibited drug. Conclusions:     X will get the special prize.     X will not get the special prize. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: Company X has marketed the product. Go ahead; purchase it if price and quality are your considerations. Conclusions:     The product must be good in quality.     The price of the product must be reasonable. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statements: Quality has a price tag. India is allocating lots of funds to education. Conclusions:     Quality of education in India would improve soon.     Funding alone can enhance quality of education. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyconclusionIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: Although we have rating agencies like Crisil, ICRA, there is demand to have a separate rating agency for IT companies to protect investors. Conclusions:     Assessment of financial worth of IT companies calls for separate set of skills, insight and competencies.      Now the investors investing in IT companies will get protection of their investment. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyconclusionIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: The standard of education in private schools is much better than Municipal and Zila Parishad-run schools. Conclusions:     The Municipal and Zila Pariskad should make serious efforts to improve standard of their schools.     All Municipal and Zila Parishad schools should be closed immediately. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyconclusionIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: All the organised persons find time for rest. Sunita, in spite of her very busy schedule, finds time for rest. Conclusions:     Sunita is an organised person.     Sunita is an industrious person. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statements: Domestic demand has been increasing faster than the production of indigenous crude oil. Conclusions:     Crude oil must be imported.     Domestic demand should be reduced. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"EitherIorIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: He stressed the need to stop the present examination system and its replacement by other methods which would measure the real merit of the students. Conclusions:     Examinations should be abolished.     The present examination system does not measure the real merit of the students. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: Fashion is a form of ugliness so intolerable that we have to alter it every six months. Conclusions:     Fashion designers do not understand the public mind very well.     The public by and large is highly susceptible to novelty. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: Until our country achieves economic equality, political freedom and democracy would be meaningless. Conclusions:     Political freedom and democracy go hand in hand.     Economic equality leads to real political freedom and democracy. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows"},{"question":"Soldiers serve their country.","options":{"A":"Mengenerallyservetheircountry.","B":"Thosewhoservetheircountryaresoldiers.","C":"Somemenwhoaresoldiersservetheircountry.","D":"Womendonotservetheircountrybecausetheyarenotsoldiers."},"answer_option":"C","answer":"Somemenwhoaresoldiersservetheircountry."},{"question":"A factory worker has five children. No one else in the factory has five children.","options":{"A":"Allworkersinthefactoryhavefivechildreneach.","B":"Everybodyinthefactoryhaschildren.","C":"Someofthefactoryworkershavemorethanfivechildren.","D":"Onlyoneworkerinthefactoryhasexactlyfivechildren."},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Onlyoneworkerinthefactoryhasexactlyfivechildren."},{"question":"Television convinces viewers that the likelihood of their becoming the victim of a violent crime is extremely high; at the same time by its very nature, TV persuades viewers to passively accept whatever happens to them.","options":{"A":"TVviewingpromotescriminalbehaviour.","B":"TVviewersaremostlikelytobevictimizedthanothers.","C":"PeopleshouldnotwatchTV.","D":"TVpromotesafeelingofhelplessvulnerabilityinviewers."},"answer_option":"D","answer":"TVpromotesafeelingofhelplessvulnerabilityinviewers."},{"question":"A forest has as many sandal trees as it has Ashoka trees. Three-fourth of the trees are old ones and half of the trees are at the flowering stage.","options":{"A":"AllAshokatreesareatthefloweringstage.","B":"Allsandaltreesareatthefloweringstage.","C":"Atleastone-halfoftheAshokatreesareold.","D":"One-halfofthesandaltreesareatthefloweringstage.","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Noneofthese"},{"question":"The government is soon going to introduce a bill which would permit the instituting of private universities under very strict directions.","options":{"A":"Wehavesomeprivateuniversitiesinourcountryevennow.","B":"Thedemandformoreuniversitiesisbeingsteppedup.","C":"SuchdirectionscanalsobeissuedwithoutinformingtheParliament.","D":"Thegovernmentgivesdirectionstoestablishanythinginprivatesector.","E":"Unlessanduntilthedirectionsaregiven,theprivateuniversitiescanchargeexorbitantfees."},"answer_option":"B","answer":"Thedemandformoreuniversitiesisbeingsteppedup."},{"question":"All that glitters is not gold.","options":{"A":"Non-metalsalsoglitter.","B":"Onlygoldglitters.","C":"Notallmetalsglitter.","D":"Glitteringthingsmaybedeceptive."},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Glitteringthingsmaybedeceptive."},{"question":"Most dresses in that shop are expensive.","options":{"A":"Therearenocheapdressesavailableinthatshop.","B":"Handloomdressesinthatshoparecheap.","C":"Therearecheapdressesalsointhatshop.","D":"Somedressesinthatshopareexpensive."},"answer_option":"C","answer":"Therearecheapdressesalsointhatshop."},{"question":"Many business offices are located in buildings having two to eight floors. If a building has more than three floors, it has a lift.","options":{"A":"Allfloorsmaybereachedbylifts.","B":"Onlyfloorsabovethethirdfloorhavelifts.","C":"Seventhfloorshavelifts.","D":"Secondfloorsdonothavelifts."},"answer_option":"C","answer":"Seventhfloorshavelifts."},{"question":"Every library has books.","options":{"A":"Booksareonlyinlibrary.","B":"Librariesaremeantforbooksonly.","C":"Nolibraryiswithoutbooks.","D":"Somelibrariesdonothavereaders."},"answer_option":"C","answer":"Nolibraryiswithoutbooks."},{"question":"In a class, three-fourth of the boys play football, one-half play cricket, one-fourth of those who play cricket do not play football.","options":{"A":"Two-thirdoftheboysplayonlyfootball.","B":"One-fourthoftheboysplayneithercricketnorfootball.","C":"One-thirdoftheboysplayneithercricketnorfootball.","D":"One-eighthoftheboysplayneithercricketnorfootball.","E":"Two-fifthoftheboysplayonlyfootball."},"answer_option":"D","answer":"One-eighthoftheboysplayneithercricketnorfootball."},{"question":"Every man should have his identity card with him. That card should mention his blood group,  complete address and telephone number for contact, in case, some serious accident takes place.","options":{"A":"Bloodcannotbetransfuseduntilitsgroupismentionedinthecard.","B":"Thepoliceneedsthisinformationespeciallywhentheaccidentisfatal.","C":"Incaseofemergency,hemayforgethisaddressandmayneedthecardtocontacthishouse.","D":"Noneissupposedtoforgethisphonenumberunderanycircumstances.","E":"Whentheseriouslyinjuredpersonishelplesstotellhisbloodgroup,thisinformationwouldsufficetoindicatetherequiredbloodgroup."},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Noneissupposedtoforgethisphonenumberunderanycircumstances."},{"question":"In this company, 60 per cent of the employees are males, 40 per cent are females, 80 per cent of the employees are sincere and 40 per cent of the employees are from this city - Rawalpura.","options":{"A":"Allmaleemployeesarefromoutstation.","B":"Allmaleemployeesaresincere.","C":"20percentoffemaleemployeesarenotsincere.","D":"AllfemaleemployeesarefromRawalpura.","E":"Noneofthese"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"Noneofthese"},{"question":"All beggars are poor.","options":{"A":"IfAisabeggar,thenAisnotrich.","B":"IfAisnotrich,thenAisnotabeggar.","C":"Allthosewhoarepoorarebeggars.","D":"IfAisrich,thenAisnotabeggar."},"answer_option":"D","answer":"IfAisrich,thenAisnotabeggar."},{"question":"This book can help because all good books help.","options":{"A":"Thisisnotagoodbook.","B":"Thisisagoodbook.","C":"Nogoodbookhelps.","D":"Somegoodbookshelp."},"answer_option":"B","answer":"Thisisagoodbook."},{"question":"Hitesh told Mohit a ghost lived by the peepal tree on the outskirts of the village.","options":{"A":"Peepaltreesgrowontheoutskirtsofthevillage.","B":"Ghostsliveonpeepaltrees.","C":"Hiteshperhapsbelievedinthestoriesofghosts.","D":"Mohitmustbeafraidofghosts."},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Mohitmustbeafraidofghosts."},{"question":"To pass the examination, one must work hard.","options":{"A":"Examinationisrelatedwithhardwork.","B":"Allthosewhoworkhard,pass.","C":"Examinationcausessomeanxietyandthosewhoworkhardovercomeit.","D":"Withouthardwork,onedoesnotpass.","E":"Hard-workingpersonisasatisfiedperson."},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Withouthardwork,onedoesnotpass."},{"question":"The data given by the U.S. Labour Ministry indicate that till the year 2000, there will be a shortage of 1,00,000 programmers. A spokesman from the industry said, \"We should understand this thoroughly America needs Indian programmers. This is not only the question of investment but also of the talent with which the Indian programmers are equipped\".","options":{"A":"Inothersectorsalso,therewillbeshortageofthetalentedlabourtilltheyear2000.","B":"Indianprogrammersarethemosttalentedintheworld.","C":"Indianprogrammersareavailableoncomparativelylesssalaryincomparisontotheprogrammersfromothercountries.","D":"InspiteofenteringwithhugecapitalintheSoftwareTraining,U.S.couldnotbeabletomeetitsownneedsfully.","E":"TheIndiansoftwaremarketiswellequippedtosendprogrammestoothercountries."},"answer_option":"D","answer":"InspiteofenteringwithhugecapitalintheSoftwareTraining,U.S.couldnotbeabletomeetitsownneedsfully."},{"question":"All the books, written by Prabhakar, are textbooks. Some of his books are published by ABC Publishing Company.","options":{"A":"ABCPublishingCompanypublishestextbooksonly.","B":"SometextbookswrittenbyPrabhakararepublishedbypublishersotherthanABCPublishingCompany.","C":"ABCPublishingCompanypublishessomecriticalessayswrittenbyPrabhakar.","D":"AllthebookspublishedbyABCPublishingCompanyhavebeenwrittenbyPrabhakar."},"answer_option":"B","answer":"SometextbookswrittenbyPrabhakararepublishedbypublishersotherthanABCPublishingCompany."},{"question":"All students in my class are bright. Manish is not bright.","options":{"A":"Somestudentsarenotbright.","B":"Manishmustworkhard.","C":"Non-brightonesarenotstudents.","D":"Manishisnotastudentofmyclass."},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Manishisnotastudentofmyclass."},{"question":"During the Puja days', people visit those houses where 'puja' is performed. They make it a point to go even if they are not invited. Manmohan visited the house of Keshav, his office colleague, during 'puja days'.","options":{"A":"KeshavhadinvitedManmohanforsomeotherfunction.","B":"Manmohan,beingareligiousman,wenttoKeshav'shouseuninvited.","C":"InKeshav'shouse,'puja'wasperformed.","D":"ManmohanwasinvitedbyKeshav."},"answer_option":"D","answer":"ManmohanwasinvitedbyKeshav."},{"question":"All guilty politicians were arrested. Kishan and Chander were among those arrested.","options":{"A":"Allpoliticiansareguilty.","B":"Allarrestedpeoplearepoliticians.","C":"KishanandChanderwerenotpoliticians.","D":"KishanandChanderwereguilty."},"answer_option":"D","answer":"KishanandChanderwereguilty."},{"question":"In the university examination, most of the candidates write in Hindi medium.","options":{"A":"SomecandidatesofthisexaminationwriteinHindi.","B":"MostlycandidateswithHindimediumappearinthisexamination.","C":"InthisexaminationnocandidatewritesanswersinmediumotherthanHindi,","D":"AllthecandidateswhoappearinthisexaminationwriteanswersinHindi."},"answer_option":"B","answer":"MostlycandidateswithHindimediumappearinthisexamination."},{"question":"Statements: The best evidence of India's glorious past is the growing popularity of Ayurvedic medicines in the West. Conclusions:     Ayurvedic medicines are not popular in India.     Allopathic medicines are more popular in India. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: Death keeps no calendar. Conclusions:     Man must die one day.     Death can come at any time. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statements: Wind is an inexhaustible source of energy and an aerogenerator can convert it into electricity. Though not much has been done in this field, the survey shows that there is vast potential for developing wind as alternative source of energy. Conclusions:     Energy by wind is comparatively newly emerging field.     The energy crisis can be dealt by exploring more in the field of aero-generation. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statements: The average number of persons per household is 5 in urban areas whereas it is 7 in rural areas. The national average is 6. Conclusions:     The population per unit area in the rural areas is higher than in the urban areas.     More persons live in the same household in the rural areas as compared to those in the urban areas. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: The best way to escape from a problem is to solve it. Conclusions:     Your life will be dull if you don't face a problem.     To escape from problems, you should always have some solutions with you. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: Parents are prepared to pay any price for an elite education to their children. Conclusions:     All parents these days are very well off.     Parents have an obsessive passion for a perfect development of their children through good schooling. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: From the next academic year, students will have the option of dropping Mathematics and Science for their school leaving certificate examination. Conclusions:     Students who are weak in Science and Mathematics will be admitted.     Earlier students did not have the choice of continuing their education without taking these subjects. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statements: It is almost impossible to survive and prosper in this world without sacrificing ethics and morality. Conclusions:     World appreciates some concepts but may not uphold it.     Concept of ethics and morality are not practicable in life. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: The use of non-conventional sources of energy will eliminate the energy crisis in the world. Conclusions:     Modern technology is gradually replacing the conventional sources of energy.      The excessive exploitation of environment has led to depletion of conventional sources of energy. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statements: My first and foremost task is to beautify this city - if city X and Y can do it - why can't we do it. - Statement of Municipal Commissioner of city Z after taking over charge. Conclusions:     The people of city Z are not aware about the present state of ugliness of their city.     The present Commissioner has worked in city X and Y and has good experience of beautifying cities. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: A man must be wise to be a good wrangler. Good wranglers are talkative and boring. Conclusions:     All the wise persons are boring.     All the wise persons are good wranglers. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: \"The Government will review the present policy of the diesel price in view of further spurt in the international oil prices\". - A spokesman of the Government. Conclusions:     The Government will increase the price of the diesel after the imminent spurt in the international oil prices.     The Government will not increase the price of the diesel even after the imminent spurt in the international oil prices. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"EitherIorIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: The Government of country X has recently announced several concessions and offered attractive package tours for foreign visitors. Conclusions:     Now, more number of foreign tourists will visit the country.      The Government of country X seems to be serious in attracting tourists. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statements: After this amendment to the Constitution, no child below the age of 14 years will be employed to work in any factory or mine or engaged in any other hazardous employment. Conclusions:     Before this amendment, children below 14 years were employed to work in factory or mine.     The employers must now abide by this amendment to the Constitution. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statements: It has been decided by the Government to withdraw 33% of the subsidy on cooking gas from the beginning of next month. - A spokesman of the Government. Conclusions:     People now no more desire or need such subsidy from Government as they can afford increased price of the cooking gas.     The price of the cooking gas will increase at least by 33% from the next month. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: A large majority of the work force in India is unorganised. Most of them earn either the minimum or uncertain wages while others are engaged in sundry jobs. Conclusions:     The workers in the organised sector get better facilities and stay longer in their jobs.     Some workers in the unorganised sector of the work force have a regular and fixed income. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: Industrial Revolution which first of all started in Europe has brought about modern age. Conclusions:     Disparity between rich and poor results in revolution.     Revolution overhauls society. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: The T.V. staff deserves an applaud for showing booth capture. Conclusions:     T.V. aims at showing things in their true perspective.     People involved in booth capturing have been recognised and are being tried by law. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyconclusionIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: America's defence secretary reiterated that they would continue to supply arms to Pakistan. Conclusions:     Pakistan is incapable of manufacturing arms.     It would ensure peace in the region. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: Fortune favours the brave. Conclusions:     Risks are necessary for success.     Cowards die many times before their death. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyconclusionIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: Irregularity is a cause for failure in exams. Some regular students fail in the examinations. Conclusions:     All failed students are regular.     All successful students are not regular. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: In case of outstanding candidates, the condition of previous experience of social work may be waived by the admission committee for M.A. (Social work). Conclusions:     Some of the students for M.A. (Social work) will have previous experience of social work.     Some of the students for M.A. (Social work) will not have previous experience of social work. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statements: Today out of the world population of several thousand million, the majority of men have to live under governments which refuse them personal liberty and the right to dissent. Conclusions:     People are indifferent to personal liberty and the right to dissent.      People desire personal liberty and the right to dissent. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: Double your money in five months - An advertisement. Conclusions:     The assurance is not genuine.     People want their money to grow. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: The XYZ Medical College has started a cell which will conduct counselling workshops in the field of stress management to patients and general public. Conclusions:     The hospital has needed resources to start such activity.     Patients and general public feel a need to have such cell in the hospital. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statements: The Prime Minister emphatically stated that his government will make every possible effort for the upliftment of poor farmers and farmhands. Conclusions:     Except poor farmers and farmhands, all others have got benefits of fruits of development.     No serious efforts have been made in the past for upliftment of any section of the society. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: A neurotic is a non-stupid person who behaves stupidly. Conclusions:     Neuroticism and stupidity go hand in hand.     Normal persons behave intelligently. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyconclusionIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: We should inform all our officers not to read newspapers during office hours - Chief Manager tells. Chief Administrator. Conclusions:     Reading newspapers during office hours is desirable.     Office efficiency will not increase by stopping this. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: The Cabinet of State X took certain steps to tackle the milk glut in the state as the cooperatives and government dairies failed to use the available milk. -  A news report. Conclusions:     The milk production of State X is more than its need.     The Government and co-operative dairies in State X are not equipped in terms of resources and technology to handle such excess milk. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statements: Video libraries are flourishing very much these days. Conclusions:     People in general have got a video craze.     It is much cheaper to see as many movies as one likes on videos rather than going to the cinema hall. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statements: Although the education system has progressed from the point of view of the number of schools, most of them are ill-equipped and have not achieved excellence in imparting education. Conclusions:     In future, we should provide good teachers and equipment to these schools.     We need not open any more schools in the future. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyconclusionIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: This book 'Z' is the only book which focuses its attention to the problem of poverty in India between 1950 and 1980. Conclusions:     There was no question of poverty before 1950.     No other book deals with poverty in India during 1950 to 1980. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: For over three decades Company X has been totally involved in energy conservation, its efficient use and management. Conclusions:     The Company has yet to learn and acquire basic things in this area.     It is dedication that is more important than knowledge and expertise. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: About 50 per cent of the animal by-products - hair, skin, horns etc. is edible protein. American chemists have developed a method of isolating 45 per cent of this protein. They used an enzyme developed in Japan to break down soya protein. Conclusions:     Americans have not been able to develop enzymes.     Animal by-products protein has the same composition as soya protein. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: The commissioner of police has appealed people not to put up banners which obstruct pedestrian or motor traffic. Conclusions:     Some of the people may respond and will not put up such banners.     Policemen will have to keep a watchful eye on the new banners which are being put up on the roads. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyconclusionIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: The Minister questioned the utility of the space research programme and suggested its replacement by other areas of felt national needs. Conclusions:     Exploring the space does not contribute to critical national needs.     Research should be oriented to national needs. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statements: The secret of success is constancy of purpose. Conclusions:     Constant dripping wears the stone.     Single-minded devotion is necessary for achieving success. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statements: Leaders, who raise much hue and cry about the use of Hindi, generally send their children to English medium schools. Conclusions:     India lacks good Hindi medium schools.     There is a world of difference between preaching and practising. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"EitherIorIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: Any young man, who makes dowry as a condition for marriage, discredits himself and dishonours womanhood. Conclusions:     Those who take dowry in marriage should be condemned by society.     Those who do not take dowry in marriage respect womanhood. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statements: The 'Official Secrets Act' (OSA) enacted by the ABC government during the war seems to be one of the major source of corruption in the country X. Conclusions:     The OSA has to be abolished immediately to put an end to the corruption in the country X.     The ABC government had an intention of encouraging corruption in the government offices. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyconclusionIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: In India, more emphasis should be placed on areas such as agriculture, engineering and technology instead of basic and pure sciences. Conclusions:     India has achieved sufficient progress in basic and pure sciences.     In the past, the productivity factor in our economy was neglected. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: If all players play to their full potential, we will win the match. We have won the match. Conclusions:     All players played to their full potential.     Some players did not play to their full potential. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyconclusionIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: The Bank of England's move to auction 25 metric tons of gold drew plenty of bidders looking for a bargain, but was criticised by major gold producers worldwide. Conclusions:     The Bank of England should not auction gold which it possesses to keep steady international prices of gold.     Bidders should quote higher gold prices to retain present value of gold in the international markets. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"NeitherInorIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: Good voice is a natural gift but one has to keep practising to improve and excel well in the field of music. Conclusions:      Natural gifts need nurturing and care.     Even though your voice is not good, one can keep practising. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyconclusionIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: Adversity makes a man wise. Conclusions:     The poor are wise.     Man learns from bitter experience. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: The interview panel may select a candidate who neither possesses the desired qualifications nor the values and attributes. Conclusions:     The inclusion of specialists on the interview panel does not guarantee that the selection will be proper.     The interview test has certain limitations in the matter of selection of candidates. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"E","answer":"BothIandIIfollow"},{"question":"Statements: The President of XYZ Party indicated that 25 independent Members of Legislative Assembly (MLA) are seriously considering various options of joining some political party. But in any case all of them collectively will join one party only. Conclusions:     The 25 independent MLAs will join XYZ party in a short period of time.     The 25 independent MLAs will join some other political party in a short period of time. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"EitherIorIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: I know nothing except the fact of my ignorance. Conclusions:     Writer's knowledge is very poor.     The world of knowledge is too vast to be explored by a single person. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: Company X has a record of manufacturing cameras of quality and the latest design so that you do not spoil even a single shot irrespective of the weather conditions. Conclusions:     No other company except X is reputed in the camera industry.     Anyone can take an acceptable shot with camera X. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows"},{"question":"Statements: India's economy is depending mainly on forests. Conclusions:     Trees should be preserved to improve Indian economy.     India wants only maintenance of forests to improve economic conditions. ","options":{"A":"OnlyconclusionIfollows","B":"OnlyconclusionIIfollows","C":"EitherIorIIfollows","D":"NeitherInorIIfollows","E":"BothIandIIfollow"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"OnlyconclusionIfollows"}],"theme-detection":[{"question":"The attainment of individual and organisational goals is mutually interdependent and linked by a common denominator - employee work motivation. Organisational members are motivated to satisfy their personal goals, and they contribute their efforts to the attainment of organisational objectives as means of achieving these personal goals. The passage best supports the statement that motivation -","options":{"A":"encouragesanindividualtogiveprioritytopersonalgoalsoverorganisationalgoals.","B":"iscrucialforthesurvivalofanindividualandorganisation.","C":"istheproductofanindividual'sphysicalandmentalenergy.","D":"istheexternalforcewhichinducesanindividualtocontributehisefforts.","E":"makesorganisationandsocietyinseparable."},"answer_option":"A","answer":"encouragesanindividualtogiveprioritytopersonalgoalsoverorganisationalgoals."},{"question":"Due to enormous profits involved in smuggling, hundreds of persons have been attracted towards this anti-national activity. Some of them became millionaires overnight. India has a vast coastline both on the Eastern and Western Coast. It has been a heaven for smugglers who have been carrying on their activities with great impunity. There is no  doubt, that from time to time certain seizures were made by the enforcement authorities, during raids and ambush but even allowing these losses the smugglers made huge profits. The passage best supports the statement that","options":{"A":"smugglinghamperstheeconomicdevelopmentofanation.","B":"smugglingoughttobecurbed.","C":"authoritiesaretakingstrictmeasurestocurbsmuggling.","D":"smugglingisfastincreasinginourcountryowingtothequickprofititentails."},"answer_option":"D","answer":"smugglingisfastincreasinginourcountryowingtothequickprofititentails."},{"question":"Though the waste of time or the expenditure on fashions is very large, yet fashions have come to stay. They will not go, come what may. However, what is now required is that strong efforts should be made to displace the excessive craze for fashion from the minds of these youngsters. The passage best supports the statement that:","options":{"A":"fashionistheneedoftheday.","B":"theexcessivecrazeforfashionisdetrimentaltoone'spersonality.","C":"thehoardforfashionshouldbedoneawaywithsoasnottoletdowntheconstructivedevelopment.","D":"workandotheractivitiesshouldbevaluedmorethantheoutwardappearance."},"answer_option":"C","answer":"thehoardforfashionshouldbedoneawaywithsoasnottoletdowntheconstructivedevelopment."},{"question":"One of the important humanitarian by-products of technology is the greater dignity and value that it imparts to human labour. In a highly industrialized society, there is no essential difference between Brahmin and Dalit, Muslim and Hindu; they are equally useful and hence equally valuable for in the industrial society individual productivity fixes the size of the pay cheque and this fixes social status. The passage best supports the statement that:","options":{"A":"technologydecidesindividual'ssocialstatus.","B":"castesandreligionsareman-made.","C":"humanlabourhasdignityandvalue.","D":"allindividuals,irrespectiveofcasteandcreed,arebornequal.","E":"industrialsocietyisagreatlevellerofmen."},"answer_option":"C","answer":"humanlabourhasdignityandvalue."},{"question":"The future of women in India is quite bright and let us hope that they will justify their abilities by rising to the occasion. Napoleon was right when he declared that by educating the women we can educate the whole nation. Because a country can never rise without the contribution of 50% of their population. The passage best supports the statement that:","options":{"A":"Indiaisstrivinghardfortheemancipationofwomen.","B":"allwomenshouldbewelleducated.","C":"anationcanprogressonlywhenwomenaregivenequalrightsandopportunitiesasmen.","D":"womenoughttobeimpartedfullfreedomtoprovetheirworthandcontributetotheprogressofthenation."},"answer_option":"D","answer":"womenoughttobeimpartedfullfreedomtoprovetheirworthandcontributetotheprogressofthenation."},{"question":"The prevention of accidents makes it necessary not only that safety devices be used to guard exposed machinery but also that mechanics be instructed in safety rules which they must follow for their own protection, and that lighting in the plant be adequate. The passage best supports the statement that industrial accidents -","options":{"A":"arealwaysavoidable;","B":"maybeduetoignorance.","C":"cannotbeentirelyovercome.","D":"canbeeliminatedwiththehelpofsafetyrules.","E":"usuallyresultfrominadequatemachinery."},"answer_option":"D","answer":"canbeeliminatedwiththehelpofsafetyrules."},{"question":"To forgive an injury is often considered to be a sign of weakness; it is really a sign of strength. It is easy to allow oneself to be carried away by resentment and hate into an act of vengeance; but it takes a strong character to restrain those natural passions. The man who forgives an injury proves himself to be the superior of the man who wronged himself and puts the wrong-doer to shame. The passage best supports' the statement that:","options":{"A":"thesuffereraloneknowstheintensityofhissufferings.","B":"peopletendtoforgivethethingshappenedinthepast.","C":"naturalpassionsaredifficulttosuppress.","D":"mercyisthenoblestformofrevenge.","E":"apersonwithcalmandcomposednaturehasdepthofthoughtandvision."},"answer_option":"D","answer":"mercyisthenoblestformofrevenge."},{"question":"Industrial exhibitions play a major role in a country's economy. Such exhibitions, now regularly held in Delhi, enable us to measure the extent of our own less advanced industrial progress and the mighty industrial power and progress of countries like the U.K., U.S.A. and Russia whose pavilions are the centres of the greatest attention and attractions. The passage best supports the statement that industrial exhibitions -","options":{"A":"greatlytaxthepooreconomies.","B":"aremoreusefulforthedevelopedcountrieslikeU.S.A.whoseproductsstandoutsuperiortothoseofthedevelopingcountries.","C":"arenotofmuchusetothecountrieswhoareindustriallybackward.","D":"boostupproductionqualitativelyandquantitativelybyanalyticalcomparisonofacountry'sproductswiththoseofthedevelopedcountries."},"answer_option":"D","answer":"boostupproductionqualitativelyandquantitativelybyanalyticalcomparisonofacountry'sproductswiththoseofthedevelopedcountries."},{"question":"The school has always been the most important means of transferring the wealth of tradition form one generation to the next. This applies today in an even higher degree than in former times for, through the modern development of economy, the family as bearer of tradition and education has become weakened. This passage best supports the statement that for transferring the wealth of tradition from one generation to the next  -","options":{"A":"therearemeansotherthantheschool.","B":"severaldifferentsourcesmustbetried.","C":"economicdevelopmentplaysacrucialrole","D":"moderntechnologymustbeputtouse.","E":"family,asever,isthemostpotentmeans."},"answer_option":"C","answer":"economicdevelopmentplaysacrucialrole"},{"question":"Emerson said that the poet was landlord, Sealord, airlord. The flight of imagination made the poet master of land, sea and air. But a poet's dream of yesterday becomes today an actual achievement and a reality for all men. Even those who invented, improved and perfected the aeroplane could hardly have dreamt of the possibility of flight into outer space. The passage best supports the statement that:","options":{"A":"seeminglyimpossibleimaginationsmakeoneagoodpoet,","B":"allimaginationsbecomearealitysomeday.","C":"whatmanimaginedhasneverbeenimpossible;hehasalwaysturneditarealitythroughhisconceptionofideasandsheerhardlabour.","D":"manhasreachedtheclimaxoftechnologicaldevelopmentwithhisexplorationintoouterspace."},"answer_option":"C","answer":"whatmanimaginedhasneverbeenimpossible;hehasalwaysturneditarealitythroughhisconceptionofideasandsheerhardlabour."},{"question":"It is up to our government and planners to devise ways and means for the mobilisation of about ten crore workers whose families total up about forty crore men, women and children. Our agriculture is over-manned. A lesser number of agriculturists would mean more purchasing or spending power to every agriculturist. This will result in the shortage of man-power for many commodities to be produced for which there will be a new demand from a prosperous agrarian class. This shortage will be removed by surplus man-power released from agriculture as suggested above. The passage best supports the statement that:","options":{"A":"employmentinproductionismorefruitfulthanemploymentinagriculture.","B":"Indianeconomyisinapoorshapebasicallyduetoimpropermobilisationofman-power.","C":"ashiftoflabourfromagriculturalsectortotheindustrialsectorwouldupliftthelivingstandard.","D":"theindustrialsectorislabour-deficientwhiletheagriculturalsectorisover-mannedinourcountry."},"answer_option":"B","answer":"Indianeconomyisinapoorshapebasicallyduetoimpropermobilisationofman-power."},{"question":"Exports and imports, a swelling favourable balance of trade, investments and bank-balances, are not an index or a balance sheet of national prosperity. Till the beginning of the Second World War, English exports were noticeably greater than what they are today. And yet England has greater national prosperity today than it ever had. Because the income of average Englishmen, working as field and factory labourers, clerks, policemen, petty shopkeepers and shop assistants, domestic workers and other low-paid workers, has gone up. The passage best supports the statement that:","options":{"A":"acountry'seconomicstandardcanbebestadjudgedbypercapitalincome.","B":"acountry'sbalanceoftradeisthemaincriteriaofdeterminingitseconomicprosperity.","C":"anation'seconomystrengthenswiththeincreaseinexports.","D":"EnglishtradehascontinuallyincreasedsincetheSecondWorldWar."},"answer_option":"A","answer":"acountry'seconomicstandardcanbebestadjudgedbypercapitalincome."},{"question":"Satisfaction with co-workers, promotion opportunities, the nature of work, and pay goes with high performance among those with strong growth needs. Among those with weak growth needs, no such relationship is present - and, in fact, satisfaction with promotion opportunities goes with low performance. This passage best supports the statement that:","options":{"A":"satisfactionisaninevitableorganisationalvariable.","B":"jobsatisfactionandperformancearedirectlyandcloselyrelated.","C":"relationshipbetweenjobsatisfactionandperformanceismoderatedbygrowthneed.","D":"everyorganisationhasfewemployeeshavingweakgrowthneed.","E":"highperformanceisessentialfororganisationaleffectiveness."},"answer_option":"C","answer":"relationshipbetweenjobsatisfactionandperformanceismoderatedbygrowthneed."},{"question":"The only true education comes through the stimulation of the child's powers by the demands of the social situations in which he finds himself. Through these demands he is stimulated to act as a member of a unity, to emerge from his original narrowness of action and feeling, and to conceive himself from the standpoint of the welfare of the group to which he belongs. The passage best supports the statement that real education -","options":{"A":"willtakeplaceifthechildrenimbibeactionandfeeling.","B":"willtakeplaceifthechildrenarephysicallystrong.","C":"isnotprovidedinourschoolstoday.","D":"comesthroughtheinteractionwithsocialsituations.","E":"comesfromtheself-centredapproachofthestudents."},"answer_option":"D","answer":"comesthroughtheinteractionwithsocialsituations."},{"question":"The press should not be afraid of upholding and supporting a just and righteous cause. It should not be afraid of criticising the government in a healthy manner. The press has to be eternally vigilant to protect the rights of the workers, backward and suppressed sections of the society. It should also give a balanced view of the things so that people can be helped in the formation of a healthy public opinion. The passage best supports the statement that","options":{"A":"presshasagreatroletoplayinademocracy.","B":"thepressistheonlymeanstoprojecttothemassesthepoliciesofthegovernment.","C":"thefreedomofpressisessentialfortheproperfunctioningofdemocracy.","D":"thepresscanbeusedbythegovernmentsasaneffectivemediafortheupliftmentofthebackwardsectionsofsociety.","E":"alltheinformationgivenbythepressshouldbewell-articulatedsoastogainagoodopiniontowardstherulingparty."},"answer_option":"C","answer":"thefreedomofpressisessentialfortheproperfunctioningofdemocracy."},{"question":"Throughout the ages the businessman has helped build civilisation's great cities, provided people with luxuries and artists with patronage, and lift his fellow citizens to understand the standard of living. In the last few centuries the businessman has seeded the Industrial Revolution around the world.  The passage best supports the statement that the businessman -","options":{"A":"isaccountabletothesociety.","B":"livesluxuriousandcomfortablelife.","C":"isthebeneficiaryoftheIndustrialRevolution.","D":"iscapableofraisinghisstandardofliving.","E":"hascontributedtothegrowthofcivilisation."},"answer_option":"E","answer":"hascontributedtothegrowthofcivilisation."},{"question":"There is a shift in our economy from a manufacturing to a service orientation. The increase in service-sector will require the managers to work more with people rather than with objects and things from the assembly line. This passage best supports the statement that:","options":{"A":"managersshouldhaveabalancedmind.","B":"assemblylinewillexistinserviceorganisations.","C":"interpersonalskillswillbecomemoreimportantinthefutureworkplace.","D":"manufacturingorganisationsignoreimportanceofpeople.","E":"serviceorganisationswillnotdealwithobjectsandthings."},"answer_option":"C","answer":"interpersonalskillswillbecomemoreimportantinthefutureworkplace."},{"question":"The virtue of art does not allow the work to be interfered with or immediately ruled by anything other than itself. It insists that it alone shall touch the work in order to bring it into being. Art requires that nothing shall attain the work except through art itself. This passage best supports the statement that:","options":{"A":"artisgovernedbyexternalrulesandconditions.","B":"artisforthesakeofartandlife.","C":"artisforthesakeofartalone.","D":"artistrealiseshisdreamsthroughhisartisticcreation.","E":"artistshouldusehisartforthesakeofsociety."},"answer_option":"C","answer":"artisforthesakeofartalone."}],"verbal-classification":[{"question":"Which word does NOT belong with the others?","options":{"A":"parsley","B":"basil","C":"dill","D":"mayonnaise"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"mayonnaise"},{"question":"Which word does NOT belong with the others?","options":{"A":"inch","B":"ounce","C":"centimeter","D":"yard"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"ounce"},{"question":"Which word does NOT belong with the others?","options":{"A":"tyre","B":"steeringwheel","C":"engine","D":"car"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"car"},{"question":"Which word does NOT belong with the others?","options":{"A":"tulip","B":"rose","C":"bud","D":"daisy"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"bud"},{"question":"Which word does NOT belong with the others?","options":{"A":"rye","B":"sourdough","C":"pumpernickel","D":"loaf"},"answer_option":"A","answer":"rye"},{"question":"Which word does NOT belong with the others?","options":{"A":"wing","B":"fin","C":"beak","D":"rudder"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"beak"},{"question":"Which word does NOT belong with the others?","options":{"A":"core","B":"seeds","C":"pulp","D":"slice"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"slice"},{"question":"Which word does NOT belong with the others?","options":{"A":"peninsula","B":"island","C":"bay","D":"cape"},"answer_option":"C","answer":"bay"},{"question":"Which word does NOT belong with the others?","options":{"A":"fair","B":"just","C":"equitable","D":"favorable"},"answer_option":"D","answer":"favorable"},{"question":"Which word does NOT belong with the others?","options":{"A":"unique","B":"beautiful","C":"rare","D":"exceptional"},"answer_option":"B","answer":"beautiful"}],"verbal-reasoning":[{"question":"Vincent has a paper route. Each morning, he delivers 37 newspapers to customers in his neighborhood. It takes Vincent 50 minutes to deliver all the papers. If Vincent is sick or has other plans, his friend Thomas, who lives on the same street, will sometimes deliver the papers for him.","options":{"A":"VincentandThomasliveinthesameneighborhood.","B":"IttakesThomasmorethan50minutestodeliverthepapers.","C":"ItisdarkoutsidewhenVincentbeginshisdeliveries.","D":"Thomaswouldliketohavehisownpaperroute."},"answer_option":"A","answer":"VincentandThomasliveinthesameneighborhood."},{"question":"The Pacific yew is an evergreen tree that grows in the Pacific Northwest. The Pacific yew has a fleshy, poisonous fruit. Recently, taxol, a substance found in the bark of the Pacific yew, was discovered to be a promising new anticancer drug.","options":{"A":"Taxolispoisonouswhentakenbyhealthypeople.","B":"Taxolhascuredpeoplefromvariousdiseases.","C":"PeopleshouldnoteatthefruitofthePacificyew.","D":"ThePacificyewwasconsideredworthlessuntiltaxolwasdiscovered."},"answer_option":"C","answer":"PeopleshouldnoteatthefruitofthePacificyew."},{"question":"Erin is twelve years old. For three years, she has been asking her parents for a dog. Her parents have told her that they believe a dog would not be happy in an apartment, but they have given her permission to have a bird. Erin has not yet decided what kind of bird she would like to have.","options":{"A":"Erin'sparentslikebirdsbetterthantheylikedogs.","B":"Erindoesnotlikebirds.","C":"Erinandherparentsliveinanapartment.","D":"Erinandherparentswouldliketomove."},"answer_option":"C","answer":"Erinandherparentsliveinanapartment."},{"question":"Tim's commute never bothered him because there were always seats available on the train and he was able to spend his 40 minutes comfortably reading the newspaper or catching up on paperwork. Ever since the train schedule changed, the train has been extremely crowded, and by the time the doors open at his station, there isn't a seat to be found.","options":{"A":"Timwouldbebetterofftakingthebustowork.","B":"Tim'scommuteislesscomfortablesincethetrainschedulechanged.","C":"Manycommuterswillcomplainaboutthenewtrainschedule.","D":"Timwilllikelylookforanewjobclosertohome."},"answer_option":"B","answer":"Tim'scommuteislesscomfortablesincethetrainschedulechanged."},{"question":"When they heard news of the hurricane, Maya and Julian decided to change their vacation plans. Instead of traveling to the island beach resort, they booked a room at a fancy new spa in the mountains. Their plans were a bit more expensive, but they'd heard wonderful things about the spa and they were relieved to find availability on such short notice.","options":{"A":"MayaandJuliantakebeachvacationseveryyear.","B":"Thespaisoverpriced.","C":"Itisusuallynecessarytobookatleastsixmonthsinadvanceatthespa.","D":"MayaandJuliandecidedtochangetheirvacationplansbecauseofthehurricane."},"answer_option":"D","answer":"MayaandJuliandecidedtochangetheirvacationplansbecauseofthehurricane."},{"question":"Ten new television shows appeared during the month of September. Five of the shows were sitcoms, three were hour-long dramas, and two were news-magazine shows. By January, only seven of these new shows were still on the air. Five of the shows that remained were sitcoms.","options":{"A":"Onlyoneofthenews-magazineshowsremainedontheair.","B":"Onlyoneofthehour-longdramasremainedontheair.","C":"Atleastoneoftheshowsthatwascancelledwasanhour-longdrama.","D":"Televisionviewersprefersitcomsoverhour-longdramas."},"answer_option":"C","answer":"Atleastoneoftheshowsthatwascancelledwasanhour-longdrama."},{"question":"On weekends, Mr. Sanchez spends many hours working in his vegetable and flower gardens. Mrs. Sanchez spends her free time reading and listening to classical music. Both Mr. Sanchez and Mrs. Sanchez like to cook.","options":{"A":"Mr.Sanchezenjoysplantingandgrowingvegetables.","B":"Mr.Sanchezdoesnotlikeclassicalmusic.","C":"Mrs.SanchezcooksthevegetablesthatMr.Sanchezgrows.","D":"Mrs.Sanchezenjoysreadingnineteenthcenturynovels."},"answer_option":"A","answer":"Mr.Sanchezenjoysplantingandgrowingvegetables."},{"question":"Georgia is older than her cousin Marsha. Marsha's brother Bart is older than Georgia. When Marsha and Bart are visiting with Georgia, all three like to play a game of Monopoly. Marsha wins more often than Georgia does.","options":{"A":"WhenheplaysMonopolywithMarshaandGeorgia,Bartoftenloses.","B":"Ofthethree,Georgiaistheoldest.","C":"GeorgiahatestoloseatMonopoly.","D":"Ofthethree,Marshaistheyoungest."},"answer_option":"D","answer":"Ofthethree,Marshaistheyoungest."},{"question":"Sara lives in a large city on the East Coast. Her younger cousin Marlee lives in the Mid-west in a small town with fewer than 1,000 residents. Marlee has visited Sara several times during the past five years. In the same period of time, Sara has visited Marlee only once.","options":{"A":"MarleelikesSarabetterthanSaralikesMarlee.","B":"Sarathinkssmalltownsareboring.","C":"SaraisolderthanMarlee.","D":"MarleewantstomovetotheEastCoast."},"answer_option":"C","answer":"SaraisolderthanMarlee."}]}